<loc>
<IT>
La cartuccia 4,6 × 30 mm è una munizione utilizzata per la pistola semiautomatica Heckler &amp; Koch UCP e per la pistola mitragliatrice Heckler &amp; Koch MP7. 
La cartuccia 4,6 × 30 mm è più leggera rispetto ad altre di dimensioni simili e sviluppa un rinculo minore, aumentando però il potere d'arresto e la capacità di penetrazione di un giubbotto antiproiettile.
Esteticamente è caratterizzata da un bossolo a collo di bottiglia e da un proiettile a punta in acciaio rivestito in ottone. 
La cartuccia è stata sviluppata nel 2001 per essere una concorrente della 5,7 × 28 mm prodotta dalla Fabrique Nationale de Herstal.
Ad un confronto diretto la 4,6 × 30 mm sparata dall'MP7 risulta più veloce e con una maggiore gittata rispetto alla 5,7 × 28 mm sparata dalla P90.

https://it.wikipedia.org/wiki/4,6_%C3%97_30_mm
</IT>
<EN>
The HK 4.6×30mm (designated as the 4,6 × 30 by the C.I.P.) cartridge is a type of ammunition primarily used in the Heckler &amp; Koch MP7 Personal defense weapon (PDW). It is designed to minimize weight and recoil while increasing penetration of body armor. It features a bottlenecked case and a pointed, steel-core, brass-jacketed bullet. 
The 4.6×30mm cartridge was introduced in 1999. It was designed as a competitor to FN Herstal's 5.7×28mm cartridge.
Compared to standard intermediate cartridges one can carry more 4.6×30mm ammunition due to the lighter weight and relative small dimensions of the cartridge. Also, due to the lighter weight of the bullet, aiming in rapid fire is much easier as recoil depends much on the weight of the bullet. CRISAT testing shows that because of the smaller diameter and high projectile velocity of the round, body armor penetration is higher than that of traditional handgun projectiles.
A series of tests performed by NATO in the United Kingdom and France indicated that 5.7×28mm was a superior cartridge. The results of the NATO tests were analyzed by a group of experts from France, the United States, Canada, and the United Kingdom and the group's conclusion was that the 5.7×28mm was "undoubtedly" the more efficient cartridge.
Among other points, the NATO group cited superior effectiveness (27% greater) for the 5.7×28mm against unprotected targets and equal effectiveness against protected targets. It also cited less sensitivity to extreme temperatures for the 5.7×28mm and cited a greater potential risk of barrel erosion with the 4.6×30mm. In addition, the group pointed out that 5.7×28mm is close to the 5.56×45mm NATO by its design and manufacture process, allowing it to be manufactured on existing production lines.
The group also pointed out that 5.7×28mm weapons are more mature than 4.6×30mm weapons, and the 5.7×28mm FN Five-seven pistol was already in production at that time, while the 4.6×30mm Heckler &amp; Koch UCP pistol was still only an early concept. However, the German delegation and others rejected the NATO recommendation that 5.7×28mm be standardized, and as a result, the standardization process was indefinitely halted.

https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/HK_4.6%C3%9730mm
</EN>
<DE>
Die 4,6 × 30 mm ist die Patrone der MP7-Maschinenpistole von Heckler &amp; Koch. Sie wurde hauptsächlich entwickelt, um durch den kleineren Querschnitt des Geschosses den Durchschlag von moderner Körperpanzerung zu ermöglichen, der mit der Munition des Vorgängermodells MP5 nicht möglich war. 
Durch die Geometrie des Geschosses mit hinten liegendem Schwerpunkt überschlägt es sich beim Durchqueren von Weichteilgewebe und hinterlässt so einen größeren Wundkanal als sein eigentlicher Durchmesser, dadurch ist die Mannstoppwirkung als sehr gut anzusehen. Wegen ihres geringen Rückstoßes aufgrund ihres niedrigen Geschossgewichtes sind Waffen dieses Kalibers besonders bei Feuerstößen leichter im Ziel zu halten als größerkalibrige Waffen. Die Zielgenauigkeit wird überdies durch die Erhöhung der Geschossgeschwindigkeit und einer dadurch gestreckteren Flugbahn verbessert. Zudem kann der Schütze deutlich mehr der leichteren Munition mit sich führen und es passen mehr Patronen in das Magazin.
Munitionssorten:
    4,6 × 30 mm Action; Geschossgewicht 2,0 Gramm (für den polizeilichen Einsatz vorgesehen)
    4,6 × 30 mm Penetrator (DM11); Geschossgewicht 2,0 Gramm
    4,6 × 30 mm Ball (DM21); Geschossgewicht 2,6 Gramm

Die Verwendung innerhalb der Bundeswehr ist aus der Liste von Bundeswehrmunition ersichtlich.
Leistung:
    Durchschlag eines Gelatineblocks auf 50 m: 280 mm
    Energieabgabe auf eine beschusshemmende Weste auf 50 m (1,6 mm Titan + 20 Schichten Kevlar): 220 J
    Energieabgabe auf eine beschusshemmende Weste auf 100 m (1,6 mm Titan + 20 Schichten Kevlar): 115 J

https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/4,6_%C3%97_30_mm
</DE>
<ES>N/A</ES>
<FR>
Le 4,6 × 30 mm est une munition créée par Heckler &amp; Koch pour le H&amp;K MP7.
La création du PDW (arme de défense personnelle) FN P90 impliqua la création d'une nouvelle munition, la SS190 5,7 x 28 mm, destinée à corriger les défauts du 9 mm et des munitions classiques utilisées dans les pistolets mitrailleurs.
Selon la même approche la firme Heckler &amp; Koch créa une nouvelle munition, la 4,6 × 30 mm destinée au HK MP7. Il s'agit d'une munition de petit calibre au projectile léger et rapide dont la portée efficace est de 200 mètres et aux excellentes capacités de perforation. Cette munition bénéficie d'un excellent rapport entre le recul et l'énergie cinétique, ce qui permet de la mettre en œuvre dans une arme très légère.
Ses caractéristiques sont les suivantes :
    masse de la balle : 1,6 grammes ;
    vitesse à la bouche : 725 m/s (MP7) ;
    énergie à la bouche : 420 joules ;
    portée effective : 200 m (MP7).

https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/4,6_%C3%97_30_mm
</FR>
</loc>