<loc>
<IT>
La FN 5.7 × 28 millimetri (indicato come 5,7 × 28 dal CIP) è una cartuccia di piccolo calibro prodotto dalla FN Herstal in Belgio. Si tratta di una cartuccia a percussione centrale con collo di bottiglia di dimensioni simili al .22 WMR Winchester Magnum Rimfire (5,7 × 27 mm) e in modo simile anche al .22 Hornet o .22 K-Hornet. La munizione è stata sviluppata da zero dalla FN. Il 5,7 × 28 mm è stato sviluppato in concomitanza con l'arma di difesa personale FN P90 (PDW) e la pistola FN Five-seven, 
in risposta alle richieste della NATO di sostituire la cartuccia Parabellum 9 × 19 mm. Nel 2002 e 2003, la NATO ha condotto una serie di test con l'intenzione di standardizzare una cartuccia PDW in sostituzione della cartuccia Parabellum 9 × 19 mm. I test hanno confrontato i pregi relativi della cartuccia 5,7 × 28 mm e della cartuccia 4,6 × 30 mm, creata da Heckler & Koch come concorrente per il 5,7 × 28 mm. La NATO ha successivamente raccomandato la cartuccia da 5,7 × 28 mm, citando prestazioni superiori nei test, ma la delegazione tedesca ha obiettato e il processo di standardizzazione è stato poi bloccato.
Dal 2006, le armi da fuoco prodotte dalla FN con calibro 5,7 × 28 mm - l'arma di difesa personale P90 e la pistola Five-seven - erano in servizio nelle forze militari e di polizia in oltre 40 nazioni in tutto il mondo. Negli Stati Uniti, le armi da fuoco 5,7 × 28 mm sono attualmente utilizzate da numerose forze dell'ordine, compreso il servizio segreto statunitense.
Oltre ad essere utilizzata nelle armi FN P90 e FN Five-seven, la cartuccia 5.7 × 28 mm è stata successivamente utilizzata in una serie di altre armi, come le carabine AR-57 e FN PS90. Excel Arms ha sviluppato quattro armi con camera da fuoco per proiettili 5,7 × 28 mm e MasterPiece Arms produce tre diverse armi da fuoco calibro 5,7 × 28 mm. La stessa cartuccia 5.7 × 28 mm è prodotta in molte varianti, tra cui due delle quali - la SS195LF e la SS197SR - sono per uso civile. 

https://it.wikipedia.org/wiki/FN_5,7_%C3%97_28_mm
</IT>
<EN>
The FN 5.7×28mm (designated as the 5.7 × 28 by the C.I.P.) is a small-caliber, high-velocity, smokeless powder, rebated rim, bottlenecked centerfire cartridge designed for handgun and personal defense weapon (PDW) uses and manufactured by FN Herstal. It is similar in length to the .22 WMR (Winchester Magnum Rimfire)(5.7×27mm) and to some degree similar also to .22 Hornet or .22 K-Hornet. Unlike many new cartridges, it has no parent case; the complete package was developed from scratch by FN.
The 5.7×28mm was developed in conjunction with the FN P90 PDW and FN Five-seven pistol, in response to NATO requests for a replacement for the 9×19mm Parabellum cartridge. In 2002 and 2003, NATO conducted a series of tests with the intention of standardizing a PDW cartridge as a replacement for the 9×19mm Parabellum cartridge. The tests compared the relative merits of the 5.7×28mm cartridge and the 4.6×30mm cartridge, which was created by Heckler & Koch as a competitor to the 5.7×28mm. 
The NATO group subsequently recommended the 5.7×28mm cartridge, citing superior performance in testing, but the German delegation objected and the standardization process was indefinitely halted. By 2006, FN's 5.7×28mm firearms — the P90 PDW and Five-Seven pistol — were in service with military and police forces in over 40 nations throughout the world. In the United States, 5.7×28mm firearms are currently used by numerous law enforcement agencies, including the U.S. Secret Service.
In addition to being used in the FN P90 and FN Five-seven firearms, the 5.7×28mm cartridge has subsequently been used in a number of other weapons, such as the AR-57 and FN PS90 carbines. Excel Arms has developed four firearms chambered in 5.7×28mm, and MasterPiece Arms offers three different firearms in 5.7×28mm. In December, 2019, Ruger announced its new Ruger-57 semi-automatic pistol chambered in this cartridge. The 5.7×28mm cartridge itself is produced in a number of varieties, two of which — the SS195LF and SS197SR — are currently offered by FN to civilian shooters.
Americans define the shoulder angle at alpha/2 ≈ 35 degrees. The common rifling twist rate for this cartridge is 1:228.6 mm (1:9 in), 8 grooves, Ø lands = 5.53 mm, Ø grooves = 5.62 mm, land width = 1.63 mm and the recommended primer type is small rifle.
According to the official C.I.P. (Commission Internationale Permanente pour l'Epreuve des Armes à Feu Portatives) rulings, the 5.7×28mm can handle up to 3,450 bar (345 MPa; 50,000 psi) Pmax (the nominal maximum) piezo pressure. In C.I.P. regulated countries, every rifle cartridge combination has to be proofed at 125% of this maximum C.I.P. pressure to be certified for sale to consumers, referred to as "PE". This means that 5.7×28mm chambered arms in C.I.P. regulated countries are currently (2018) proof tested at 4,313 bar (431.3 MPa; 62,550 psi) PE piezo pressure.

https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/FN_5.7%C3%9728mm
</EN>
<DE>
Die Patrone 5,7 × 28 mm ist eine von der belgischen FN Herstal SA entwickelte Munition für Handfeuerwaffen. Diese ab etwa 1985 entwickelte Munition entspricht neuen taktischen Erfordernissen von Militär und Polizei und soll auf Entfernungen unter 200 m die Vorteile von Pistolen- und Gewehrmunition vereinen. Das sind vor allem geringer Rückstoß, hohe Magazinkapazität, hohe Durchschlagskraft gegen Schutzwesten und geringe Umfeldgefährdung. 
Das Geschoss der Patrone 9 × 19 mm durchschlägt einen 30 cm starken Block aus ballistischer Gelatine und gibt in ihm nur etwa 70 % seiner Energie an das Zielmedium ab. Dieses bedeutet eine geringe Aufhaltekraft (Mannstoppwirkung) und gleichzeitig eine Gefährdung für Personen und Objekte hinter dem Ziel. Das Geschoss der Patrone 5,7 × 28 mm gibt seine Energie auf 25 cm bis 30 cm vollständig ab. Es besitzt aus der P90 auf 200 m mit etwa 230 Joule nur zwei Drittel der Energie des 9-mm-Geschosses. Auf 800 m können die rund 90 Joule eines 9-mm-Geschosses noch tödlich wirken. Die Energie des 5,7-mm-Geschosses hat sich bis dahin auf 44 Joule verringert.
Zu den Vorteilen der neuen Munition gehört, dass sie mit 19,2 Nm/s nur die Hälfte vom Rückstoß des Kalibers 5,56 × 45 mm (39 Nm/s) und nur zwei Drittel des Rückstoßes der 9 × 19 mm (etwa 27 Nm/s) erzeugt, also wesentlich einfacher zu handhaben ist. Nach Presseberichten soll es durch den geringen Rückstoß möglich sein, die P90 einhändig im Dauerfeuermodus zu schießen. Auch soll sich das Schießen mit der Pistole FN Five-seveN ähnlich dem Schießen mit einer Kleinkaliberwaffe anfühlen.
Ein weiterer Vorteil ist die sehr flache Flugbahn. Auf 200 m Entfernung fällt das Geschoss nur um 16 cm. Ein 9-mm-Geschoss fällt auf diese Entfernung um mehr als 50 cm. Der Schütze muss also weniger Korrekturen an der Zieloptik vornehmen.

https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/5,7_%C3%97_28_mm
</DE>
<ES>
El 5,7 × 28 mm es un cartucho para pistola y subfusil. Fue específicamente diseñado por FN para su subfusil P90 y la pistola FN Five Seven.​ Surge a raíz de los requerimientos de la OTAN, para un cartucho capaz de perforar chalecos y cascos antibala, pero manejable en un arma corta.
El 5,7 x 28 es capaz de perforar un casco o chaleco antibalas hasta una distancia de unos cien metros,​ esto es la mitad o menos que la munición de fusil, pero también tiene la mitad de retroceso y es más pequeña, por lo que resulta manejable en un arma pequeña como una pistola o subfusil, y cubre de sobra la distancia a la que se suele disparar con estas armas.
Aunque el fabricante asegura que tiene un buen poder de detención, existen dudas al respecto a causa de una posible sobrepenetración del blanco,​ por lo que, mientras no esté contrastado en combate, es hoy un calibre minoritario, adoptado por unos pocos cuerpos de élite policiales.
El 5,7 x 28 es particularmente adecuado para unidades de intervención o rescate de rehenes, debido a un tipo de bala especial desarrollada para él, que tras atravesar un blanco duro, como un chaleco antibalas, se desestabiliza y gira, perdiendo toda capacidad perforante.​ Con esto se consigue evitar atravesar los blancos u otros obstáculos, como paredes, con el consiguiente peligro de herir a otras personas con estas balas perdidas, pero se retiene la capacidad de neutralizar a blancos provistos de protección como chalecos antibala.

https://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/5,7_%C3%97_28_mm
</ES>
<FR>
Le 5,7 × 28 mm est un calibre de cartouche développé par FN Herstal pour le FN P90 et le FN Five-seveN. Elle est destinée à engager des cibles jusqu'à 200 mètres et à perforer les protections individuelles comme les gilets pare-balles ou les casques. Sa légèreté lui permet de perdre rapidement son énergie lors d'un impact, ce qui limite les risques de surpénétration et les dommages collatéraux qu'ils impliquent.
ST Kinetics affirme que la conception de leur CPW permet une conversion de ce dernier en calibre 5,7 × 28 mm. (Lien Wikipedia Anglais : ST Kinetics CPW) 
Il s'agit d'une munition intermédiaire, plus légère et rapide qu'une munition d'arme de poing, qui ressemblerait à une 5,56 mm OTAN réduite. À titre de comparaison, elle est approximativement deux fois plus légère qu'une 9 mm Parabellum tout en étant plus courte qu'une 5,56 mm OTAN ce qui permet au FN P90 d'être doté d'un chargeur de 50 coups au lieu des 30 coups généralement observés sur les pistolets mitrailleurs et les fusils d'assaut.
Elle développe un faible recul soit 1,43 kgm/s contre environ 4 kgm/s pour le 5,56 mm OTAN et 2,8 kgm/s pour le 9 mm Parabellum. Ce faible recul permet un tir plus rapide et plus contrôlable, notamment en automatique. Il peut également être mis en œuvre dans des armes plus légères.
Son énergie cinétique est en revanche comparable à celle du 9mm parabellum (494 joules pour une munition standard tirée d'une arme de poing contre 529 joules pour le 5,7 × 28 mm standard) et nettement inférieure à celle d'une 5,56 mm OTAN (1767 joules).
Outre le FN P90, le 5,7 × 28 mm est également tiré depuis un pistolet semi-automatique, le Five-SeveN. Ce dernier tirant parti des qualités de la 5,7 × 28 mm est à la fois léger et doté d'un chargeur de grande capacité (20 coups). 

https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/5,7_%C3%97_28_mm
</FR>
</loc>