<loc>
<IT>N/A</IT>
<EN>
The 5mm Remington Rimfire Magnum or 5mm RFM is a bottlenecked rimfire cartridge introduced by Remington Arms Company in 1969. Remington chambered it in a pair of bolt-action rifles, the Model 591 and Model 592, but the round never became very popular, and the rifles were discontinued in 1974. About 52,000 rifles and 30,000 barrels for the T/C Contender pistol were sold during its brief production run. Remington discontinued the cartridge itself in 1982, leaving owners with no source of ammunition.
In 2008, the cartridge was reintroduced by Mexico's Aguila Ammunition in collaboration with Centurion Ordnance.
From 1982 until 2008, no ammunition manufacturers manufactured rounds for this cartridge. Some firearms manufacturers even created conversion kits to allow the existing 5 mm guns to shoot other more-common cartridges.
At the 2008 SHOT Show, Aguila Ammunition announced it would reintroduce the cartridge and begin commercial production of 5mm RFM ammunition. Until 2019, the cartridges were sold in the United States of America under the Centurion brand. In 2019, Aguila Ammunition announced the company now offered two 5mm RFM loads: one with a semi-jacketed hollow point bullet and a second with a full jacketed hollow point bullet. Both loads use a 30 grain projectile and have a muzzle velocity of 2,300 fps.
The 5 mm RRM offers higher velocity than the .22 WMR and more energy than both the .22 WMR and the later .17 HMR. It offers improved performance on small-game and for varmint hunting, along with excellent accuracy. The Aguila/Centurion 5mm Remington Magnum ammunition comes in two types: the original "white box" with a 30 gr dimpled jacketed soft point at 2,300 fps, as well as a varmint "yellow box" round with a 30 gr jacketed hollow point at 2,400 fps. Chronograph testing has shown that these rounds can actually run about 100 fps faster than claimed by Aguila.

https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/5mm_Remington_Rimfire_Magnum
</EN>
<DE>N/A</DE>
<ES>
El 5 mm Remington Magnum Rimfire es un cartucho de fuego anular agolletado introducido por Remington Arms Company en 1969, inicialmente para los rifles de cerrojo Remington Modelo 591 y Modelo 592, pero el cartucho nunca llegó a ser muy popular, y los rifles fueron descontinuados en 1973. La munición está siendo producido por Centurion / Águila en dos versiones. Más de 52.000 fusiles fueron vendidos durante su breve ciclo de producción.
Remington diseño una vaina agolletada similar a la del cartucho un poco más obsoleto .22 Winchester Magnum Rimfire, pero más fuerte para manejar la presión de los 5 mm a 33000 psi, creando así el primer cartucho agolletado moderno. Usa una bala de 5 mm (.204’’) que realmente mide 5.2 mm, que es la misma bala usada en el cartucho de fuego central más moderno .204 ruger.
Por un breve tiempo, Thompson Center Arms comercializó armas de fuego en 5 mm Rem Mag Rimfire; desde 1982 hasta 2008 no se fabricó este tipo de cartuchos, pero algunos fabricantes de armas de fuego crearon kits de conversión para que las armas 5 mm RMR dispararan cartuchos más comunes.
En la feria SHOT 2008, la empresa brasileña Taurus anunció la producción de un arma calibrada para el cartucho 5 mm RMR, coincidiendo con dicho anuncio, la empresa mexicana Águila Ammo anunció la producción de cartuchos 5 mm RMR a partir de 2008.
El 5 mm RMR ofrece mayor energía de impacto que cualquier .22 WMR o .17 HMR, ofrece un rendimiento mejorado para la cacería menor y la cacería varmint, además de una excelente precisión. La munición Águila/Centurion 5 mm RMR se ofrece en 2 versiones, ambas con bala de 30 granos: La original, encamisada, con punta hueca y suave, y la versión varmint encamisada y con punta hueca. Según el libro Cartridges of the world, la versión original fabricada por Remington, poseía una bala encamisada de punta hueca de 38 granos capaz de alcanzar una velocidad de 640 m/s.

https://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/5_mm_Remington_Magnum_Rimfire
</ES>
<FR>N/A</FR>
</loc>