<loc>
<IT>N/A</IT>
<EN>
The 6.5×25mm CBJ is a pistol cartridge designed for the CBJ-MS personal defence weapon. 
The 6.5×25mm CBJ has the same functional dimensions as the 9×19mm Parabellum and was designed to produce the same recoil and pressures to allow most 9 mm weapons to be converted to 6.5×25mm CBJ with a simple barrel change. Also, because the 6.5×25mm CBJ has the same overall dimensions as the 9×19mm Parabellum, it can be used in 9 mm magazines. The primary loading of the standard ball round fires a saboted tungsten 2 g (31 gr) 4.0 mm diameter sub-projectile, weighing 2.5 g (39 gr) with the sabot. 
It has a muzzle velocity of 730 m/s (2,400 ft/s) from a 120 mm (4.7 in) barrel with a muzzle energy of 533 J (393 ft x lb). From a 300 mm (12 in) barrel, it has a muzzle velocity of 900 m/s (3,000 ft/s) with a muzzle energy of 810 J (600 ft x lb), and has good armor penetration out to 400 meters. The standard saboted tungsten ball round can pierce 9 mm of armor plate and leave a 6 mm diameter entry hole when fired from a 300 mm length barrel. Against the same plate, both 5.56x45 NATO SS109 and 7.62x51 NATO Ball failed to penetrate. 
From a 300 mm barrel, the tungsten saboted round has the same trajectory as a 5.56 NATO from an M4 carbine and a velocity of 578 m/s (1,900 ft/s) at 300 m (328 yd), which will penetrate CRISAT armor. 6.5×25mm CBJ rounds are slower and heavier than both 5.7×28mm and 4.6x30mm.
There are several other 6.5×25mm CBJ bullets other than the sabot in full-caliber. Military rounds include a "spoon-tip" loading that increases the chance of the bullet to yaw on impact, and a cheap training version with a different core material. Police rounds include a 2.5 g (39 gr) high-energy-transfer round that can penetrate CRISAT armor at up to 50 meters, and a frangible round for training and situations requiring minimal barrier penetration. A subsonic armor-piercing round weighs 8 g (120 gr) for use with a suppressor.

https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/6.5%C3%9725_mm_CBJ
</EN>
<DE>N/A</DE>
<ES>N/A</ES>
<FR>N/A</FR>
</loc>