<loc>
<IT>
Dal 1930 è stata la cartuccia d'ordinanza per l'esercito Russo. Le pistole Russe meccanicamente simili alle Americane Browning e Colt erano le TT30 e TT33 costruite grossolanamente per risparmiare tempo e denaro risultarono ottime armi tanto che Cina e Ungheria ne produssero molti esemplari. Quelli Ungheresi furono gli unici a camerare la 9mm Luger.
La 7,62 Tokarev assomiglia alla 7,63 Mauser tanto che sia le munizioni che i dati di ricarica possono essere adottati per entrambe e camerate dalle stesse armi riducendo le dosi per le armi più datate.
La velocità media della munizione si attesta intorno ai 500 Mt/sec e quindi ottime energie per palle di soli 83 grani.

http://www.tiropratico.com/ammunition/pagine/762Tokarev.html
</IT>
<EN>
The 7.62×25mm Tokarev cartridge (designated as the 7,62 × 25 Tokarev by the C.I.P.) is a Russian rimless bottlenecked pistol cartridge widely used in former Soviet satellite states, and in China and Pakistan among other countries. The cartridge has since been replaced in most capacities by the 9×18mm Makarov in Russian service.
The cartridge is in principle an enhanced Russian version of the 7.63×25mm Mauser. The Russians produced a wide array of loadings for this cartridge for use in submachine guns.[citation needed] These include armor-piercing, tracer, and incendiary rounds. This cartridge has excellent penetration and can easily defeat lighter ballistic vests (NIJ level I and IIA) as well as some kevlar helmets, such as the American PASGT helmet. When fired from a carbine-length barrel the cartridge may penetrate NIJ level II, but is readily stopped by the current standard armor NIJ level IIIA.
Although most firearms chambered in this caliber were declared obsolete and removed from military inventories, some police and special forces units in Russia, Pakistan and (mainly) in China may still use it because of the large quantity of stored ammunition available.
There is a common misconception that 7.62 Tokarev surplus ammunition in the United States uses copper-coated mild steel bullets, and that this increases the chance of dangerous ricochets when fired at hard targets and can damage bullet traps often used on shooting ranges. While steel-core ammunition in 7.62×25 is available internationally, in the United States the importation of 7.62×25 cartridges loaded with copper-coated steel bullets is illegal; federal law defines these as armor-piercing pistol ammunition. The so-called steel bullets sold in the United States are generally 
lead-core bullets with copper-washed steel jackets, and these do not present a significantly greater risk of ricochet than a standard copper-jacketed projectile. In 2018, 7.62×25 ammunition was available for importation, from Romania, Czech Republic, Bulgaria, Serbia, and Russia. 
The pistol-fired bullet has various muzzle velocities around the range of 1,300 to 1,800 fps. A common velocity is around 442 metres per second (1,450 ft/s) with about 544 joules (401 ft⋅lbf) of energy. Given the wide disparity in ammunition manufactured in many different nations, ammunition is encountered that yields higher and lower velocities. Some newly manufactured ammunition intended for commercial use has a velocity of approximately 1,560 feet per second (480 m/s). Wolf Gold FMJ tops out at 1,720 feet per second (520 m/s) with 570 foot-pounds force (770 J) as does PPU ammunition. 
Some of this ammunition, such as the Wolf Gold and Sellier &amp; Bellot, use boxer primed brass cases that are reloadable. 

https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/7.62%C3%9725mm_Tokarev
</EN>
<DE>
Die 7,62 × 25 mm Tokarew M1930 ist eine sowjetische Pistolenpatrone. Sie wurde in den 1920er-Jahren zusammen mit der Selbstladepistole TT-30 entwickelt. 
In der Roten Armee wurden neben den Ordonnanzrevolvern Nagant M1895 auch größere Stückzahlen der Selbstladepistole Mauser C96 im Kaliber 7,63 × 25 mm verwendet. Dadurch war die Mauser-Munition in der Sowjetunion weit verbreitet. Da eigene Waffen- und Munitionsentwicklungen in der Sowjetunion ebenso wie im früheren Zarenreich auf zölligen Maßen beruhten, wurde die Patrone im Zuge der Entwicklung der ersten sowjetischen Selbstladepistole auf die gängigen Maschinen angepasst. Die alte Einheit Linie in der Feinmechanik entspricht 1/10 Zoll, somit ergeben drei Linien ein Kaliber von 7,62 mm. 

https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/7,62_%C3%97_25_mm_Tokarew_M1930
</DE>
<ES>
El 7,62 × 25 mm Tókarev es un cartucho abotellado para pistola usado ampliamente por la antigua Unión Soviética y sus aliados. 
El cartucho es en principio la versión soviética del 7,63x25mm Mauser. Son muy similares, de hecho, algunas armas pueden usar ambos cartuchos, pero de todas formas no es recomendable.
Los soviéticos produjeron una amplia gama de cargas para este cartucho para usar en subfusiles. Sin embargo, muchas armas recamaradas para este cartucho han sido declaradas obsoletas y retiradas de los inventarios, aunque algunas unidades de Rusia y (principalmente) en China lo mantienen en uso, en lugar del más popular 9 mm Makarov actualmente en uso.
El 7,62 Tókarev es usualmente más potente que la versión de Mauser, y puede dañar las armas recamaradas para el 7,63 mm Mauser. 
El cartucho tiene una velocidad promedio de alrededor de 400 m/s, y unos 600 julios de energía. La carga normal produce un fogonazo fuerte y luminoso cuando se dispara en pistolas, que sorprende a eventuales espectadores.
El arma más notable que usó este cartucho fue la pistola Tokarev TT-33, además de numerosos subfusiles, incluidos los PPD-40, PPSh-41, y PPS-43 soviéticos, y los Vz.24, Vz.26 (CZ-25) checoslovacos, K-50M, y PP-19 Bizon.
Medidas:
    Peso del cartucho=7,8 g
    Cuello=8,4 mm
    Hombro=9,4 mm
    Base=9,7 mm
    Culote=9,9 mm
    Vaina=25mm
    Largo total=34 mm
    Paso de estrías=1:250 mm

Prestaciones:
    Peso de la bala=5,8 g
    Velocidad=409 m/s
    Energía=488 julios


https://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/7,62_%C3%97_25_mm_Tokarev
</ES>
<FR>
La 7,62 x 25 mm TT (pour Toula-Tokarev) est une munition soviétique dérivé du 7,63 mm Mauser. Créée par l'ingénieur Tokarev, elle s'appelle 7,62 mm Modèle 1930 dans l'Armée rouge et était tirée dans des pistolets et des pistolets mitrailleurs. Elle possède un étui en forme de bouteille. La RPC et la Tchécoslovaquie en ont produit des variantes plus puissantes : les 7,62 mm Type P et 7,62 mm M48. Elle fut remplacée par la 9 mm Makarov. Elle est réputée pour traverser les gilets pare-balles. 
Données numériques et balistiques:
    Diamètre réel du projectile : 7,67 à 7,85 mm
    Masse du projectile : 5,5 grammes (86 grains)
    Longueur de l'étui : 24 à 25,5 mm
    Longueur de la cartouche : 34,18 à 35 mm
    Vitesse initiale
        Tokarev TT 33 : 420 m/s
        PPsh-41 : 475 m/s
    Énergie à la bouche :
        Tokarev TT 33 : 540 J
        PPsh-41 : 693 J
Avec l'évolution de la poudre et des ogives elle permet différente vitesse :
    Munition à tête creuse de 5.5 g (85 gr) avec une vitesse pouvant varier de 376 m/s à 482 m/s pour une énergie en joules comprise entre 390 et 655.
    Munition à ogive blindé de 5.5 g (85 gr) avec une vitesse pouvant varier de 409 m/s à 525 m/s pour une énergie en joules comprise entre 488 et 760.


https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/7,62_%C3%97_25_mm_TT
</FR>
</loc>