<loc>
<IT>
Unica cartuccia nel suo genere, nata per il revolver nagant 1895, che all'atto dello sparo ha il tamburo perfettamente accoppiato alla canna per evitarne le classiche sfuggite di gas, la 7,62x39 contiene al suo interno polvere e palla per far si ache allo sparo il bossolo possa fungere da guarnizione all'insieme meccanico dell'arma. Il sistema meccanico che accoppia il tamburo alla canna e il bossolo molto lungo (oltre la palla) permettono di sfruttare tutta la spinta dei gas di sparo. Il complicato sistema però non è esente da problemi specialmente in guerra, dove polvere e terra sono i principali nemici di questa arma. 
Per la ricarica esistono dies prodotti dalla CH. 

http://www.tiropratico.com/ammunition/pagine/7e62x38nagantrev.html
</IT>
<EN>
7.62×38mmR (also known as 7.62 mm Nagant and Cartridge, Type R) is a unique ammunition cartridge designed for use in the Russian Nagant M1895 revolver.
A small number of experimental submachine guns (e.g., Tokarev 1927), designed by Fedor Tokarev, were also produced in a 7.62 mm Nagant chambering. None, however, were accepted into Soviet service.
The projectile is seated below the mouth of the cartridge, with the cartridge crimp sitting just above the bullet. When fired in the Nagant revolver, the crimp expands into the forcing cone, completing the gas-seal and ostensibly increasing muzzle velocity by approximately 23 m/s (75 ft/s).
The 7.62 mm caliber was chosen, in part, to simplify the tooling used in barrel making and manufacture of projectiles — the Russian service rifle of the time, the Mosin–Nagant M1891 featured an identical bore diameter, being chambered for the 7.62×54mmR rifle cartridge.
Commercially manufactured and loaded 7.62×38R cartridges are no longer difficult to find. Most commercially loaded ammunition for the Nagant, including Fiocchi and the "СССР"-marked yellow box imports, are target ammunition, and do not have great stopping power. The low power of these rounds has given the Nagant a reputation as an underpowered sidearm. 
However, the original military ball cartridges fired bullets in the 6.5 g (100 grains) range at up to 330 m/s (1,100 ft/s), making them close to the .32-20 Winchester and .32 H&amp;R Magnum in power. 
One advantage of the round, if proper brass can be found, is that it leaves the chambers totally clean, and there is no need to scrape lead and powder residue out. 

https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/7.62%C3%9738mmR
</EN>
<DE>
Die Patrone 7,62 × 38 mm Nagant war eine Revolvermunition, die bereits 1890 für den Nagant-Revolver entwickelt wurde. 
Die 7,62 Nagant war in ihrer Form einzigartig, denn der belgische Konstrukteur Léon Nagant entwarf sie speziell für den Einsatz in einem gasdichten Revolver. Als Basis diente ihm die Patrone 8 × 41 mm R. Zu diesem Zweck kombinierte er den Abzug mit einem Mechanismus, der die Trommel vor der Schussabgabe an den Laufansatz presste. Das Geschoss ragte nicht aus der Patrone heraus, sondern wurde völlig von der Hülse umschlossen. 
Der Patronenrand war leicht nach innen gebördelt; brach der Schuss, wurde der Rand nach außen gewölbt und versiegelte somit den Trommelspalt zusätzlich. Damit war es möglich, die Waffe mit einem Schalldämpfer auszurüsten, was mit konventionellen Revolvern wegen deren Trommelspalt nicht sinnvoll ist. Der Gasdruck wurde durch die Technik etwas erhöht, die Geschossenergie blieb gleichwohl gering. Die Patrone war im Gegensatz zu anderer Revolvermunition konisch, denn der Nagant hatte keine leicht zugängliche Trommel. 
Die Patrone wurde zusammen mit dem Nagant-Revolver in Staaten wie Belgien, Schweden und Polen eingeführt. Besondere Verbreitung fanden Waffe und Munition jedoch in Russland, wo sie 1895 Ordonnanz wurden. Nach der Oktoberrevolution übernahm sie auch die Rote Armee in ihre Ausrüstung, wo sie bis zum Ende des Zweiten Weltkrieges verblieb. Erst danach standen moderne Pistolen in ausreichenden Stückzahlen zur Verfügung. Trotzdem blieb die Waffe und ihre Munition bis Anfang der 1980er-Jahre bei Wach- und Werkschutzeinheiten der UdSSR im Dienst. 

https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/7,62_%C3%97_38_mm_Nagant
</DE>
<ES>N/A</ES>
<FR>
Le 7,62 × 38 mm Nagant (en langue russe : :7,62×38 мм Наган) est un calibre russe conçu pour être tirée par le revolver belgo-russe Nagant 95. La cartouche présente la particularité de l'enserrement complet de la balle dans la douille. Cette cartouche à bourrelet a été fabriquée de 1895 à 1945 par les grandes cartoucheries européennes. Aujourd'hui elle n'est produite qu'en Italie avec une munition aux performance légèrement inférieures à celles de l'Armée russe. Sa désignation métrique est 7,62 x 38 R, synonymes : 7,62 mm Nagant russe, Patrone 2602 (r), GR 684. 
Données balistiques:
    Cartouches militaires russes
        Vitesse initiale : 295 m/s
        Energie cinétique initiale : 305 joules
    Cartouches commerciales italiennes (fabrication années 2000)
        Vitesse initiale : 260 m/s
        Energie cinétique à 10 m de la bouche : 217 joules


https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/7,62_%C3%97_38_mm_Nagant
</FR>
</loc>