<loc>
<IT>
La cartuccia 7,63 mm Mauser è in realtà l'evoluzione della 7,65 × 25 mm Borchardt. Per la precisione, la pistola semiautomatica Borchardt C-93 fu la prima semiautomatica moderna e da essa derivò la famosa pistola Luger P08. Mauser non fece altro che riadattare la cartuccia alla sua arma, la C96. Inoltre aumentò notevolmente la carica di lancio portando il proiettile alla velocità di 450 m/s. La cartuccia impiega un bossolo a collo di bottiglia e fondello tipo rimless. 

https://it.wikipedia.org/wiki/7,63_%C3%97_25_mm_Mauser
</IT>
<EN>
The 7.63×25mm Mauser (.30 Mauser Automatic) round was the original cartridge for the Mauser C96 service pistol. This cartridge headspaces on the shoulder of the case. It later served as the basis for the 7.62mm Tokarev cartridge commonly used in Soviet and Eastern Bloc weapons. 
This cartridge was based on the 7.65mm Borchardt of 1893, the most successful semi-automatic pistol cartridge in production at the time, due to its use in the Borchardt C-93 pistol. The 7.63mm Mauser is sometimes confused with the later 7.65mm Parabellum (.30 Parabellum), also a bottlenecked pistol cartridge used in the Luger Parabellum. It has been manufactured from the 1890s until the present by various ammunition manufacturers. 
Firearms chambered for the 7.63mm Mauser cartridge include the pistol for which it was designed, the Mauser C96 in all variants and copies, the Astra Model 900 and variants, the Schwarzlose Model 1898, the 1911-pattern Star models A and M, and a handful of pre-World War II submachine guns such as the Swiss Bergmann M/20 exported to China and Japan and SIG's unique MKMO. 
Several Soviet pistol and submachine gun developments of the late 1920s were designed to use the 7.63mm Mauser cartridge. The Mauser cartridge thus became the basis for the 7.62mm Tokarev as officially adopted by the Soviet Union. Although the case dimensions of the two cartridges are nearly identical, the 7.62mm Tokarev has a stronger powder charge and is generally not suited for use in Mauser C96 pistols or other firearms chambered for 7.63mm Mauser. However, the slightly less powerful 7.63mm Mauser could be used safely in firearms chambered for the more powerful 7.62mm Tokarev. 
This became important later during World War II on the Eastern Front when the Germans began using captured 7.62×25mm weapons, notably the PPSh-41 and PPS, and fed them with 7.63mm Mauser rounds. During the Finnish-Soviet Winter War and World War II, the cartridge was issued by Finnish and German forces for use in captured Soviet submachine guns, due to its inherent substitutability for the Soviet 7.62×25mm round. According to Finnish military archives, the Finnish Army ordered one million rounds of 7.63mm Mauser from FN for this purpose.

https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/7.63%C3%9725mm_Mauser
</EN>
<DE>
Die Patrone 7,63 × 25 mm wurde speziell für die ab 1896 gebaute Mauser-Selbstladepistole C96 entwickelt. 
Die Grundlage der Munition war die Patrone 7,65 × 25 mm Borchardt. Die Hülsenform (Flaschenhalshülse) war gleich, im Vergleich zur Borchardt-Patrone wurde die Treibladung jedoch derart verstärkt, dass die neue Munition in der Borchardt-Pistole nicht mehr verwendet werden konnte. Die Flugbahn geriet zwar sehr gestreckt, jedoch mangelte es dem Projektil trotz hoher kinetischer Energie an Mannstoppwirkung, da das Kaliber zu klein war.
Gleichwohl gehörte die 7,63-mm-Mauserpatrone bis zur Entwicklung der .357 Magnum zur stärksten Munition für Kurzwaffen. In der Sowjetunion wurde die Mauserpatrone in den 1930er-Jahren zur 7,62 × 25 mm TT modifiziert und für die neue Tokarew TT-30 (später TT-33) verwendet. Die 7,63er-Patrone konnte in den Tokarew-Pistolen verschossen werden, was aber durch den höheren Gasdruck der Mauserpatrone riskant war.
Aus der 7,63 × 25 mm wurde 1904 die stärkere 9 × 25 mm Mauser abgeleitet. 

https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/7,63_%C3%97_25_mm
</DE>
<ES>
El 7,63 × 25 mm Mauser, también conocido como .30 Mauser Automatic, es un cartucho de pistola, fue la munición original de la Mauser C96. La base de este cartucho fue el cartucho 7,65 × 25 mm Borchardt de 1893, el único cartucho de pistola automática exitoso en aquel entonces. El 7,63 mm Mauser es confundido a veces con el 7,65 × 21 mm Parabellum (.30 Luger), otro cartucho de pistola abotellado.
El 7,63 mm Mauser fue la base del cartucho 7,62 × 25 mm Tokarev adoptado por la Unión Soviética. A pesar de que las dimensiones de los dos cartuchos son casi idénticas, el 7,62 Tokarev tiene una carga de pólvora más potente, y no es apto para ser usado en pistolas C-96 u otras armas recamaradas para su cartucho. Sin embargo, el 7,63 mm Mauser puede usarse en armas recamaradas para el 7,62 mm Tokarev.
Entre las armas recamaradas para el cartucho 7,63 mm Mauser estaba la Mauser C96 con sus variantes y copias, la Astra Modelo 900 y sus variantes, así como los subfusiles anteriores a la Segunda Guerra Mundial como el SIG Modelo 1920 exportado a China y Japón, la SIG MKMO, y el MP34 alemán (para exportación, la mayoría se fabricó en 9 x 19 mm Parabellum)
Durante la Guerra de Invierno y la Guerra de Continuación entre Finlandia y la Unión Soviética, el cartucho fue producido para las fuerzas finesas y alemanas para usar los subfusiles soviéticos capturados, aprovechando que podía reemplazar al cartucho 7,62 x 25. Según los archivos militares de Finlandia, el ejército finés ordenó un millón de cartuchos 7,63 Mauser a la FN para este propósito.
El 7,63 mm Mauser es producido actualmente por las compañías Fiocchi Munizioni, Sellier &amp; Bellot y Prvi Partizan. 

https://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/7,63_%C3%97_25_mm_Mauser
</ES>
<FR>
Le 7,63 × 25 mm Mauser fut, dès l'an 1896, la première cartouche à être utilisée comme munition du pistolet Mauser C96. 
Lors de la conception du pistolet Mauser C96, le choix de la munition s'est naturellement porté sur une des cartouches les plus récentes, celle utilisée par le pistolet Borchardt. Cette cartouche, connue sous le nom de 7,65 mm Borchardt, s'est révélée insuffisamment puissante pour le robuste mécanisme du Mauser C96. Ses concepteurs ont donc augmenté très sensiblement les performances de celle-ci, créant une cartouche nouvelle sous la référence 7,63 × 25 mm Mauser. Aux États-Unis, elle est connue sous le nom de .30 Mauser (trente centièmes de pouce). 
Ayant la forme d'une bouteille (forme caractéristique pour la fin du XIXe siècle) cette munition restera la plus rapide, pour une arme de poing, jusqu'à l'arrivée du .357 Magnum vers 1935. Sa vitesse à la bouche élevée (430 m/s) lui confère une trajectoire très plate. Cette propriété explique la graduation de la planchette de hausse du Mauser allant jusqu'à 1 000 mètres, valeur qui demeure très optimiste pour une arme de poing. Néanmoins, l'utilisation de l'étui-crosse du Mauser C96, le transformant en petite carabine, 
permet des tirs à des distances bien supérieures à celles normalement dévolues aux autres pistolets (jusqu'à 300 mètres). La force de pénétration de cette munition est importante. Les « gangsters » de Chicago des années trente s'en serviront pour percer les blindages des automobiles de leurs concurrents. La cartouche de 7,63 Mauser sera finalement copiée vers 1930 en Union soviétique et poursuivra sa carrière sous le nom de 7,62 Tokarev (voir Tokarev TT 33). 
Si les deux munitions sont généralement interchangeables, il est souhaitable de vérifier les données de chargement ou de rechargement avant utilisation dans une arme comme le C96 qui peut avoir déjà vécu beaucoup d'aventures… 

https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/7,63_%C3%97_25_mm_Mauser
</FR>
</loc>