<loc>
<IT>N/A</IT>
<EN>
The 7.65×20mm Longue (also known as 7.65mm French Longue, 7.65 mm Long, 7.65mm MAS, 7.65×20mm, 7.65L and .30-18 Auto for use in the Pedersen Device) was a straight, rimless cartridge used in the French Modèle 1935 pistol, as well as the MAS-38 submachine gun. 
The cartridge was developed for the United States and secretly produced in quantity too late for its intended use during World War I. The United States scrapped the weapons built for the cartridge between the world wars. France adopted weapons for the cartridge and those weapons saw combat use; so the cartridge is best known by its French name.
The French military were introduced to the cartridge when the US demonstrated the Pedersen device after the end of World War I in Le Mans and again when John Browning exhibited a carbine in the same caliber in 1920. The US .30 Pedersen cartridge (Auto Pistol Ball Cartridge caliber .30 Model of 1918 or .30-18 Automatic) 
used in the Pedersen device was the basis for the 7.65×20mm Longue. The cartridge dimensions were identical, although Pedersen device cartridges were loaded with a slightly heavier 80 grains (5.2 g) bullet which achieved a velocity of 1,300 feet (400 m) per second in the longer barrel of M1903 Springfield rifles.
Remington Arms produced 65 million cartridges for the Pedersen device between 1918 and 1920. French 7.65×20mm Longue ammunition was manufactured in quantity from approximately 1935 to 1960. In 2019, Steineil began producing 7.65X20mm Longue, making new ammunition available again.

https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/7.65%C3%9720mm_Longue
</EN>
<DE>
Die Patrone 7,65 × 20 mm ist eine französische Pistolenpatrone. Sie wurde 1925 in Frankreich entwickelt und auch nur dort produziert. 
Die Patrone wurde als Weiterentwicklung der Browningpatrone 7,65 × 17 mm für eine neue Armeepistole 1925 entworfen. Diese Pistole wurde jedoch nicht in die Bewaffnung der französischen Armee aufgenommen, so dass die Munition erst 1935 mit der Selbstladepistole Modell 1935A als 7,65 mm longue M 1935 eingeführt wurde. 
Die Munition war an der unteren Leistungsgrenze für militärische Zwecke. Neben der Petter-Pistole wurde sie auch in der MPi MAS 1938 verwendet.
Nach 1945 wurde sie durch die Patrone 9 × 19 mm ersetzt. 

https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/7,65_%C3%97_20_mm
</DE>
<ES>N/A</ES>
<FR>
La munition 7,65 × 20 mm Long aussi désigné 7,65 MAS et 7,65 French outre-Atlantique pour pistolet et pistolet-mitrailleur fut règlementaire dans l'Armée française, la gendarmerie nationale et la police nationale. Son appellation métrique est 7,65 × 20 mm. Elle fut fabriquée en France, en Tchécoslovaquie et aux États-Unis de 1920 à 1960 environ. 
Données numériques:
    Diamètre réel maximal du projectile : 7,82 mm.
    Longueur de l'étui : 20 mm.
    Longueur cartouche : 30,20 mm.
    Vitesse : 340 m/s.
    Énergie : 300 joules.
	
https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/7,65_%C3%97_20_mm_Long
</FR>
</loc>