<loc>
<IT>N/A</IT>
<EN>
It was used in the Type A and B Nambus, Type 14 Nambu and Type 94 pistols, Tokyo Arsenal Model 1927, Type II machine pistol, Hino Komuro M1908 Pistol and the Type 100 submachine gun. It uses 8.2 mm (.320") bullets. Power is relatively low, with military loads developing about 280 J (200 foot·pounds), comparable to the American .380 ACP and substantially weaker than contemporary military cartridges such as 9×19mm Parabellum, .45 ACP, and 7.62×25mm Tokarev.
Like almost all of the Imperial Japanese weapon designs of that era, production of 8 mm Nambu ammunition ceased after the end of World War II, as the weapons that fired it were removed from service. Some small-scale production (primarily using remanufactured brass) has occurred in the United States, but handloading is more common among owners of 8 mm Nambu pistols. New manufactured brass and copper plated lead bullets (.320") are now available through HDS. 
Reloadable cases might be formed from .40" S&amp;W, but this would require swaging the case heads down from .424" to .403" in a hydraulic press. A regular reloading press would quickly be ruined by this sort of operation. The Japanese Army cartridges in 8 mm Nambu have no markings on the headstamp unlike the Japanese Navy cartridges. 

https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/8%C3%9722mm_Nambu
</EN>
<DE>
Die Patrone 8 × 22 mm Nambu wurde von Oberst Kijirō Nambu für die gleichnamige Pistole konstruiert und 1914 in die kaiserlich japanische Armee eingeführt. Die Waffe wurde im Laufe der Zeit konstruktiv angepasst, die Patrone aber blieb unverändert.
Waffe und Munition wurden nur in Japan hergestellt. Die Produktion wurde mit der Niederlage Japans im Zweiten Weltkrieg eingestellt. 

https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/8_×_22_mm_Nambu
</DE>
<ES>
El 8×22mm Nambu es un cartucho para pistola, sin pestaña y con cuello de botella introducido en Japón en 1904. Fue utilizado en las pistolas Nambu Tipo A y B, Nambu Tipo 14 y Tipo 94; Tokyo Arsenal Modelo 1927, pistola ametralladora Tipo 2, Hino Komuro M1908 y el subfusil Tipo 100. Utiliza balas 8,2 mm (.320"). La potencia es relativamente baja, con cargas militares que desarrollan alrededor de 280 J (200 pies·libras), comparable al americano 
.380 ACP y sustancialmente más débil que los cartuchos militares contemporáneos como los 9 × 19 mm Parabellum , .45 ACP, y 7.62 × 25 mm Tokarev. Como el destino de casi todos los diseños de armas japonesas Imperiales contemporáneas, la producción del 8 mm Nambu cesó luego de finalizada la Segunda Guerra mundial, cuando las armas que lo disparaban fueron retiradas del servicio. Mientras una producción a pequeña escala (principalmente utilizando latón remanufacturado) 
ha ocurrido en los Estados Unidos, la recarga manual es común entre dueños de pistolas 8 mm Nambu. Los cartuchos del Ejército Japonés en 8 mm Nambu no tienen marcas en el culote, a diferencia de los cartuchos de la Marina Japonesa. 

https://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/8_%C3%97_22_mm_Nambu
</ES>
<FR>N/A</FR>
</loc>