<loc>
<IT>N/A</IT>
<EN>
9mm P.A. (Pistole Automatik, German for "automatic pistol"), 9×22mm or 9mm P.A.K. (Pistole Automatik Knall, "automatic blank pistol") is a firearm cartridge for a non-lethal gas pistol noisemaking gun. Caliber 9mm P.A. includes various blank, gas or rubber ammunitions made for different use.
9mm P.A. Blank has also been used for theatrical purposes, including as a modification to muzzle-loading firearms, allowing early-modern muskets and the like to be fired on-stage without the actors learning the complex steps of loading with loose powder.

Each of the 9mm P.A. cartridge variants are distinguished by a proper color: green, yellow, blue, red, etc.
9mm P.A. ammunitions can be used for different purposes depending on the legislation, these include military training, cinema props, self-defense (rubber bullets can be used only in Russia), dog training, historical reenactment, holiday or new year celebration (mostly in Turkey, Germany and Italy). Colombia S.A. and other South American countries also allow the use of rubber bullets for self Defense.
The use of this ammunition also depends on the 9mm P.A. gun's barrel which can be of three kinds depending on the country's own gun legislation that can be more or less restrictive.
Fully obstructed barrel are called "top firing" (or "top venting") for they have a long hole on the barrel's top while the muzzle is closed. "Front firing" (or "front venting") guns have a semi-obstructed barrel that allows for a flame, smoke or tear gas to be ejected out of the muzzle. According to American federal laws, both "front firing" and "top firing" new guns must be identified by a red plastic tip fixed on the muzzle.
Russia's guns legislation allows civilians self-defence hence local 9mm P.A. guns can have a clear barrel that can fire non-lethal rubber bullets. 

These blank cartridges can also be used to fire pyrotecnics (single or multi-shots) or non-lethal "self-gomm" rubber bullets with the proper adaptor attached to the barrel.
9mm P.A. Knall
Cal. 9mm P.A. Blank (a.k.a. «9mm P.A.K.») are blank cartridges made for semi-automatic pistols.
    GREEN. Standard "Blank" cartridges.
    YELLOW. "Flash Defense" blank cartridges producing a longer flame at the end of the barrel.
9mm R./9mm R. NC
	Semi-automatic 9mm P.A. ammunitions are not compatible with gas pistols 9mm R. (.380) or 9mm R NC designed for blank-firing revolvers. 

Tear gas
9mm P.A. CS
Cal. 9mm P.A. CS are cartridges loaded with tear gas CS (80 mg).
    YELLOW. "CS" cartridges are loaded with 80mg.

9mm P.A. CN
Cal. 9mm P.A. CN are cartridges loaded with tear gas CN (160 or 220 mg).
    BLUE. "CN" cartridges are loaded with 160mg.
    PURPLE. "Supra CN" cartridges are loaded with 220mg.

9mm P.A. PV
Cal. 9mm P.A. PV are cartridges loaded with pepper spray (20, 30 or 45 mg) and intended to be used for self-defense against dangerous animals.
    BROWN. "Pepper" cartridges are loaded with 20mg.
    RED. "Pepper flash" cartridges are loaded with 30mg.
    RED. "Extra strong" cartridges are loaded with 45mg.

Rubber bullets
	Front-firing 9mm P.A. pistols can shoot 18 mm non-lethal self-gomm rubber bullets through an adapter attached to the barrel's end. Unlike 9mm P.A. rubber bullets, these 18 mm rubber bullets are manually loaded by the muzzle. 
9mm P.A. Tehkrim
Cal. 9mm P.A. Tehkrim. Russian ammunitions maker Tehkrim manufactures non-lethal rubber bullets (0.68g) chambered in 9mm P.A. This particular ammunition cannot be used in standard 9mm P.A. blank firing pistols sold in Europe and America for they use semi-obstructed (front firing) or fully obstructed (top-firing) barrels.
    RED.
9mm P.A. PP9RP
Cal. 9mm P.A. PP9RP. Russian ammunition with a rubber bullet (standard, sport or magnum) similar to Tehkrims.
    BLACK.
	
(https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/9mm_P.A.K.)
</EN>
<DE>
9 mm P.A.K. (Pistole Automatik Knall, offiziell 9 mm PA Blanc) ist ein Kaliber von Platz- und Reizstoffpatronen für Selbstladepistolen, insbesondere für Schreckschuss- oder Startpistolen. 
Kartuschen (ugs. Platzpatronen) in diesem Kaliber sind zylindrisch. Sie werden aus Messing oder Stahl hergestellt. Am unteren Rand befindet sich eine Auszieherrille (auch Gürtel genannt). In diese greift die Auszieherkralle der Pistole hinein, um die verschossene Kartusche aus dem Patronenlager zu befördern. Die Ladung der Kartuschen besteht in den meisten Fällen aus Cellulosenitrat. Dieses Pulver erzeugt einen lauten "hellen" Knall. Früher wurde auch Schwarzpulver verwendet, welches ein "dumpfes" Knallgeräusch erzeugt. Schwarzpulver kann das Abschussgerät beschädigen, da es unsauber verbrennt. 
Beim Verbrennen bleiben hygroskopische Metallsalze als Verbrennungsprodukt zurück. Platzpatronen haben eine grüne Innenhülse aus Kunststoff, welche beim Verschießen aufplatzen. Sie dienen bei Schreckschusswaffen zur Erzeugung eines Knalls, sowie zur Zündung von Signalmunition und sonstiger Pyrotechnik. Daneben existieren Kartuschen mit Blitzknallsatz. Diese erzeugen ein vergleichsweise großes und helles Mündungsfeuer. Diese sind mit einer hellblauen Kappe gekennzeichnet. Bei sehr alten Kartuschen können unterschiedlichste Farbmarkierungen vorkommen, deren Bedeutung nicht immer eindeutig zugeordnet werden kann.

Es werden verschiedene Patronenarten verwendet.
Gaspatronen
	Im gleichen Kaliber existieren auch Patronen, mit denen Reizgase wie CN-Chloracetophenon und CS-2-Chlorbenzylidenmalonsäuredinitril (z. B. in Notwehr) verschossen werden können. Diese Gase bewirken bei Kontakt mit den Augen oder den Schleimhäuten ein starkes Brennen sowie einen kräftigen Tränenfluss. Patronen mit dieser Füllung sind an ihrer gelben Kappe zu erkennen. 
Pfefferpatronen
	Eine weitere Patronenvariante ist mit künstlichen Capsaicin (Nonivamid) oder Pfefferextrakten gefüllt. Während CN- oder CS-Gas bei Personen unter Alkohol- oder Drogeneinfluss nicht immer die volle Wirkung zeigt, besteht bei Pfeffer diese Einschränkung weniger. Diese Patronen weisen eine rote (bzw. früher braune) Kappe auf. 

(https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/9_mm_P.A.K.)
</DE>
<ES>N/A</ES>
<FR>N/A</FR>
</loc>