<loc>
<IT>
La cartuccia calibro 9mm Makarov (N.B. questa cartuccia è nota in diverse fonti bibliografiche come 9mm Stechkin, 9mm sovietico, 9mm Modello 59 o con la denominazione metrica di 9x18mm) venne realizzata nell'ex Unione Sovietica poco dopo la fine della seconda guerra mondiale. Nella mente del suo ideatore, si trattava di una cartuccia destinata ad essere camerata in pistole, mitra, pistole mitragliatrici e, più in generale, ad impieghi essenzialmente militari. 
Un tempo circondata da un profondo alone di mistero, questa cartuccia ha cominciato ad essere maggiormente conosciuta in occidente dopo la fine della c.d  Guerra Fredda. Parallelamente, hanno cominciato a diffondersi in occidente anche alcune armi camerate per il 9mm Makarov, tra le quali la più famosa è certamente la c.d. "PM" o Pistolet Makarova, nota anche come "Pistola M" o "pistola tipo 59". Morfologicamente parlando, questa pistola è molto SIMILE alla Walther PP e, 
nonostante quello che molti sono portati a credere, si tratta di un'arma di OTTIMA qualità. Ciò è vero, a maggior ragione, con particolare riferimento agli esemplari prodotti nella ex DDR o nell'ex URSS.

https://www.grurifrasca.net/oldsite/Sito/Ricarica/pistole/9makarov.html
</IT>
<EN>
The 9×18mm Makarov (designated 9mm Makarov by the C.I.P. and often called 9×18mm PM) is a Russian pistol and submachine gun cartridge. During the latter half of the 20th century it was a standard military pistol cartridge of the Soviet Union and the Eastern Bloc, analogous to the 9×19mm Parabellum in NATO and Western military use. 
During the Second World War and the early Cold War, the 7.62×25mm Tokarev was the standard automatic pistol round for the Soviet Union and its satellites in Eastern Europe. This ammunition is still in use by many of these countries today. During the war the Red Army had found a few shortcomings of its 7.62mm TT-33 pistol, one of which was a tendency to inadvertently drop its magazine while in operation. The army wanted something that was lighter, with a heel release instead of a button and different ammunition. 
A direct blowback design was chosen for the pistol's operation, since it would be quick and cheap to manufacture, as well as accurate, due to the fixed-barrel design allowed by direct blowback operation. 
The 9×18mm round was designed by Boris V. Semin in 1946, and was intended to be a relatively powerful round with modest bolt thrust that could function safely in a simple or direct blowback pistol. It was based on the 9×18mm Ultra cartridge which was developed in 1936 by Gustav Genschow & Co. for the German Luftwaffe, as a more powerful alternative to the 9×17mm used in the Walther PP, also a simple blowback design pistol. Nikolay Fyodorovich Makarov went on to design the Makarov PM pistol around the 9×18mm round in 1947. 
In 1951 both the Makarov pistol and the round were accepted by the Soviet Army, hence the round became commonly known thereafter as the Makarov as well (it is not its official designation).Calibers in the USSR were measured between the lands in the rifling and not the grooves. As such, 9×18mm Makarov ammunition uses a larger diameter bullet than other common 9 mm rounds, measuring 9.27 mm (0.365 in), compared with 9.017 mm (0.355 in) for 9×19mm Parabellum. 
After its introduction in 1951, the 9×18mm Makarov round spread throughout the militaries of Eastern Bloc nations. 

https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/9%C3%9718mm_Makarov
</EN>
<DE>
Die Patrone 9 × 18 mm (oder auch als 9 mm Makarow oder 9 × 18 PM bekannt) war die Standard-Pistolenmunition der Sowjetarmee und der übrigen Streitkräfte des Warschauer Paktes. In den Nachfolgestaaten der Sowjetunion ist die Patrone nach wie vor weit verbreitet. 
Gegen Ende des Zweiten Weltkrieges suchte die Führung der Sowjetarmee nach Ersatz für die betagte Pistole Tokarew TT-33. Bei der Neuentwicklung der Pistole orientierte man sich an der deutschen Walther PP, die mit einfachem Masseverschluss (unverriegelter Rückstoßlader) auskam. Dementsprechend wurde auch keine starke Patrone erforderlich; dies hätte den Verschlussmechanismus überfordert.

Die Tokarew-Munition hatte eine deutlich höhere Geschossenergie und eine gestrecktere Flugbahn, denn sie war auch für den Einsatz in Maschinenpistolen vorgesehen. Mit der Ausmusterung der MPis und der Umstellung der Bewaffnung auf Sturmgewehre bestand dafür jedoch keine Notwendigkeit mehr. Die neue Patrone sollte bei geringerem Rückstoß eine größere Aufhaltekraft entfalten, die Reichweite war nachrangig. 
In jüngerer Vergangenheit erachtete das russische Militär die Energie der Geschosse jedoch als zu schwach und führte im Jahr 2003 mit der Jarygin PJa eine Pistole im Kaliber 9 × 19 mm ein. 

https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/9_%C3%97_18_mm
</DE>
<ES>
El 9 × 18 mm Makárov (a veces llamado 9 × 18 mm PM) es un cartucho soviético para pistolas y subfusiles. Fue la alternativa del Bloque del Este al 9 x 19 mm Parabellum. 
El 9 x 18 mm fue el cartucho estándar para los países del Bloque del Este, en muchos de los cuales se mantiene en uso.
Este cartucho fue diseñado para que en caso de guerra, occidente no pudiera utilizar este cartucho en sus armas, ya que es muy diferente al 9x19 parabellum y no son compatibles 

El 9 x 18 mm tiene una balística inferior al 9 x 19 Parabellum. Las pruebas indican que la munición sobrante genera una presión de 1400 kg/cm2, significativamente menor que los 2460 kg/cm2 o más que generan las cargas propulsoras del 9 mm Parabellum. Esto es así para poder utilizar pistolas con el sistema de retroceso directo, en lugar de las pistolas de calibre 9 mm Parabellum u otras que generan altas presiones, que requieren mecanismos de bloqueo de recámara. 
El 9 x 18 mm Makárov no es intercambiable con los más potente 9 mm Parabellum, 9 mm Largo y otros, y su balística se acerca más a la de su pequeño hermano, el 9 mm Corto, siendo un poco más potente que este. 

https://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/9_%C3%97_18_mm_Makarov
</ES>
<FR>
Le 9 × 18 mm Makarov ou 9 × 18 PM est un calibre d'arme de poing créé en Union soviétique à la fin des années 1940 pour remplacer le 7,62 × 25 mm TT. Comme son prédécesseur, il dérive d'une munition allemande, la 9 mm Ultra, inventée dans le cadre d'un programme d'essai de la Luftwaffe. Son énergie initiale la situe entre le 9 mm court et le 9 mm Parabellum. Elle est tirée par des pistolets semi-automatiques et des pistolets mitrailleurs.
La première arme chambrée en 9 × 18 PM fut le Makarov PM (pistolet Marakova) adopté en 1951 par l'Armée rouge, puis en 1959 par l'Armée populaire de libération chinoise (Type 59). Resté le calibre réglementaire russe jusqu'au début des années 2000, il a engendré une version musclée (balle légère et dose de poudre forte) dénommée 9 mm Makarov modifié (9 × 18 PMM). 

https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/9_%C3%97_18_mm_Makarov
</FR>
</loc>