<loc>
<IT>N/A</IT>
<EN>
he 9×23mm Largo (9mm Largo, 9mm Bergmann–Bayard, 9mm Bayard Long) centerfire pistol cartridge was developed in 1901 for the Bergmann Mars pistol. 
The round was considered powerful for the day, producing a muzzle energy of between 330 and 430 ftxlbf (450 and 580 J) depending on the loading. A number of small changes to the Mars and the cartridge were made and the pistol that resulted was called the Bergmann–Bayard 1903.

This pistol was adopted by the Spanish army in 1905 as the "Pistola Bergmann de 9 mm. modelo 1903". Unable to find a German manufacturer to complete the Spanish order for 3,000 pistols, Theodor Bergmann turned to a Belgian manufacturer, Anciens Etablissements Pieper (who used the trademark "Bayard") to complete the order. The final pistol, modified by AEP, was known as the "Bergmann Bayard 1908", or in Spain as the "Pistola Bergmann de 9 mm. modelo 1908". 
Although adopted in 1908 first deliveries did not take place until two years later. Meanwhile, other manufacturers such as Campo-Giro had adopted the 9mm Bergmann–Bayard round and, due to its long history of use in Spanish submachine guns, carbines and pistols, today it is most commonly known as the "9mm Largo". At the same time the Bergmann–Bayard model 1910 semi-automatic pistol was adopted by the Danish military and remained in production until 1935.
The cartridge headspaces on the mouth of the case. With 125 gr (8.1 g; 0.29 oz) jacketed projectiles, the muzzle energy is 336 foot pounds, slightly lower than a standard-pressure 9×19mm Luger. Compared to the 9×19mm Luger +P, performance is also lower but at lower pressure in the 9×23mm Largo. While external dimensions are almost identical, the 9×23mm Largo is a very different cartridge from the modern, high-performance 9×23mm Winchester. 
Firing the thicker-walled 9×23mm Winchester round in a 9×23mm Largo pistol is dangerous, as old 9mm Largo pistols cannot handle the pressure generated by the 9×23mm Winchester. Performance is similar to the contemporary 9×23mm Steyr, but the cartridges were developed independently and their dimensions are just different enough to render them non-interchangeable

https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/9%C3%9723mm_Largo
</EN>
<DE>N/A</DE>
<ES>
El cartucho de percusión central 9 × 23 mm se desarrolló en 1901 para la pistola Bergmann Mars. Este cartucho ha recibido las deignaciones mas comunes entre otras: 9 x 23 mm / 9 Largo / 9 mm Bergmann-Bayard / 9 mm Campo-Giro / 9 mm Astra 1921 y 9mm Danische Pistolenpatrone. 
Este cartucho se consideró poderoso para la época, produciendo una energía de boca de entre 450 y 580 julios dependiendo de la carga. Se hicieron una serie de pequeños cambios en la pistola Bergmann Mars -anteriormente calibrada para el cartucho 7,63 x 25 Mauser - y el cartucho, y la pistola que resultó se denominó Bergmann-Bayard Modelo 1903 .
La Bergmann Mars Modelo 1903 fue adoptada y declarada reglamentaria por el ejército español en 1905 como la Pistola Bergmann de 9 mm. Modelo 1903 para reemplazar a los ya obsoletos revólveres Smith & Wesson Modelo 1884 en servicio. Incapaz de encontrar un fabricante alemán para completar el pedido español de 3.000 pistolas, Theodor Bergmann se dirigió al fabricante belga, Anciens Etablissements Pieper (que usaba la marca registrada "Bayard") y que completó el pedido. 
Esta pistola con ciertas modificaciones fue conocida como Bergmann Bayard 1908 (no debe confundirse con la Pieper- Bayard 1908), o en España como Pistola Bergmann de 9 mm. Modelo 1903/08, ya que aunque se adoptó en 1905, la entrega de las aproximadamente 3.000 pistolas no se completó hasta dos años después. Mientras tanto, otros fabricantes como Esperanza y Unceta con su pistola Campo Giro adoptaron el cartucho 9 mm Bergmann-Bayard y, debido a su larga historia de uso en subfusiles, 
carabinas y pistolas españolas, hoy en día se conoce más comúnmente como el 9 Largo. Al mismo tiempo, la pistola semiautomática Bergmann-Bayard modelo 1910 fue adoptada por el ejército danés y se mantuvo en producción hasta 1935. 

https://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/9_x_23_mm
</ES>
<FR>
Le 9 × 23 mm Largo est le nom ibérique du calibre 9mm Bergmann-Bayard, développé par Theodor Bergmann qui l'utilisa en premier dans le pistolet automatique "MARS". Ce calibre fut adopté par le Danemark et l'Espagne comme munition réglementaire. Utilisé principalement dans des pistolets semi-automatiques et pistolets mitrailleurs essentiellement en Amérique Latine. Appelé métriquement 9x23mm. 

https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/9_%C3%97_23_mm_Largo
</FR>
</loc>