<loc>
<IT>
La cartuccia calibro 9x25mm Dillon è un derivato diretto della cartuccia calibro 10mm Automatic ottenuto per riduzione del colletto fino a consentire l'introduzione di un proiettile del diametro di 9mm. Secondo una prima ricostruzione storica, questa cartuccia venne realizzata nei primi anni '90 del XX secolo dagli americani  A. Myhre e R. Letham che erano alla ricerca di una nuova munizione da impiegare nelle competizioni di tiro dinamico. Tramite l'interessamento di R. Shelby della Dillon (la nota azienda americana produttrice di presse professionali per ricarica), la nuova cartuccia venne realizzata in pochi mesi tra il 1992 ed il 1993. 
Secondo un'altra e diversa ricostruzione storica, Myhre e Letham non inventarono la cartuccia ex.novo, ma riutilizzarono semplicemente  le conoscenze accumulate circa 15 anni prima da altri tiratori americani, relative ad una munizione sperimentale (wildcat) detta .38-45, la quale non era altro che una cartuccia da 9mm ricavata da un bossolo del .45ACP. Quale che sia la verità, il 9x25 Dillon aveva, ed ha ancora oggi, ottime potenzialità sulla carta, che sono per altro rimaste quasi del tutto inespresse.

(https://www.grurifrasca.net/oldsite/Sito/Ricarica/pistole/9x25D.html)
</IT>
<EN>
The 9×25mm Dillon is a pistol wildcat cartridge developed for use in USPSA/IPSC Open guns. The cartridge is made by necking down a 10mm Auto case to 9 mm. 
Around 1987, Randy Shelley, an employee of Dillon Precision, necked down 10mm auto brass to 9mm. His goal was to get as much slow-burning powder in the case as possible in order to drive a 9mm bullet to the velocity needed to qualify for the then IPSC Major power factor of 175. The short-necked and steep-shouldered cartridge holds twice the powder of a .38 Super Auto case.
Most shooters, looking at the 9×25mm Dillon today, focus on the extreme velocities of which it is capable. A 115 grain bullet at 1800 fps is impressive, but more than needed for competition. There, a 115 only needed to be going a bit over 1500 fps to make Major. What competitors in the late 1980s and early 1990s who were using the 9×25mm Dillon were doing was adjusting the powder used, to produce more pressure in the compensator, or muzzle brake. A muzzle brake works by diverting gases to reduce felt recoil. 
The greater the gas volume, or the pressure that gas is at, the more force the compensator or muzzle brake creates. Competitors could "feed" the compensator more gases. This turned out to be too much of a good thing. The muzzle blast created by the combination proved to be tiring over the course of a match, and the resulting recoil re-direction proved hard on elbows and shoulders. Leatham developed loads with less blast and shock to mitigate this, but discovered there was little advantage over a similar load in .38 Super.
What finally put an end to the 9×25mm Dillon in competition was component wear, magazine capacity and lowering of the USPSA Major power factor from 175 to 165 (160 for IPSC competition). Barrels and compensators in high-pressure cartridges like .38 Super at Major velocities have a much shorter service life than lower-pressure ones. For maximum-permitted length magazines as used in USPSA/IPSC competition, a .38 Super magazine holds more rounds than a 9×25mm Dillon magazine. With the lowering of the USPSA power factor, safety and effectiveness of .38 Super loads improved to a point that the 9×25mm Dillon was no longer competitive and once worn out, pistols were often retired or rebuilt in .38 Super. 

(https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/9%C3%9725mm_Dillon)
</EN>
<DE>N/A</DE>
<ES>N/A</ES>
<FR>N/A</FR>
</loc>