<loc>
<IT>N/A</IT>
<EN>
.22 BB Cap (Bulleted Breech Cap) also known as the 6mm Flobert, is a variety of .22 caliber rimfire ammunition. Invented by Louis-Nicolas Flobert in 1845. It was the first rimfire metallic cartridge. The .22 BB Cap and .22 CB Cap are interchangeable and are relatively quiet, low velocity cartridges, designed for indoor target shooting. 
These rimfires closely resemble a .22 caliber air rifle in power and are often used for indoor shooting and close range pest control. Developed for indoor shooting galleries with special "gallery guns", the .22 BB Cap was the first rimfire cartridge, dating back to 1845. It has no separate propellant charge, relying on the impulse created by the primer alone to fire a round lead ball. This results in a low muzzle velocity of around 700 ft/s (210 m/s) or less. More common is the .22 CB cap, which fires a slightly heavier conical bullet and is available in a variety of cartridge lengths. 

https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/.22_BB

The .22 CB Cap (Conical Breech Cap) is a more powerful version of the .22 BB cap (aka: 6mm Flobert) rimfire metallic cartridge, which was invented by Louis-Nicolas Flobert in 1845. The .22 BB Cap and .22 CB Cap are interchangeable and are relatively quiet, low velocity cartridges, designed for indoor target shooting. 
The .22 CB Cap has a very small propellant charge (usually no gunpowder, just the primer), resulting in a low muzzle velocity of between 350 and 853 ft per second (107 and 260 m/s).[3] Due to their low power, classic CB rounds used in indoor target practice can be trapped by many pellet gun traps since some modern pellet guns exceed the velocity of the CB round (however, this depends on the limits designed in the individual pellet trap). In longer rifle barrels the CB has a very quiet, seemingly non-existent report due to the lack of residual pressure at the muzzle (see Internal ballistics). The CB loses velocity fast in longer barrels, due to the lack of anything other than the primer as a propellant.
Modern rounds:
The original .22 CB Cap has the same tiny case as the .22 BB Cap and the two cartridges are interchangeable. There are now .22 rounds sold as .22 CB Short and .22 CB Long which come in the standard .22 rimfire cartridge case sizes to allow the rounds to be used in standard magazine fed firearms which would likely jam with the tiny BB or CB cases. The CCI .22 CB Short and .22 CB Long use the same 29 grain bullet as the regular .22 Short and .22 Long. The CCI CB rounds have a muzzle velocity of 720 feet per second (ft/s) for an impact energy of 33 foot/pounds (ft/lb). The standard .22 Short and .22 Long fire the same bullet weight at 1045 ft/s for 70 ft/lb. The CB rounds are a relatively quiet round for short range target practice, 
control of small pests, or use in older .22 guns that might not be safe with modern high pressure rounds. For trapping these CB Short and CB Long rounds in indoor target practice, a standard .22 bullet trap is needed. Other modern CB type rounds, such as the .22 Aguila Colibri and .22 Aguila Super Colibri, have bullets in the same weight range as the original CB Cap with velocities in the 300 ft/s to 500 ft/s range using the Long case. 

https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/.22_CB
</EN>
<DE>
Als Flobertpatrone wird eine Munitionsart bezeichnet, bei der das Zündmittel gleichzeitig das Treibmittel ist. Erfinder war der französische Büchsenmacher Louis Nicolas Auguste Flobert, der Mitte des 19. Jahrhunderts das bis dahin nur als Zündmittel verwendete Knallquecksilber auch als Treibmittel einsetzte. Er ließ sich diese Patrone 1846 patentieren.
Flobert-Gewehre, die man auch als Zimmerbüchse bzw. Zimmerstutzen bezeichnet, verschießen schwache Randfeuermunition mit einer Rund- oder Spitzkugel im Kaliber 4 bis 9 mm; es sind auch Flobert-Schrot- und Platzpatronen erhältlich. 

https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Flobert_(Munition)
</DE>
<ES>
Los cartuchos .22 Flobert (llamados en Europa 6 mm Flobert) fueron los primeros cartuchos de percusión anular en el mundo, diseñados y producidos en 1845 para la pistola de Salón Flobert. Estos cartuchos no usan pólvora, sino que son propulsados por fulminato de mercurio. Este cartucho también es la base para la creación de armas que usan una cápsula fulminante como impulsor y un balín (pellet) o perdigón (BB) como proyectil. Los cartuchos 6 mm Flobert, por su bajo contenido de detonante, alcanzan velocidades entre los 220 y 210 metros por segundo,2​ aproximadamente lo mismo que un fusil de aire comprimido calibre 5,5 mm de mediana potencia, pero ya que es mayor el peso del proyectil, estos cartuchos producen una energía de impacto de entre 27 y 46 julios, el equivalente a un fusil de aire de alta potencia.
Por lo general los cartuchos 6 mm Flobert se les puede dar la denominación milimétrica de 5,6 x 7, pero existen las dos excepciones del 6 mm Flobert Bosquette y el 6 mm Flobert National, cuya denominación métrica decimal se puede entender como 5,85 x 7, estos dos últimos, tienen más fulminante, y una bala con un poco más de peso, por lo cual, producen más velocidad y energía de impacto. El National tiene un peso de 34 granos y una velocidad de 240 m/s, lo cual produce una energía de impacto de más de 63 julios, mientras el Bosquette tiene un peso de 33 gramos y una velocidad de 245 m/s, lo cual hace que produzca 64 julios de energía de impacto.
Actualmente los cartuchos 6 mm Flobert y .22 Corto se utilizan muy poco. En países como México es más usado el sistema de cápsula fulminante con proyectil. Este consiste simplemente en colocar un diábolo de plomo o una posta, delante de una cápsula fulminante (que solo es la vaina de un cartucho .22 Corto recortado y cerrado en forma de flor, lleno con fulminato de mercurio en lugar de pólvora). Ambos son asegurados y después un percutor golpea la pestaña de la cápsula fulminante, generando una detonación mucho menor que la producida por un cartucho .22 Corto. En México existen dos empresas dedicadas a la fabricación de armas con este sistema, Productos Mendoza e Industrias Cabañas, cada una con su propio sistema de percusión y extracción. 
Este tipo de sistema por lo general es monotiro, y solo se usan cápsulas fulminantes o salvas calibre .22 con balín (pellet) o perdigón (BB) calibre 4,5 mm (.177’’)
Actualmente solo se fabrican en Europa como "armas de jardín", ya que no contienen pólvora y su efecto es más similar al causado por las armas de aire comprimido. 

https://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/6_mm_Flobert
</ES>
<FR>N/A</FR>
</loc>