<loc>
<IT>
Il .22 Short è una cartuccia a percussione anulare per armi da fuoco sia lunghe che corte. 
Fino al 2004 è stata la cartuccia impiegata dalle pistole per la specialità di tiro definita Rapid Fire Pistol (in Italia pistola automatica o PA).
Con le variazioni del regolamento che imposero l'uso del .22 LR sulle armi per questa specialità, la .22 Short è praticamente scomparsa. Resta comunque nei cataloghi dei maggiori fabbricanti di munizioni mondiali per l'uso in numerose carabine a ripetizione semiautomatica e manuale. 

https://it.wikipedia.org/wiki/.22_Short

Il .22 Long Rifle (o .22 LR) è una cartuccia a percussione anulare, per fucile e pistola. Spesso ci si riferisce semplicemente a questa cartuccia come .22 LR e, occasionalmente, con la designazione metrica 5,6 × 15 mm R (R=rimmed, cioè orlata). 
È una delle poche cartucce accettate da una grande quantità di fucili e pistole. Virtualmente ogni costruttore di armi da fuoco produce almeno un modello camerato per essa ed è stato così per più di un secolo. La .22 Long Rifle e le cartucce simili (.22 Short, .22 Long e .22 Extra Long) usano un heeled bullet; questo termine significa che il proiettile ha lo stesso diametro del bossolo, con una minima parte più stretta (heel) che s'incastra nel bossolo.

https://it.wikipedia.org/wiki/.22_Long_Rifle
</IT>
<EN>
.22 Short is a variety of .22 caliber (5.6 mm) rimfire ammunition. Developed in 1857 for the first Smith &amp; Wesson revolver, the .22 rimfire was the first American metallic cartridge. The original loading was a 29 or 30 gr (0.066 or 0.069 oz; 1.879 or 1.944 g) bullet and 4 gr (0.0091 oz; 0.2592 g) of black powder. The original .22 rimfire cartridge was renamed .22 Short with the introduction of the .22 Long in 1871.[1]
Developed for self defense, the modern .22 Short, though still used in a few pocket pistols and mini-revolvers, is mainly used as a quiet round for practice by the recreational shooter. The .22 Short was popularly used in shooting galleries at fairs and arcades; several rifle makers produced "gallery" models for .22 Short exclusively. Due to its low recoil and good inherent accuracy, the .22 Short was used for the Olympic 25 meter rapid fire pistol event until 2004, and they were allowed in the shooting part of modern pentathlon competitions before they switched to air pistols.[1]
Several makes of starter pistols use .22 Short blank cartridges. Some powder-actuated nail guns use the .22 Short cartridge as a power source. 

https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/.22_Short

The .22 Long Rifle or simply .22 LR (metric designation: 5.6×15mmR) is a long-established variety of .22 caliber rimfire ammunition, and in terms of units sold is still by far the most common ammunition in the world today. It is used in a wide range of rifles, pistols, revolvers, smoothbore shotguns (No. 1 bore), and even submachine guns. 
The traditional .22 rimfire cartridges (BB, CB, short, long, extra long, and long rifle) differ in construction from more modern cartridges in the way the bullet is constructed and held in the case. Bullets for traditional .22 rimfires are the same outside diameter as the case but are constructed with a narrower cupped "heel" on the base of the bullet which is inserted into the case. The case mouth is then crimped around the heel, leaving exposed the majority of the bullet bearing surface that contacts the barrel of the gun. The bearing surface of .22 rimfire bullets is often lubricated and the surface is exposed to contamination. This was a common design in the early black powder cartridge era.
In later cartridges including the .22 WRF and .22 WMR rimfires and modern centerfires, the bullet body is a uniform diameter and the bearing surface is inserted completely within the neck of the cartridge case, held in place by tension from the case neck around the bullet bearing surface (in some cartridges the case mouth maybe also be crimped into a cannelure (groove) in the bullet). The heeled bullet cartridge is considered weaker than the uniform diameter bullet cartridge which encloses the bearing surface of the bullet within the cartridge neck. Overall reliability of heeled bullet rimfire ammunition is high, but it is lower than the reliability of most centerfire ammunition. 

https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/.22_Long_Rifle
</EN>
<DE>
Die Patrone .22 kurz (auch als .22 short bezeichnet) wurde bis 2004 hauptsächlich im Bereich des Pistolen-Sportschießens verwendet. 
Die .22 kurz wurde auf der Basis der 6 mm Flobert in den USA entwickelt. 1857 brachte die Firma Smith &amp; Wesson ihren ersten Revolver, den Smith &amp; Wesson No 1, in diesem Kaliber heraus. Die Originalpatrone hatte ein 1,9 Gramm schweres Geschoss und eine Schwarzpulverladung von 0,26 Gramm Gewicht.
Erst 1927 brachte Remington eine .22 kurz mit korrosionsfreier Zündung auf den Markt. Bis dahin hatte die quetschbare Zündmasse im Hülsenrand unter anderem aus Quecksilber, Kaliumchlorid und Sulfat-Antimon bestanden. Diese Bestandteile führten wegen der Schwefel- und Chlorverbindungen zu erheblicher Korrosion an den Waffenläufen. 

https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/.22_kurz

Die Patrone .22 lfB (lang für Büchsen), auch .22 lr (long rifle) genannt, ist eine Randpatrone für Kleinkaliber-Handfeuerwaffen sowohl als Büchse als auch als Faustfeuerwaffe.
In XWaffe, dem Datenstandard des deutschen Nationalen Waffenregisters, wird diese Patrone als .22lr unter der Katalognummer 9 geführt.
Die .22 lfB zündet per Randfeuerzündung. Der Schlagbolzen trifft auf den vorstehenden Bodenrand mit der Initialladung, welche die Treibladung zündet.
Die umgangssprachliche Bezeichnung ist Kaliber "22", da der Punkt für Zoll aus dem Englischen nicht mitgesprochen wird. 
Die Patrone .22 lfB benötigt je nach Waffenart unterschiedliche Patronenlagermaße. Bei Revolvern muss das Patronenlager vom Stoßboden bis zum Übergang lediglich 16,33 mm und bei Selbstladern 17,05 mm lang sein. Wird das Maß unterschritten, ist die Angabe des Maßes in der Handelsbezeichnung der Waffe aufzunehmen. 

https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/.22_lfB
</DE>
<ES>
El .22 Corto, originalmente .22 Short en inglés, es un tipo de cartucho para revólver desarrollado en 1857 para el primer revólver de Smith &amp; Wesson. 
Se trata de un cartucho de pequeño calibre, el menos potente de uso común hoy. Casi sin retroceso y pequeño, por este motivo era usado en armas deportivas y menos para realizar disparos rápidos. En especial en la disciplina olímpica de Pistola Velocidad y usualmente se ocupa además en tiro deportivo junior. Actualmente ha caído en desuso debido a que la nueva reglamentación obliga al uso de pistolas que disparen el .22 Long Rifle para esta disciplina.
Como cartucho de defensa es bastante deficiente, aunque se ha usado en algunas pequeñas pistolas. Debido a su escaso poder de detención, que hace que seguramente no logre derribar de un disparo (ni seguramente de varios) de forma inmediata al blanco, salvo impactos a corta distancia en zonas vitales o especialmente sensibles.
Monta una bala de 1,8 gramos, que sale a una velocidad de 220 m/s y desarrolla 61 julios. 

https://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/.22_Corto

El .22 Long Rifle, o 5,6 × 15 mm R en sistema métrico, es un cartucho de percusión anular y pequeño calibre para pistola y carabina​ usado sobre todo en el tiro deportivo. 
Desarrollado en 1887 por la empresa estadounidense J. Stevens Arms,​ originalmente usaba pólvora negra pero a comienzos del siglo XX se fabricó con nitropólvora. En ese mismo año todavía muchos fabricantes de cartuchos buscaban hacer un cartucho más potente que el .22 Long de 1871, por lo que en 1880 se desarrolló el .22 Extra Long y fue en 1887 cuando J. Steven Arms combinó la vaina del .22 Long con la bala de 40 granos del .22 Extra Long para crear el .22 Long Rifle. La versión "alta velocidad" de Remington apareció en 1930. Con el paso de los años ha sido el cartucho con más desarrollos y versiones.
La popularidad de este cartucho se debe a que es barato, genera poco retroceso y hace poco ruido. Este cartucho es tan popular que incluso existen kits de conversión para AR-15, M1911 y Glock 25 entre muchas otras armas cuyo kit incluye un cañón, un cargador con entrada especial y aditamentos de cerrojo.

https://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/.22_Long_Rifle
</ES>
<FR>
La .22 Court (5,6 mm) est une cartouche à percussion annulaire, variante de la 6 mm Flobert, qui est apparue en 1857 comme munition du revolver de poche S&amp;W N°1. Elle présentait alors une balle en plomb nu de 1,9 g propulsée par 0,26 g de poudre noire. 
Elle est utilisée dans des armes de défense personnelle et de tir sportif. Elle peut se chambrer dans des modèles tirant les .22 Long et .22 Long Rifle mais l'inverse est impossible. 

https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/.22_Court

Le .22 Long Rifle (désignation métrique : 5,56 x 15 mm R) est une munition à percussion annulaire (la composition d'amorçage se trouvant contenue dans le bourrelet de la cartouche) de calibre 5,5 millimètres, soit 22/100 de pouce, apparue en 1887.
C'est la munition la plus répandue au monde, d'après la NSSF, National Shooting Sports Foundation une association commerciale nationale américaine pour l'industrie des armes à feu, le calibre .22 LR représente plus de la moitié de la production de cartouches.
Elle a été directement extrapolée du .22 Court (ou .22 Short) et du .22 Long sous l'impulsion de la marque américaine Arms &amp; Tool Company et fabriquée par Peters (États-Unis) pour la manufacture d'armes Stevens de même nationalité.
C'est le calibre utilisé pour les compétitions internationales de biathlon. 

https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/.22_Long_Rifle
</FR>
</loc>