<loc>
<IT>N/A</IT>
<EN>
The .327 Federal Magnum is a cartridge introduced by Federal Cartridge but also sold by Sturm, Ruger, intended to provide the power of a .357 Magnum in six shot, compact revolvers, whose cylinders would otherwise only hold 5 rounds. The .327 has also been used in full-sized revolvers with a capacity of seven rounds or more. The .327 Federal Magnum is actually a super magnum having replaced the .32 H&amp;R Magnum as the pinnacle of power in this diameter revolver cartridge. 
Introduced by Federal Cartridge company, the .327 Federal Magnum is an attempt to improve on the .32 H&amp;R Magnum introduced in 1984. Like the .32 H&amp;R, the .327 Federal is a lengthened version of the original .32 S&amp;W cartridge, which dates back to 1878. In 1896, the .32 S&amp;W Long was introduced, which generated slightly higher velocities. The introduction of the .32 H&amp;R increased pressures from 15,000 psi to 21,000 CUP, giving velocities of approximately 1,200 ft/s (370 m/s).
Based on the .32 H&amp;R Magnum, with a 1/8" longer case, strengthened web at the base of the case, thicker case walls, and different heat-treatment and metallurgy, the .327 Federal can be loaded to much higher pressure levels (45,000 psi (310,000 kPa)) than its predecessor (21,000 CUP). The .327's actual bullet diameter is .312 in (7.92 mm) and achieves muzzle velocities up to 1,400 ft/s (430 m/s) with 100 gr (6.5 g; 0.23 oz) bullets, and up to 1,300 ft/s (400 m/s) with 115 gr (7.5 g; 0.26 oz) bullets, when fired from the 3 1/16" (78 mm)-barreled Ruger SP101 revolver.
With its strengthened case and increased pressure ceiling, the .327 Federal reaches the velocity levels of the .357 Magnum, if not the same power. Since the .327 still shares all case dimensions, excluding length, with the .32 S&amp;W, .32 ACP, .32 S&amp;W Long, and .32 H&amp;R Magnum, revolvers chambered for the .327 Federal can also safely chamber and fire these shorter cartridges. This makes the .327 Federal unique, as it can fire five different cartridges from the same gun with no modifications.
While felt recoil exceeds that of the .32 H&amp;R, revolvers in .327 Federal are much easier to control than equivalent models chambered in .357 Magnum. Comparing the two calibers, Chuck Hawks says, "There is no doubt that, for most shooters, the .357 Mag. produces uncomfortable recoil and muzzle blast."
The .327's recoil energy is 3.08 ft⋅lbf (4.18 J) for an 85 gr (5.5 g; 0.19 oz) jacketed hollowpoint (JHP) load, 5.62 ft⋅lbf (7.62 J) for the 115 gr (7.5 g; 0.26 oz) JHP, and 5.58 ft⋅lbf (7.57 J) for the 100 gr (6.5 g; 0.23 oz) softpoint (SP). For comparison, the figures are 1.46 ft⋅lbf (1.98 J) for an 85 gr (5.5 g; 0.19 oz) .32 H&amp;R Magnum load and 7.22 ft⋅lbf (9.79 J) for a 125 gr (8.1 g; 0.29 oz) .357 Magnum load.

https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/.327_Federal_Magnum
</EN>
<DE>N/A</DE>
<ES>N/A</ES>
<FR>
La munition de .327 Federal est une version plus puissante du .32 H&amp;R Magnum commercialisé depuis 2008 pour le revolver de défense personnelle Ruger SP 101. 
Balistique indicative:
    Type de la munition : balle blindée à pointe creuse
    Masse de la balle : 5,5 à 7,5 g
    Vitesse initiale : 400–430 m/s
    Énergie initiale : 584-590 joules
	
https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/.327_Federal_Magnum
</FR>
</loc>