<loc>
<IT>
La 7,65 × 17 mm Browning (conosciuta anche come .32 ACP) è una cartuccia per pistola semiautomatica. 
Adotta un bossolo semi-rimmed e monta una palla da 308 millesimi di pollice da 71 o da 60 grani, con velocità iniziale di 270 m/s per la più pesante e 295 m/s per l'altra. Per questa cartuccia sono stati progettati anche alcuni mitra, per esempio il CZ Skorpion. È caratterizzata da un buon livello di penetrazione ma da un rinculo modesto che ne permette l'uso in armi a chiusura a massa (attuata cioè solo dall'inerzia dell'otturatore e dalla spinta della sua molla) piccole, facilmente tascabili e semplici nella costruzione meccanica. 

https://it.wikipedia.org/wiki/7,65_%C3%97_17_mm_Browning
</IT>
<EN>
.32 ACP (Automatic Colt Pistol, also known as the .32 Automatic) is a centerfire pistol cartridge. It is a semi-rimmed, straight-walled cartridge developed by firearms designer John Browning, initially for use in the FN M1900 semi-automatic pistol. It was introduced in 1899 by Fabrique Nationale, and is also known as the 7.65×17mmSR Browning or 7.65 mm Browning Short.
The .32 ACP was intended for blowback semi-automatic pistols which lacked a breech locking mechanism. It was John Pedersen with the Remington Model 51 that delivered a true locked breech for the .32 ACP cartridge. The relatively low power and light bullet of the cartridge allowed Browning to incorporate a practical blowback mechanism in a small Pocket Size Pistol. It is still used today primarily in compact, inexpensive pistols, unless the pistol is used for ISSF competition where the cost then escalates. Cartridges in .32 ACP are also sometimes used in caliber conversion sleeves, also known as supplemental chambers, for providing an alternative pistol caliber carbine function in .30-caliber hunting and service rifles.
Some comparison of the ".32 Automatic" as defined by SAAMI and the "7.65 Browning" as defined by CIP may be useful. Although some of the cartridge measurements differ by as much as 0.16mm, the names are considered to be synonymous. However, the maximum average pressure - as measured by a transducer on the test barrel - is 20,500 psi (1,410 bar) according to SAAMI, while CIP allows up to 1,600 bar (23,000 psi). This may explain why the cartridges from European manufacturers tend to chronograph at higher muzzle velocities compared to those from American manufacturers. 

https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/.32_ACP
</EN>
<DE>
Die 7,65 × 17 mm Browning ist eine von John Browning entwickelte Patrone für Selbstladepistolen. Sie wird auch als .32 ACP (Automatic Colt Pistol), .32auto oder als 7,65 Browning bezeichnet; ihre richtige metrische Bezeichnung lautet 7,65 × 17 mm HR (Halbrand). 
Die 7,65 Browning entstand 1897 auf Grundlage der .32 S&amp;W, als Browning die FN Model 1900 für die belgische Fabrique Nationale d’Armes de Guerre (FN) konstruierte. Browning erkannte, dass zylindrische Hülsen für Selbstladepistolen Vorteile gegenüber Flaschenhalshülsen boten. Ab 1903 stellte Colt die Patrone unter der in Amerika üblichen zölligen Bezeichnung .32 ACP her, was ihr außerhalb Europas zu großer Verbreitung verhalf. Die 7,65 Browning zählt zu den weitestverbreiteten Pistolenpatronen der Welt. Sie ist die schwächste für Dienstwaffen geeignete Munition. 

https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/7,65_mm_Browning
</DE>
<ES>
El 7,65 × 17 mm Browning SR o 7,65 mm Browning, también llamado .32 ACP (Automatic Colt Pistol) o .32 Automatic, es un cartucho de pistola de forma cilíndrica, diseñado por John Moses Browning, para usarse en la pistola FN M1900. Fue introducido en 1899 por FN,​ y usado por primera vez en la Browning M1900. 
El 7,65 × 17 mm Browning es compacto y liviano, pero de corto alcance y con un poder de parada marginal. Las armas recamaradas para este cartucho a menudo son apreciadas por diseño compacto y bajo peso en relación al calibre, en especial para usar como arma de portación oculta. A pesar de ser capaz de matar, las balas de baja velocidad de 4,2 g o 4,6 g no son capaces de incapacitar personas fácilmente. La munición con balas de punta hueca ha estado disponible durante décadas y puede incrementar el poder de parada, aunque esto sigue siendo controvertido (con balas de baja velocidad, las balas de punta hueca no expanden como se espera. Incluso cuando la expansión ocurre, puede lograrse el mismo efecto con balas encamisadas que tienen más penetración).
En Europa, el 7,65 × 17 mm Browning es más ampliamente aceptado que en América, con un largo historial de uso por parte de civiles y de agencias militares y policiales.​ El cartucho gana popularidad debido a las modernas pistolas para portación (en los países o estados donde es legal) recamaradas para él, tales como Kel-Tec P-32, Beretta Tomcat y la Seecamp LWS 32. Este incremento en la popularidad permitió a muchos fabricantes de municiones desarrollar nuevas cargas con mejores rendimientos para el cartucho. 

https://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/7,65_%C3%97_17_mm_Browning
</ES>
<FR>
La cartouche 7,65 × 17 mm Browning ou .32 ACP ou encore .32 Auto, conçue par John M. Browning, a initialement été fabriquée par la FN Herstal dès 1899. Cette munition adaptée aux pistolets semi-automatiques de petit et moyen gabarit a été très largement distribuée tant aux États-Unis qu’en Europe. 

https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/7,65_%C3%97_17_mm_Browning
</FR>
</loc>

