<loc>
<IT>N/A</IT>
<EN>
The .32 H&amp;R Magnum is a rimmed cartridge designed for use in revolvers. It was developed in 1984 as a joint venture between Harrington &amp; Richardson and Federal Cartridge. The .32 H&amp;R Magnum is produced by lengthening the .32 S&amp;W Long case by .155", to 1.075". 
The .32 H&amp;R Magnum offers substantially more performance than most other .32 caliber handgun cartridges, such as the .32 ACP, and is considered an effective small-game hunting cartridge. Its higher velocity offers a flat trajectory, while the light weight of the bullet results in low recoil. 
The older .32-20 Winchester was extremely popular in the Winchester lever- and Colt single-actions, available at the turn of the century, for small-to-medium game hunting. The .32 H&amp;R offers near duplicate performance.
One of the .32 H&amp;R Magnum's favorable attributes is that it offers .38 Special energy levels and allows a small-frame revolver to hold six cartridges, whereas a similarly sized revolver in .38 Special holds only five rounds. Penetration is also usually increased compared to the .38 Special with bullets of the same weight due to greater sectional density.
Maximum pressure for the .32 H&amp;R Magnum is set at 21,000 CUP by SAAMI.
The .327 Federal Magnum is based on the .32 H&amp;R Magnum and increases performance to levels near that of the .357 Magnum. 

https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/.32_H%26R_Magnum
</EN>
<DE>N/A</DE>
<ES>
El .32 H&amp;R Magnum (Harrington &amp; Richardson) es un cartucho para revólver. 
Introducido en 1984 como una versión más potente del .32 S&amp;W Long. Se han fabricado varios modelos de revólver para este calibre. 
Considerablemente más potente y preciso que otros .32, el .32 Magnum puede usarse para el tiro deportivo y la caza menor.
Dispara una bala de 7,65 mm de calibre y 95 grains de peso a 315 m/s. Dando 308 julios. 

https://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/.32_H%26R_Magnum
</ES>
<FR>
La munition de .32 H&amp;R Magnum est une version plus puissante du .32 S&amp;W Long commercialisé depuis 1983 pour un revolver de défense personnelle de marque Harrington &amp; Richardson. Son but fut de concurrencer le .38 Special mais sa diffusion fut restreinte. 
Balistique indicative:
    Masse de la balle : 5,5 ou 6 g
    Vitesse initiale : 311–335 m/s
    Énergie initiale : 279 joules
	
https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/.32_Harrington_%26_Richardson_Magnum
</FR>
</loc>