<loc>
<IT>N/A</IT>
<EN>
The .32 S&amp;amp;W cartridge (also known as the .32 S&amp;amp;W Short) was introduced in 1878 for Smith &amp;amp; Wesson pocket revolvers. It was originally designed as a black powder cartridge. The .32 S&amp;amp;W was offered to the public as a light defense cartridge for "card table" distances.
Originally designed by the Union Metallic Cartridge Company (UMC) as a black powder cartridge using nine grains of black powder, the round has been loaded with smokeless powder exclusively since 1940. It is low-powered and perfect for use in small frame concealable revolvers and derringers. The round remained popular in the United States and Europe long after the firearms chambered for it were out of production.[1] At one time it was considered to be the bare minimum for a self-defense round and was judged unsuitable for police work.
For defensive uses, the .32 S&amp;amp;W is grouped with other turn-of-the-century cartridges designed for use in "belly guns"—guns meant for use in point-blank defensive situations, such as in a carriage or an alleyway. These cartridges include the .25 ACP, and the .22 Short, Long, and Long Rifle. For comparison, the .32 S&amp;amp;W projectile is over 40% larger in diameter and over twice as heavy as the 40-grain lead round-nose bullet used in the .22 Long Rifle of its day (known as standard velocity today). 
The .32 S&amp;amp;W's velocity of approximately 700 feet per second (210 m/s) was very close to the .22 Long Rifle's performance from a sub-3-inch (76 mm) barrel, but with larger diameter and better sectional density.
Although the .32 S&amp;amp;W's round-nose bullet was less than optimal for defense, it did offer significant improvement over these other common handgun calibers of the day. This performance made guns chambered in .32 S&amp;amp;W, sometimes referred to as .32 Short, very popular as a gentleman's "vest gun".

https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/.32_S%26W

The .32 S&amp;W Long, also known as 7.65x23mm, is a straight-walled, centerfire, rimmed handgun cartridge, based on the earlier .32 S&amp;W cartridge. It was introduced in 1896 for Smith &amp; Wesson's first-model Hand Ejector revolver. Colt called it the .32 Colt New Police in revolvers it made chambered for the cartridge
The .32 S&amp;W Long headspaces on the rim and shares the rim dimensions and case and bullet diameters of the shorter .32 S&amp;W cartridge and the longer .32 H&amp;R Magnum and .327 Federal Magnum cartridges. The shorter .32 S&amp;W may be fired in handguns chambered for the .32 S&amp;W Long; and the .32 S&amp;W Long may be fired in arms chambered for the longer H&amp;R and Federal magnums; although the longer cartridges should not fit and must not be fired in arms designed for the shorter and less powerful cartridges.
The .32 S&amp;W Long and .32 Long Colt are not interchangeable. At one time it was widely publicized that these rounds would interchange, but in truth it has never been deemed safe to do so.

https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/.32_S%26W_Long
</EN>
<DE>
Die Patrone .32 S&amp;W long ist eine in den USA entwickelte und dort verbreitete Revolver-Patrone. 
Die Patrone .32 S&amp;W long wurde 1896 zusammen mit dem ersten Smith &amp; Wesson Revolver mit ausschwenkbarer Trommel vorgestellt. Vorläufer der Patrone war die 1878 entwickelte .32 S&amp;W, die eine Hülsenlänge von 15 mm besitzt. Beide Patronen sind in ihren ballistischen Leistungen vergleichbar und aus Waffen mit dem Kaliber .32 S&amp;W lang kann auch die Munition .32 S&amp;W verschossen werden. Die Firma Colt bot Waffen für diese Patrone mit der Kaliberangabe .32 Colt New Police an.
Die in der Disziplin Zentralfeuerpistole verwendeten Sportpistolen Hämmerli 280, Walther GSP, Pardini HP, Benelli MP 90 S und Benelli MP 95E sind ebenfalls für das Kaliber ausgelegt, verwenden aber ein Wadcutter Projektil, das nicht über den Hülsenmund hinausragt. Dort entspricht also die Patronenlänge der Hülsenlänge. 

https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/.32_S%26W_Long
</DE>
<ES>
El .32 S&amp;amp;W es un cartucho introducido en 1878 para el revólver Smith &amp;amp; Wesson modelo 1½.
Aunque su tamaño es muy parecido al .32 Colt Corto, no son intercambiables. Sí puede utilizarse en armas que usan el .32 S&amp;amp;W Long, el .32 H&amp;amp;R Magnum o el .327 Federal Magnum, pero no al revés.
Como munición de defensa personal es limitada, pues difícilmente derribará de un disparo. Pero tiene un retroceso muy escaso.​ Usaba balas de 88 granos calibre 7,65 mm a 205 m/s, dando unos 120 julios. Actualmente, una versión de potencia semejante, el .32 S&amp;amp;W Long, denominada wadcutter, es el calibre más utilizado en tiro de precisión; concretamente en la modalidad de fuego central, siendo su pequeña carga suficiente para obtener gran agrupación en disparos a 25 m. 

https://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/.32_S%26W
</ES>
<FR>
Le .32 Smith &amp;amp; Wesson est un type de cartouche pour revolvers de police et de défense personnelle, fabriquée à l'origine par la compagnie Smith &amp;amp; Wesson. Sa commercialisation date de 1876 pour le S&amp;amp;W Baby Russian.
Le calibre .32 (7,84 mm) S&amp;amp;W correspond au calibre .32 européen pour la balle, mais pas pour la douille, qui est un peu plus épaisse. Les munitions appelées .32 S&amp;amp;W ne sont pas nécessairement un produit de la marque Smith &amp;amp; Wesson, mais bien un type de munition, qui oblige le fabricant à prévoir des chambres plus larges dans le barillet que celles du .32 européen.
Cette cartouche à la poudre noire, a par la suite aussi été fabriquée avec de la poudre pyroxylée (avec une charge trois fois moindre).
Ce précurseur du .32 S&amp;amp;W Long fut répandu jusque dans les années 1900 pour les armes de poche. Elle est toujours produite industriellement en 2008 (Autriche, Brésil, Italie et États-Unis). 

https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/.32_Smith_%26_Wesson

Le .32 Smith &amp; Wesson Long est une cartouche pour revolvers de tir sportif et de défense personnelle, fabriquée par la compagnie Smith &amp; Wesson, elle est également utilisée dans quelques pistolets semi-automatiques de tir sportif. Sa commercialisation date de 1896 pour le S&amp;W .32 Hand Ejector. Cette version musclée du .32 Smith &amp; Wesson fut répandue jusque dans les années 1960 pour les armes de poche. Ces petits revolvers arment souvent les criminels des polars de James Lee Burke ou de New York, police judiciaire. Sa variante sportive, le .32 S&amp;W Long Wadcutter, est toujours en usage en 2019. 

https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/.32_S%26W_Long
</FR>
</loc>