<loc>
<IT>
La cartuccia .357 SIG è un tipo di munizione per pistola semiautomatica realizzata dalla SIG in collaborazione con la Federal Cartridge.
La .357 SIG è stata creata a partire dal 1994 sulla base della cartuccia .40 S&amp;W, con l'intenzione di ottenere una munizione delle stesse dimensioni ma con potenza simile ad una .357 Magnum sparata da un revolver con canna da 2" (50 mm c.ca). 

https://it.wikipedia.org/wiki/.357_SIG
</IT>
<EN>
The .357 SIG pistol cartridge (designated as the 357 Sig by the SAAMI and 357 SIG by the C.I.P. or 9×22mm in unofficial metric notation) is the product of Swiss-German firearms manufacturer SIG Sauer, in cooperation with ammunition manufacturer Federal Cartridge. The cartridge is used by a number of law enforcement agencies and has a good reputation for accuracy.
Americans would define the shoulder angle at alpha/2=18 degrees. The common rifling twist rate for this cartridge is 406 mm (1 in 16 in), 6 grooves, Ø lands=8.71 mm, Ø grooves=9.02 mm, land width=2.69 mm and the primer type is small pistol.
Several sources have published contradicting information regarding .357 SIG headspacing. This is due to the cartridge having been originally designed as a .357 (9.02mm) round, but then rapidly adapted to the .355 (9mm) bullet. According to the official C.I.P. (Commission Internationale Permanente Pour L'Epreuve Des Armes A Feu Portatives) 
2008 revised documents, the .357 SIG headspaces on the case mouth (H2). Some US sources are in conflict with this standard. However, the cartridge and chamber drawing in the ANSI/SAAMI American National Standards also clearly shows the cartridge headspacing on the cartridge mouth. Likewise, US reloading supplier Lyman has published that the .357 SIG headspaces on the case mouth.
According to the C.I.P. rulings the .357 SIG case can handle up to 305 MPa (44,236 psi) piezo pressure. In C.I.P. regulated countries every pistol cartridge combo has to be proofed at 130% of this maximum C.I.P. pressure to certify for sale to consumers.
The SAAMI pressure limit for the .357 SIG is set at 275.80 MPa (40,000 psi), piezo pressure.

https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/.357_SIG
</EN>
<DE>
.357 SIG ist eine von SIGARMS in Zusammenarbeit mit Federal Cartridge 1994 entwickelte Zentralfeuerpatrone. Die .357 SIG verwendet eine modifizierte .40-S&amp;W-Hülse, wobei der Hülsenhalsdurchmesser zum Hülsenmund hin verkleinert wurde, sodass .357-Geschosse verwendet werden können. Es handelt sich also um eine Patrone mit Flaschenhalshülse, die ähnliche Eigenschaften wie eine Gewehrpatrone aufweist. SIG vermied es, seine neue Patrone als 9 × 22 mm zu bewerben, 
um eine vorherige öffentliche Ablehnung zu vermeiden. Stattdessen nannten sie sie .357, um den Grund für die neue Patrone zu versinnbildlichen: Sie sollte die gleichen Eigenschaften wie die 125 grain schwere .357-Magnum-Patrone haben, jedoch in einer halbautomatischen Waffe genutzt werden.
Wegen der relativ hohen Mündungsgeschwindigkeit ergibt sich eine besonders günstige ballistische Flugbahn, welche die effektive Reichweite einer Waffe im Kaliber .357 SIG erhöht. Der E0-Wert kann bei entsprechender Munition über 1050 J liegen, was bei Pistolen eher die Ausnahme ist. Dies sorgt für eine besonders hohe Durchschlagskraft, weshalb die .357 SIG sich auch gut für den Einsatz gegen geschützte Ziele eignet. 
Viele .40-S&amp;W-Kaliber-Pistolen können zu .357-SIG-Kaliber-Pistolen umgebaut werden, indem man den Lauf ersetzt. Pistolen mit relativ schwachen Rückstoßfedern erfordern auch den Austausch dieser. Magazine sind miteinander kompatibel. .357-SIG-Umbau-Kits haben zudem die Popularität dieser Patrone gesteigert, jedoch sollte hier angemerkt werden, dass die .357 bis zu 345 bar höheren Druck erzeugen kann als die .40 S&amp;W, was sich negativ auf die .40-S&amp;W-Pistolen auswirken kann. 

https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/.357_SIG
</DE>
<ES>
El .357 SIG o 9 × 22 mm en el sistema métrico, es un cartucho para pistola producido por el fabricante de armas suizo SIG-Sauer en colaboración con el fabricante de munición estadounidense Federal Cartridge. 
Cuando a instancias del FBI se redujo la potencia del 10mm Auto, a fin de reducir el retroceso para facilitar el entrenamiento y evitar problemas de manejo con personas menos corpulentas (como los agentes femeninos), apareció un nuevo cartucho que ofrecía ese nuevo nivel de potencia, siendo más pequeño y manejable: el .40 S&amp;W, que demostró un equilibrio entre prestaciones balísticas y manejabilidad excelente. No tardó en popularizarse.
Basándose en el .40 S&amp;W, apareció un cartucho "wildcat" (de diseño "casero"), que básicamente usaba una vaina ("casquillo") del .40 S&amp;W abotellada, a fin de montar una bala del 9 mm Parabellum. El resultado fue tan bueno que la SIG Sauer decidió adoptarlo y terminó por fabricarse en serie. 
El .357 SIG dispara una bala de 9 mm a una velocidad mucho mayor que la Parabellum, sin que el cartucho sea mucho más grande y sin mucho más retroceso, de hecho, menos que el del .40, ya de por sí manejable. La potencia es solo un 20% menor que la de un .357 Magnum, a pesar de ser bastante más corto. Lo que permite fabricar pistolas con empuñaduras lo bastante pequeñas como para adaptarse a la mano de casi cualquier usuario. Además del SIG Sauer P226, Glock creó los 31,32 y 33 en .357 SIG.
Los detractores de este calibre dicen que tiende a gastar demasiado rápido el cañón de las armas, acortando su vida útil, en comparación con otras municiones. 

https://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/.357_SIG
</ES>
<FR>
Les cartouches de pistolet .357 SIG sont un produit de la fabrique d'armes à feu suisse Sig-Sauer, en collaboration avec le fabricant de munitions américain Federal Cartridge
En 1994, SIGARMS, filiale américaine de SIG à l'époque, développe en partenariat avec Federal Cartridge (en), une munition de calibre .357 (9,06 mm). L'objectif était de créer une munition de pistolet automatique puissante, comparable au .357 Magnum dont l'étui à bourrelet la rend peu adapté au chargement dans un pistolet mais avec un recul inférieur. En conséquence, les différents chargements comportent une balle plus légère mais aussi plus rapide. En conséquence, outre son énergie cinétique élevée, la munition présente une trajectoire plus tendue qu'une munition plus conventionnelle comme la 9 mm Parabellum sans pour autant atteindre les performances d'une .357 Magnum chargée avec une balle de 8 grammes.
L'étui de la nouvelle munition est basé sur celui du .40 S&amp;W, rétreint en forme de bouteille pour recevoir le projectile de 9 mm. 

https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/.357_SIG
</FR>
</loc>