<loc>
<IT>
La cartuccia calibro .380 ACP (Automatic Colt Pistol, chiamata anche 9 x 17 mm, 9 mm corto o anche 9 mm Browning corto), è una cartuccia per pistole. 
Venne creata nel 1908 dalla Browning Arms Company Il successo del .380 ACP fu così grande che nel 1910, la Colt intraprese la produzione di una nuova arma camerata per questa cartuccia appositamente per il mercato americano. Può essere utilizzata con la prima pistola al mondo "fatta in casa" con stampa 3D, chiamata Liberator.
Progettata appositamente per le armi a chiusura labile, viene considerata la cartuccia più potente di questa categoria. Come tutte le cartucce usate con questa chiusura, sviluppa energie relativamente modeste; perciò le armi che usano la .380 ACP sono ritenute maggiormente adatte per difesa personale. Essa non deve essere confusa con il .38 ACP, di superiori dimensioni e prestazioni. 
In Italia questo calibro viene utilizzato nelle armi d'ordinanza dei reparti ordinari della Guardia di Finanza (Beretta 84 e 85) e di vari Corpi e servizi di Polizia Locale/Municipale, tra cui il Corpo di Polizia Locale di Roma e di Milano. L'Arma dei Carabinieri, fino ai primi anni del 2000, utilizzava questo calibro nelle pistole Beretta 85 assegnate agli Ufficiali come arma d'ordinanza. 

https://it.wikipedia.org/wiki/.380_ACP
</IT>
<EN>
The .380 ACP (9×17mm) (Automatic Colt Pistol) is a rimless, straight-walled pistol cartridge developed by firearms designer John Moses Browning. The cartridge headspaces on the mouth of the case. It was introduced in 1908 by Colt, for use in its new Colt Model 1908 pocket hammerless semi-automatic, and has been a popular self-defense cartridge ever since, seeing wide use in numerous handguns (typically smaller weapons). 
Other names for .380 ACP include .380 Auto, 9mm Browning, 9mm Corto, 9mm Kurz, 9mm Short, 9×17mm and 9 mm Browning Court (which is the C.I.P. designation). It should not be confused with .38 ACP. 
The .380 ACP cartridge was derived from Browning's earlier .38 ACP design, which was only marginally more powerful. The .380 ACP was designed to be truly rimless, with headspace on the case mouth instead of the rim for better accuracy. These relatively low-powered designs were intended for blowback pistols which lacked a barrel locking mechanism, which is often required for any handgun firing a round more powerful than a .380. 
Using blowback operation, the design can be simplified, and lowered in cost; a locking mechanism is unnecessary, since the mass of the slide and strength of the recoil spring are enough to absorb the recoil energy of the round, due to the round's relatively low bolt thrust. Blowback operation also permits the barrel to be permanently fixed to the frame, which promotes accuracy, unlike a traditional short recoil-operation pistol, which requires a "tilting" barrel to unlock the slide and barrel assembly when cycling. 
A drawback of the blowback system is that it requires a certain amount of slide mass to counter the recoil of the round used. The higher the power of the round, the heavier the slide assembly has to be in order for its inertia to safely absorb the recoil, meaning that a typical blowback pistol in a given caliber will be heavier than an equivalent recoil-operated weapon. Blowback weapons can be made in calibers larger than .380 ACP, but the required weight of the slide and strength of the spring makes this an unpopular option. 
Although the low power of the .380 ACP does not require a locking mechanism, there have been a number of locked-breech pistols chambered in .380 ACP, such as the Remington Model 51, Kel-Tec P3AT and Glock 42; all three being designed to be lighter than blowback-operated .380 ACP weapons. There have also been some relatively diminutive (blowback-operated) submachine guns, such as the Ingram MAC-11 and the Czech vz. 83.

https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/.380_ACP
</EN>
<DE>
Die .380 ACP (Automatic Colt Pistol, im deutschen Sprachraum auch als 9 mm kurz geführt) ist eine Pistolenpatrone. Sie geht zurück auf das Jahr 1908 und wurde von John Moses Browning entwickelt. Die Geschossenergie ist wesentlich geringer als die einer 9 mm Parabellum, denn sie war für den Einsatz in Pistolen mit unverriegeltem Masseverschluss vorgesehen.
Dabei ist zu bemerken, dass ebenfalls von Browning eine andere Patrone im Nominalkaliber .38 ACP (9 × 23 mm HR) entwickelt wurde. 

https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/.380_ACP
</DE>
<ES>
El 9 × 17 mm Corto, también llamado 9 mm Corto, 9 mm Kurz, 9 mm Short, .380 ACP y .380 Auto, es un cartucho de pistola con casquillo recto y sin pestaña, desarrollado por el diseñador de armas John Moses Browning. Fue introducido por Colt en el mercado en 1908, siendo desde entonces un popular cartucho para defensa personal y gozando de amplia difusión en España durante los dos primeros tercios del siglo XX.
Así como el cartucho 7,65 x 17 Browning es considerado como aquel que puso fin a la Segunda Guerra Mundial por ser empleado por Adolf Hitler para suicidarse (el 30 de abril de 1945), el cartucho 9 x 17 corto es considerado como aquel que empezó la Primera Guerra Mundial, por ser empleado para el asesinato del Archiduque Francisco Fernando de Austria y su esposa (el 28 de junio de 1914).
El 9 × 17 mm Corto fue diseñado para las primeras pistolas accionadas por retroceso, cuyos cañones no tenían mecanismos de acerrojado. El mecanismo de acerrojado que tienen la mayoría de pistolas no es necesario para el 9 × 17 mm Corto, debido a la poca presión que ejerce sobre la recámara al ser disparado. El muelle recuperador es suficiente para dirigir la energía del disparo a la corredera. Esto simplifica la producción de pistolas calibradas para este cartucho, por lo que generalmente se reduce el costo. 
También permite fijar el cañón al armazón de la pistola, aumentando la precisión. Sin embargo, existen varias pistolas que disparan el 9 × 17 mm Corto con recámara acerrojada. También existe un pequeño subfusil de este calibre, el Ingram MAC-11.
El 9 × 17 mm Corto es un cartucho compacto y ligero, pero tiene un alcance relativamente corto y menos poder de parada que otros cartuchos de pistola modernos. Incluso así, continúa siendo un popular cartucho de defensa personal para los tiradores que desean una pistola ligera y con un retroceso manejable. Es algo menos potente que un .38 Special con carga de pólvora estándar y monta balas con un diámetro de 9 mm (.357 pulgadas). 
La bala más pesada que puede montarse en un casquillo de 9 × 17 mm Corto es de 115 granos (7,5 g), aunque el peso estándar siempre ha sido de 85, 90 o 95 granos (5,5 g, 5,8 g o 6,2 g). El 9 × 17 mm Corto nuevamente ha vuelto a ganar popularidad, debido a las pistolas compactas y baratas que lo emplean. Entre las pistolas populares que disparan este cartucho figuran las españolas Astra 300, 3000 y 4000, la Beretta Cheetah, Walther PPK, la Bersa Thunder 380, la Ruger LCP la Kel-Tec P-3AT, la S&amp;W Bodyguard .380 , 
la Taurus PT-58 , la CZ modelo 83 y las Glock G25, G28 y G42. 

https://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/9_%C3%97_17_mm_Corto
</ES>
<FR>
Le 9 × 17 mm court est un calibre de cartouche aussi nommé .380 ACP, ou encore 9 mm Browning. Sa désignation métrique est 9 x 17 mm. 
Caractéristiques:
    Masse de la balle : de 5,50 à 6,15 grammes
    Vitesse initiale : de 274 à 305 m/s

Dans la longue série des calibres conçus par John M. Browning vers 1910, le 9 mm court est l’un des plus polyvalents. Bien que de puissance nettement supérieure au 7,65 Browning, cette munition est mise en œuvre par des pistolets automatiques de catégorie comparable. Ainsi, le Walther PP et le Mauser Hsc auront des versions pour chacun de ces calibres sans que les carcasses et glissières soient modifiées. 
Parmi les nombreux fabricants de pistolets automatiques ayant mis sur le marché des armes chambrées dans ce calibre, citons le Beretta Cheetah, le LLAMA III-A, le Astra Constable, le CZ 83, le Taurus PT58S, et le récent Ruger LCP, plusieurs modèles Glock. 

https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/9_%C3%97_17_mm_court
</FR>
</loc>