<loc>
<IT>
La .38 Special è un tipo di cartuccia per arma corta, prevalentemente revolver prodotta dalla Smith &amp; Wesson.
Venne progettata nel 1902 per equipaggiare i revolver delle forze di polizia statunitensi 
Non essendo dotata di potenza molto elevata, in molti casi i componenti delle forze di polizia ritennero necessario avere a disposizione armi più efficaci. Per questa ragione sono state in seguito allestite versioni in questo calibro dotate di maggior potenza (denominate .38 Special + P) o con pallottola più pesante, come per la .38 Special 200 grani. Ma, essendo uguale la dimensione esterna della cartuccia, il loro uso in revolver a struttura particolarmente leggera, come ad esempio il Colt Cobra poteva essere pericoloso. In seguito progettata la più potente .357 Magnum che, avendo un bossolo più lungo, necessita di armi progettate appositamente per quel tipo di cartuccia, anche se alcune armi camerate per il .357 di solito possono sparare anche cartucce .38 Special. 

https://it.wikipedia.org/wiki/.38_Special
</IT>
<EN>
The .38 Smith &amp; Wesson Special (commonly .38 Special, .38 Spl, or .38 Spc, pronounced "thirty-eight special") is a rimmed, centerfire cartridge designed by Smith &amp; Wesson. It is most commonly used in revolvers, although some semi-automatic pistols and carbines also use this round. The .38 Special was the standard service cartridge of most police departments in the United States from the 1920s to 1990s, and was also a common sidearm cartridge used by soldiers in World War II. In other parts of the world, it is known by its metric designation of 9×29.5mmR or 9.1×29mmR.
Known for its accuracy and manageable recoil, the .38 Special remains one of the most popular revolver cartridges in the world more than a century after its introduction. It is used for target shooting, formal target competition, personal defense, and for hunting small game. 
Due to its black-powder heritage, the .38 Special is a low-pressure cartridge, one of the lowest in common use today at 17,000 PSI. By modern standards, the .38 Special fires a medium-sized bullet at rather low speeds. In the case of target loads, a 148 gr (9.6 g) bullet is propelled to only 690 ft/s (210 m/s). The closest comparisons are the .380 ACP, which fires much lighter bullets slightly faster than most .38 Special loads; the 9×19mm Parabellum, which fires a somewhat lighter bullet significantly faster; and the .38 Colt Super, which fires a comparable bullet significantly faster. All three of these are usually found in semi-automatic pistols.
The higher-pressure .38 +P loads at 20,000 PSI offer about 20% more muzzle energy than standard-pressure loads and places between the .380 ACP and the 9 mm Parabellum; similar to that of the 9×18mm Makarov. A few specialty manufacturers' +P loads for this cartridge can attain even higher energies than that, especially when fired from longer barrels, produce energies in the range of the 9 mm Parabellum. These loads are generally not recommend for older revolvers or ones not specifically "+P" rated. 

https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/.38_Special
</EN>
<DE>
Die .38 Special ist eine in den USA entwickelte und dort weit verbreitete Revolver-Patrone. 
Die .38 Special wurde von dem US-Unternehmen Smith &amp; Wesson 1902 als Nachfolger der von Fehlern geplagten .38 Long Colt für die Revolver-Modelle Military &amp; Police entwickelt.
Bei der .38er handelt es sich um eine in den USA weit verbreitete Zentralfeuerpatrone, die im zivilen, aber auch im militärischen/polizeilichen Sektor Verwendung findet. Für diese Patrone stehen sehr viele Geschossvarianten zur Verfügung, wie z. B. Wadcutter-Geschosse oder Hohlspitzgeschosse, Geschosse mit Schrot oder sogenannte Short-Stop-Patronen.
Diese Munition kann auch aus Revolvern des Kalibers .357 Magnum verschossen werden, da ihre Abmessungen abgesehen von der Hülsenlänge ähnlich sind. Aufgrund der relativ geringen Leistung der .38er entwickelte Smith &amp; Wesson die oben genannte Patrone im Kaliber .357 Magnum. 

https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/.38_Special
</DE>
<ES>
El .38 Smith &amp; Wesson Special, comúnmente llamado .38 Special, .38 Spl o .38 Spc, como 9×29 mmR en el sistema métrico, es un cartucho para armas ligeras. Es uno de los más vendidos[cita requerida]. Fue creado por Smith &amp; Wesson en 1902 y a más de un siglo desde su creación, todavía sigue siendo popular, aunque ahora para autodefensa y tiro deportivo o recreativo. Son más numerosos los modelos de revólver que usan este cartucho, si bien existen algunos modelos de pistola semiautomática que lo utilizan. Este cartucho fue el más común para los revólveres de uso policial desde los años 1950 hasta los años 1980.{{cr} popular entre las guerrillas
A pesar de su nombre, su diámetro es de .357 pulgadas. Este cartucho es semejante al .357 Magnum; excepto en la longitud de su casquillo que es 3 mm menor que en el Magnum, y por lo tanto su potencia es también menor por contener menos pólvora, pero fundamentalmente es menor por usar pólvora de quemado rápido, mientras que el 357 utiliza pólvora de quemado progresivo, la cual trabaja a mayores presiones logrando gran velocidad. Debido a la semejanza de ambos calibres, los cartuchos .38 Special se pueden utilizar en revólveres Magnum, pero no al revés. Es común que los usuarios de los revólveres .357 Magnum prefieran sustituir 
este cartucho por el .38 Special en su arma, debido a su menor retroceso y su estampido más suave. No obstante, respecto al uso de cartuchos del .38 Special en revólveres del .357 Magnum, hay que advertir que la diferencia de longitud del cartucho supone que la zona de vuelo (hasta la toma de estrías) es mayor y ello va en el deterioro de sus prestaciones balísticas.
Al principio los cartuchos utilizaban pólvora negra y después pólvora sin humo. Muchos fusiles de palanca usan el .38 Special

https://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/.38_Special
</ES>
<FR>
La munition de .38 Special a été extrapolée à partir de la .38 Long Colt, et commercialisée en 1902, pour le revolver Smith &amp; Wesson .38 Hand Ejector de ce millésime, dernier avatar du modèle 1899 (chambré pour la .38 Long Colt) avant le modèle Military &amp; Police 1905.
La .38 Special est une munition extrêmement répandue, elle est la plus diffusée commercialement pour les revolvers, depuis la fin de la Seconde Guerre mondiale. 
La .38 Special fut très utilisée dans la police, pour la défense, à titre supplétif dans l’armée américaine durant la Seconde Guerre mondiale, et reste la cartouche reine du tir sportif en catégorie « gros calibre » UIT-ISSF, c’est-à-dire pour la discipline du « Pistolet Sport », avec des revolvers (S&amp;W modèle 14 K-38 Masterpiece, Colt Diamondback, Colt Officer’s Match, Manurhin MR 38 Match), ou parfois des pistolets semi-automatiques (S&amp;W modèle 52 Master notamment, qui a établi un record du monde, divers modèles Colt et SIG par le passé).
Elle est toutefois concurrencée pour cette discipline par la .32 Smith &amp; Wesson Long Wad-cutter, autre munition de revolver que l’on retrouve de plus en plus tirée dans des pistolets semi-automatiques européens, en raison de sa semblable précision et de son recul moindre permettant un tir plus précis et plus rapide, mais qui est d’un diamètre inférieur (8 millimètres), ce qui peut être un désavantage, car les trous sont plus petits et donc pardonnent moins les erreurs de visée, mais l'arbitrage tient compte de cette différence de diamètre puisque les impacts de .32 sont « pigés » avec une pige de .38. Ce calibre est aussi celui qui chambre les armes des policiers municipaux avec le .32 ACP.
Selon Cibles (cf. bibliographie), 19 millions de revolvers chambrant cette munition ont été vendus depuis 1902. 

https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/.38_Special
</FR>
</loc>

