<loc>
<IT>
La cartuccia calibro .38 Super Automatic (nota invariabilmente nelle fonti bibliografiche come .38 Super, .38 S.A. o .38 Super Auto), nacque nel 1929 come "...aggiornamento  tecnico ..." della preesistente cartuccia calibro .38 ACP realizzata nel 1900 da John Moses Browning. Le due cartucce sono esteriormente simili, tuttavia, operando a pressioni di esercizio nettamente diverse, NON è possibile sparare un cartuccia calibro .38 Super Auto in una vecchia Colt camerata per il risalente .38 ACP!!

https://www.grurifrasca.net/oldsite/Sito/Ricarica/pistole/38sa.html
</IT>
<EN>
The .38 Super, also known as .38 Superauto or .38 Super Auto, is a pistol cartridge that fires a 0.356-inch-diameter (9.04 mm) bullet. The Super was introduced in the late 1920s as a higher pressure loading of the .38 ACP or .38 Auto. The old .38 ACP propelled a 130-grain (8.4 g) bullet at 1,050 ft/s (320.0 m/s). The improved .38 Super Auto pushed the same 130-grain (8.4 g) bullet at 1,280 ft/s (390.1 m/s). The .38 Super has gained distinction as the caliber of choice for many top pistol match competitors; 
it remains one of the dominant calibers in IPSC competition. The cartridge was designed for use in the M1911 pistol and was capable of penetrating the body armor and automobile bodies of the late 1920s. When the .357 Magnum was introduced in 1934, this advantage of the .38 Super was no longer enough to lure police departments and officers from the traditional revolver.
The .38 Super retains the original dimensions of the .38 ACP case. The cartridge was originally designed to headspace on the semi-rim, which worked in the Colt M1900 due to the design of the feed ramp. When the .38 Auto became the .38 Super, in the 1911A1, the feed ramp could no longer be used as rim support. As a result of this, observed accuracy of the .38 Super suffered until Irv Stone of Bar-Sto barrels re-designed the chamber to allow headspacing on the case mouth. 
Since then, all new production .38 Super pistols headspace on the case mouth, as with other cartridges in this class. The semi-rimmed case is known to cause feeding problems in some magazines, especially double stack magazines, and led to the development of new variants with reduced rims (typically only .003" per side).
In 1974 the industry added the +P headstamp to the .38 Super to further distinguish it from the lower-pressure .38 ACP. Most current ammunition manufacturers label ammunition for the Super as .38 Super +P.
Since the .38 Super is dimensionally the same as the .38 ACP, an unsafe condition can be caused by firing .38 Super cartridges in a firearm designed for the much lower pressure .38 ACP. The weakness, in the Colt M1900, Colt M1902, and others derived from that design, comes from the assembly wedge at the front of the slide. If the wedge comes out, or the slide cracks at the wedge, the slide can come off the rear of the frame when fired. The 1911 and 1911A1, having a slide that is solid on front, cannot come off the frame that way. 

https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/.38_Super
</EN>
<DE>
.38 Super, auch als .38 Super Auto bekannt, ist eine in den USA entwickelte und dort verbreitete Pistolen-Patrone. 
Die Munition .38 Super ist eine als Alternative zur .380 ACP entwickelte Patrone. Sie ist länger als die weiter verbreitete 9 mm Parabellum. Die dadurch mögliche, größere Pulverladung verleiht dem Geschoss eine höhere Geschwindigkeit und somit höhere Geschossenergie und höheren Geschossimpuls als das 9 × 19-mm-Geschoss[3]. Die .38 Super ist bei Polizei und Sicherheitskräften wenig verbreitet, obwohl sie gegenüber der .40 S&amp;W den Vorteil bietet, aufgrund der 1 mm schlankeren Patrone mehr Munition im Pistolen-Magazin unterbringen zu können. 
Colt fertigt heute noch Pistolen im Kaliber .38 Super, allerdings mit einreihigem Magazin mit neun Patronen. 

https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/.38_Super
</DE>
<ES>
El .38 Super, también conocido como .38 Super Automatic, es un cartucho para pistola que monta una bala de 9,04 mm. El .38 Super fue introducido a fines de la década de 1920 como una variante con mayor carga propulsora del .38 ACP o .38 Auto. El anterior .38 ACP disparaba una bala de 8,4 g con una velocidad de 320 m/s. El mejorado .38 Super también disparaba la misma bala de 8,4 g con una velocidad de 390,1 m/s.
El .38 Super se ha ganado la reputación de ser el cartucho de elección para varios tiradores prácticos; se mantiene como uno de los principales cartuchos empleados en las competencias de la IPSC.
Este cartucho fue diseñado para una variante de la pistola Colt M1911 y era capaz de perforar los chalecos antibalas y las carrocerías de los automóviles de fines de la década de 1920. Cuando el cartucho .357 Magnum fue introducido al mercado en 1934, esta ventaja del .38 Super no bastó para que las agencias policiales y sus oficiales abandonen el tradicional revólver.
El casquillo del .38 Super conserva las dimensiones originales del .38 ACP. Fue originalmente diseñado como un cartucho con semipestaña, para poder ser empleado por la pistola Colt M1900 debido al diseño de su rampa de alimentación. Cuando el .38 Auto pasó a ser el .38 Super, la rampa de alimentación de la Colt M1911A1 ya no podía utilizarse como un apoyo para la pestaña. A causa de esto, la precisión del .38 Super fue mala hasta que Irv Stone de la empresa Bar-Sto Barrels rediseñó la recámara para permitir la adecuada inserción de la boca del casquillo. 
Desde entonces, todas las pistolas de serie que disparan el .38 Super tienen esta característica. Se sabe que el casquillo con semipestaña causa problemas de alimentación en algunos cargadores, especialmente los de doble hilera, lo que llevó al desarrollo de variantes con pestaña reducida.
En 1947, los fabricantes de cartuchos añadieron el marcaje +P al culote del casquillo del .38 Super para distinguirlo del .38 ACP con baja presión. La mayoría de los actuales fabricantes de cartuchos etiquetan los empaques de este cartucho con .38 Super +P.
Como el .38 Super tiene las mismas dimensiones que el .38 ACP, se corre el riesgo de disparar cartuchos .38 Super con una pistola que dispara el menos potente .38 ACP. El problema con las pistolas Colt M1900, M1902 y otras derivadas de este diseño, es la cuña de ensamblaje en la parte delantera de la corredera. Si la cuña se suelta, o si la corredera se raja cerca de la cuña, la corredera puede ir hacia atrás y salirse del armazón al disparar. 
Las pistolas Colt M1911 y M1911A1, que tienen una corredera cuya parte delantera es maciza, no pueden soltarse de esta manera. 

https://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/.38_Super
</ES>
<FR>
Le calibre .38 Super est une création de la fabrique d'armes Colt, destinée aux pistolets semi-automatiques. C'est une version dopée du .38 Auto. Le diamètre de la balle mesure 0,356 pouce (avec une tolérance de 1/1000 de pouce).
La balle de 38 est légèrement plus grosse que le 9 mm Parabellum qui a un diamètre de 355. Le 38 super auto fut introduit dans les années 1920, c'est un calibre plus puissant que le calibre .38 Special inventé en 1900. Il eut un certain succès aux États-Unis durant la Prohibition puis auprès des policiers et militaires latino-américains. Depuis 1990, il est devenu un calibre de tir sportif.
C'est un calibre puissant, rapide, certains chargements pouvant atteindre des vitesses de 500 m/s lors de compétition de Tir sportif de Vitesse. 

https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/.38_Super
</FR>
</loc>