<loc>
<IT>N/A</IT>
<EN>
The .38 S&amp;W (9×20mmR) is a revolver cartridge developed by Smith &amp; Wesson in 1877. Versions of the cartridge were the standard revolver cartridges of the British military from 1922 until the 1960s. Though similar in name, it is not interchangeable with the later .38 Smith &amp; Wesson Special due to a different case shape and slightly larger bullet diameter.
The .38 Colt New Police was Colt's Manufacturing Company's proprietary name for what was essentially the .38 S&amp;W with a flat-nosed bullet.
The U.S. .38 S&amp;W Super Police cartridge was nearly identical to the British .38/200 Mk I, using a 200 gr (13 g) lead alloy bullet with a muzzle velocity of 630 ft/s (190 m/s) and a muzzle energy of 176 ft⋅lbf (239 J), and was supplied by several U.S. manufacturers to the British government as equivalent to the Mk I loading.
MKE's 9.65 mm Normal (9.2×23mmR (.38 Smith &amp; Wesson)) cartridge has a 177 gr (11.5 g) lead-antimony alloy bullet with a gilding-metal full metal jacket and a Boxer-primed brass case. The "normal" designation differentiates it from their 9.65mm Special (9.1×29mmR (.38 Special)) round. It uses the 9.65 mm (.38-caliber) nominal bore rather than its 9.2 mm (.361-caliber) actual bore. It has a muzzle velocity of 590 ft/s (180 m/s). 

https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/.38_S%26W
</EN>
<DE>
Die .38 S&amp;W war eine Revolverpatrone, die das Unternehmen Smith &amp; Wesson 1876 herausbrachte. Sie war für deren Kipplauf-Revolver 38 SA (Single Action) vorgesehen und anfangs mit Schwarzpulver geladen. Die Waffen erwiesen sich als erfolgreich; auch Konkurrenzfirmen wie Colt oder Harrington &amp; Richardson bauten eigene Kurzwaffen, die auf der Patrone basierten. 
Nach dem Ersten Weltkrieg suchte das britische Militär Ersatz für die alte und als zu stark befundene Ordonnanzmunition im Kaliber .455 Webley. Auf der Grundlage der .38 S&amp;W wurde die .38/200 entwickelt. Der Zusatz deutet das Geschossgewicht in Grain an (umgerechnet etwa 13 Gramm). In der ersten Version wurde ein stumpfes Bleigeschoss verwendet. Aufgrund von Bedenken, dass diese Projektile nicht der Haager Landkriegsordnung entsprächen, wurde ab 1937 ein leichteres Vollmantel-Rundkopfgeschoss eingeführt. Die Munition gehörte noch bis 1963 zur Ausrüstung des britischen Heeres.
Die .38 Special (ebenfalls von Smith &amp; Wesson) ist eine weitaus modernere und leistungsstärkere Patrone, die nicht mit dieser verwechselt werden darf. 

https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/.38_S%26W
</DE>
<ES>
El .38 S&amp;W o 9 x 20 R es un cartucho de revólver desarrollado por la Smith &amp; Wesson en 1877. Versiones de este cartucho fueron la munición estándar de los revólveres del Ejército Británico desde 1922 hasta la década de 1960. A pesar de la similitud de su nombre, no es intercambiable con el posterior .38 Smith &amp; Wesson Special debido a la forma del casquillo y su bala de calibre ligeramente mayor.
El .38 Colt New Police era una marca registrada de la Colt's Manufacturing Company para su versión del .38 S&amp;W que montaba una bala con punta plana.
El cartucho estadounidense .38 S&amp;W Super Police era casi idéntico al .38/200 Mk I británico, montando una bala de aleación de plomo de 13 g y con una energía de 239 J, siendo suministrado durante la guerra por varios fabricantes estadounidenses al gobierno británico como un equivalente del Mk I.
El cartucho turco 9,65 mm Normal (9,2 x 23 R; .38 Smith &amp; Wesson) de la MKE (Makina ve Kimya Endüstrisi Kurumu, Corporación de Industrias Mecánicas y Químicas) monta una bala encamisada con núcleo de aleación de plomo de 11,5 g en un casquillo con cápsula fulminante Boxer. La designación "Normal" lo distingue del cartucho 9,65 Special (9,1 x 29 R; .38 Special). Usa el calibre 9,65 mm en lugar del calibre 9,2 mm. Tiene una velocidad de boca de 180 m/s. 

https://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/.38_S%26W
</ES>
<FR>
La cartouche civile pour revolver .38 S&amp;W a été conçue par Smith and Wesson en 1877. Les cartouches .38 Colt New Police et .380 British Service en sont dérivées. Elle est toujours en fabrication en 2008. Quelques armes de poing sont encore en vente. 
C'est une des plus anciennes cartouches américaine à percussion centrale. Elle a été conçue en 1876 par la firme Smith &amp; Wesson pour le revolver "Perfected" à canon basculant qui a aussi été le premier double action de la marque. Il s'agissait de proposer une munition intermédiaire entre le calibre .32 S&amp;W et le calibre .44.40.
    En 1877, la cartouche d'origine avait une charge de poudre noire de 0,78 grammes et pesait 9,40 grammes. Pour les armes ancienne, les munitions actuelles qui sont chargées à la poudre sans fumée (poudre pyroxylée), ne doivent pas dépasser une pression de 1200 bars (contre 1500 bars pour la .38 Special créée en 1902 et 3000 bars pour la .357 Magnum créée en 1935). Le tir d’une munition moderne dans une arme ancienne nécessite une vérification préalable de l’arme par un armurier.
    La .38/200, ou balle Super Police, version adoptée en Grande-Bretagne en 1930 et réélaborée par la Royal Small Arms de Enfield avec une charge de poudre sans fumée et une balle de 200 grains (1 grains = 0.065 gramme). Elle est interchangeable avec la munition américaine.
    En 1922, apparait la balle MK1, adoptée en 1930 comme balle réglementaire de l'armée anglaise, avec aussi une balle de 200 grains.
    En 1939, elle est remplacée par la MK2, balle de même poids chemisée de 178. (voir .380 MK I/MK II)

https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/.38_S%26W
</FR>
</loc>