<loc>
<IT>N/A</IT>
<EN>
The .400 Corbon is an automatic pistol cartridge developed by Cor-Bon in 1997. It was created to mimic the ballistics of the 10 mm Auto cartridge in a .45 ACP form factor. It is essentially a .45 ACP case, necked down to .40 caliber with a 25-degree shoulder. 
Ballistics fall somewhere between the .40 S&amp;W and the 10 mm Auto. Unlike the 10 mm which operates at a SAAMI maximum of 37,500 psi, the .400 Corbon operates at 29,000 psi (although one source states that the pressure is 26,500 psi), much closer to the SAAMI maximum pressures for .45 ACP (21,000 psi), and .45 ACP +P (23,000 psi).[10] SAAMI Maximum Average Pressure for 400 Cor-Bon is 35,000 psi.
In 2008, Michael Shovel, then National Sales Manager for CORBON/Glaser, stated that Cor-Bon "submitted the 400 COR-BON to SAAMI and it was approved [in 2006]. Pressures for the 400 are in the 23,000 PSI range." The difference between SAAMI maximum average pressure is only 2,500 psi and identical to that of the .40 S&amp;W (35,000 psi).
The .400 Corbon is a versatile cartridge useful for target shooting, practical shooting competition, self-defense, and the handgun hunting of small and medium game. The loads with the lighter bullets are appropriate for small game. Handloaders have worked up safe loads using 180 gr (12 g) bullets at 1,250 ft/s (380 m/s) making it an adequate round for hunting some medium game at close distances.
For practical shooting competitors, the .400 Corbon makes IPSC Major Power Factor of 175 and surpasses the IDPA Enhanced Service Pistol's Power Floor of 125,000 in most loads using a 5-inch barrel.The .400 Corbon also surpasses the Steel Challenge Shooting Association's stop plate's power actor floor of 120 and qualifies for metallic silhouette Big Bore Competition under IHMSA rules.
According to Ed Sanow, the 135 gr (8.7 g). JHP penetrated 9 inches (230 mm) of ordnance gelatin and "equals the predicted stopping power of the 10mm 135-grain (8.7 g) JHP loads," and that the 165 gr (10.7 g). JHP "penetrates an ideal 12.3 inches (310 mm) of gelatin" and "should be a 92-percent stopper, per the Fuller Index."

https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/.400_Cor-Bon
</EN>
<DE>
Bei der Patrone .400 CorBon handelt es sich um eine 1997 eingeführte Patrone für Pistolen. Der Entwickler und Präsident der Firma CorBon, Peter Pi, formte Hülsen der Patrone .45 ACP zu Flaschenhalshülsen für 10-mm-Geschosse um. Das große Volumen der Hülsen ermöglicht in Verbindung mit einem relativ kleinen Geschoss, die ungefähre Leistung der Patrone .41 Magnum zu erreichen.
Da die Patronen keinen hohen Gasdruck benötigen, können sie problemlos aus fast allen Waffen des Kalibers .45 ACP verschossen werden. Es ist lediglich ein entsprechender Lauf notwendig.
Die Bezeichnung CorBon (auch Cor-Bon) ist aus den englischen Wörtern core (für Geschosskern) und bonded (verbunden) abgeleitet. Dabei werden der Geschossmantel und der Bleikern durch ein spezielles Klebeverfahren miteinander verbunden.
Fabrikpatronen (nur mit Hohlspitzgeschoss) werden mit folgenden Leistungsdaten angeboten:
135 grs (8,75 g) mit 442 m/s und einer Energie von 855 Joule
155 grs (10,0 g) mit 405 m/s und einer Energie von 820 Joule 

https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/.400_Corbon
</DE>
<ES>N/A</ES>
<FR>N/A</FR>
</loc>