<loc>
<IT>
La .40 Smith &amp; Wesson è una cartuccia per pistole prodotta dalla Smith &amp; Wesson derivata dalla 10 mm Auto. 
La cartuccia .40 S&amp;W riceve la catalogazione SAAMI nel 1989. Poche cartucce sono nate dopo i primi del '900 con scopi prettamente operativi e la .40 S&amp;W rappresenta un punto d'arrivo importante di una lunga evoluzione delle munizioni da 10 millimetri per arma corta. Con energie nettamente superiori al 9 mm Luger, il .40 S&amp;W è diventato in poco tempo molto apprezzato, in particolar modo negli Stati Uniti dove molti dipartimenti di polizia e uffici dello sceriffo lo hanno adottato come calibro d ordinanza.
Nell'intento di F.B.I. e Smith &amp; Wesson si è voluto ottimizzare l'impianto di cartuccia della 10 mm Auto che inizialmente fu solo ridotta nella carica di lancio per renderla più mite allo sparo.
La .40 S&amp;W prende vita con un accorciamento del bossolo del 10 mm Auto da 25,10 mm a 21,70 mm, mentre l'innesco di tipo large pistol lascia il posto ad uno small pistol; carica dedicata per il ridimensionamento della cartuccia la cui altezza finita scende da 32 mm a 29,7 mm con palla da 180 grani e 290 m/s. e 48 kgm del 10 Auto F.B.I. load, ma con circa 1000 atmosfere in più. 

https://it.wikipedia.org/wiki/.40_Smith_%26_Wesson
</IT>
<EN>
The .40 S&amp;W is a rimless pistol cartridge developed jointly by major American firearms manufacturers Smith &amp; Wesson and Winchester. The .40 S&amp;W was developed from the ground up as a law enforcement cartridge designed to duplicate performance of the Federal Bureau of Investigation's (FBI) reduced-velocity 10mm Auto cartridge which could be retrofitted into medium-frame (9mm size) semi-automatic handguns. It uses 0.40-inch (10 mm) diameter bullets ranging in weight from 105 to 200 grains (6.8 to 13.0 g).
The common rifling twist rate for this cartridge is 406 millimetres (16.0 in), 6 grooves, Diam. lands = 9.91 ;mm, Diam. grooves = 10.17 mm, land width = 3.05 mm and the primer type is small pistol. According to the official C.I.P. guidelines, the .40 S&amp;W case can handle up to 225 megapascals (32,600 psi) piezo pressure. In C.I.P.-regulated countries every pistol/cartridge combo has to be proofed at 130% of this maximum C.I.P. pressure to certify for sale to consumers.
The SAAMI pressure limit for the .40 S&amp;W is set at 241.32 megapascals (35,001 psi) piezo pressure.
The .40 S&amp;W cartridge has been popular with law enforcement agencies in the United States, Canada, Australia and Brazil. While possessing nearly identical accuracy, drift and drop as the 9mm Parabellum, it also has an energy advantage over the 9mm Parabellum and .45 ACP, and with a more manageable recoil than the 10mm Auto cartridge. Marshall &amp; Sanow (and other hydrostatic shock proponents) contend that with good jacketed hollow point bullets, the more energetic loads for the .40 S&amp;W can also create hydrostatic shock in human-sized living targets.
Based on ideal terminal ballistic performance in ordnance gelatin during lab testing in the late 1980s and early 1990s, the .40 S&amp;W earned status as "the ideal cartridge for personal defense and law enforcement". Ballistically the .40 S&amp;W is almost identical to the .38-40 Winchester introduced in 1874, as they share the same bullet diameter and bullet weight, and have similar muzzle velocities.
The energy of the .40 S&amp;W exceeds standard-pressure .45 ACP loadings, generating between 350 foot-pounds (470 J) and 500 foot-pounds (680 J) of energy, depending on bullet weight. Both the .40 S&amp;W and the 9mm Parabellum operate at a 35,000 pounds per square inch (240 MPa) SAAMI maximum, compared to a 21,000 pounds per square inch (140 MPa) maximum for .45 ACP.
.40 S&amp;W pistols with standard (not extended) double-stack magazines can hold as many as 16 cartridges. While not displacing the 9mm Parabellum, the .40 S&amp;W is commonly used in law enforcement applications in keeping with its origin with the FBI. Select U.S. special operations units have available the .40 S&amp;W and .45 ACP for their pistols. The United States Coast Guard, having dual duties as maritime law enforcement and military deployments, has adopted the SIG Sauer P229R DAK in .40 S&amp;W as their standard sidearm. 
The .40 S&amp;W was originally loaded at subsonic velocity (around 980 ft/s (300 m/s)) with a 180 grains (11.7 g) bullet. Since its introduction, various loads have been created, with the majority being either 155, 165 or 180 gr (10.0, 10.7 or 11.7 g). However, there are some bullets with weights as light as 135 gr (8.7 g) and as heavy as 200 gr (13.0 g). Cor-Bon and Winchester both offer a 135 gr (8.7 g) JHP and Cor-Bon also offers a 140 gr (9.1 g) Barnes XPB hollow-point. 
Double Tap Ammo, based out of Cedar City, Utah, loads a 135 gr (8.7 g) Nosler JHP, a 155 gr (10.0 g), 165 gr (10.7 g) and 180 gr (11.7 g) Speer Gold Dot hollow-point (marketed as "Bonded Defense"), a 180 gr (11.7 g) Hornady XTP JHP, and three different 200 gr (13.0 g) loads included a 200 gr (13 g) Full Metal Jacket (FMJ), a 200 gr (13 g) Hornady XTP JHP and Double Tap's own 200 gr (13 g) WFNGC (Wide Flat Nose Gas Check) hard cast lead bullet; the latter specifically designed for hunting and woods carry applications. 

https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/.40_S%26W
</EN>
<DE>
Die Patrone .40 S&amp;W ist eine von Smith &amp; Wesson entwickelte Pistolen-Patrone.
Sie ist auch bekannt als:

    10 × 22 mm
    .40
    .40 Auto
    .40 Liberty
    10 mm Kurz
Die Patrone wurde von Smith &amp; Wesson 1990 entwickelt. Wegen des starken Rückstoßes der 10 mm Auto hatte das FBI die Patrone heruntergeladen und so praktisch eine 10 mm „light“ geschaffen. Da man bei der 10 mm Auto ebenfalls bemängelt hatte, dass die Hülse zu lang war, nutzte man den Umstand aus, dass die übrig gebliebene Menge an Pulver auch in eine kleinere Hülse passte. Smith &amp; Wesson entwickelte die Patrone, wobei das Kaliber gleich blieb und nur die Patronenhülse gekürzt wurde.
Mit einer kürzeren Hülse konnte diese neue Patrone dann auch in kleinere Pistolen geladen werden, die ursprünglich für das Kaliber 9-mm-Parabellum konzipiert waren. Die .40 S&amp;W wurde zusammen mit den Winchester-Munitionsfabriken als neu geschaffenes Produkt 1990 auf der Shot-Show in den Vereinigten Staaten vorgestellt. Die Patrone lief der 9 mm Parabellum den Rang als Dienstwaffenkaliber in den Vereinigten Staaten ab und wird mittlerweile von 75 % der Behörden dort eingesetzt, 
unter ihnen das FBI, die Küstenwache, die Grenzpolizei, einige State Troopers und Highwaypatrols sowie lokale Polizeieinheiten. Auch außerhalb der Vereinigten Staaten hat sie in mehreren Ländern Einzug gehalten, so in Kanada, Australien, Jordanien (CTU Anti-Terror-Einheit) und den Bundespolizeibehörden in Brasilien. Sie bietet ungefähr 40 % mehr Energie als eine 9 mm Parabellum bei normalem Druck. Die Patrone ist auch als Unterschall-Version (subsonic) erhältlich.
Andere Geschossgewichte sind z. B.: 180 grains, V0 290 m/s, E0 492 Joule 

https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/.40_S%26W
</DE>
<ES>
El .40 S&amp;W (10 × 22 mm Smith &amp; Wesson) es un cartucho de pistola aparecido en la década de los años 90. Actualmente muy popular en Estados Unidos, tanto para uso policial como entre particulares. El origen de este calibre fue el requerimiento por parte del FBI de un arma menos potente que el 10 mm Auto, a fin de reducir el riesgo de las balas perdidas y obtener un retroceso más manejable. El .40 S&amp;W se ha convertido en el calibre más usado por los cuerpos policiales de los Estados Unidos con los años, desplazando al 9 mm Parabellum. Además, se ha vuelto muy popular entre civiles. 
El motivo de esto es que mantiene un logrado equilibrio de prestaciones. El retroceso es poco mayor al de una 9 mm, lo que le hace manejable por cualquier persona. Sin embargo, el poder de detención es sensiblemente mayor, siendo mucho más probable derribar a un blanco de un disparo, sin usar munición especial, que con una 9 Luger. La perforación, si bien no llega a la del 9 mm, es adecuada y superior al viejo .45 ACP. Esta característica la hace ideal para el uso policial, ya que una excesiva penetración reduce el poder de detención, como es el caso del 9 × 19 mm Parabellum. La combinación de estas prestaciones le ha hecho muy flexible en su uso en situaciones de defensa personal, y la precisión es lo bastante buena para su uso deportivo.
Además de pistolas, ya existen algunos modelos de subfusiles para este calibre, usados por grupos de asalto policiales que ya usaban pistolas con esa munición. 
</ES>
<FR>
Le .40 S&amp;W est un calibre de cartouche développé conjointement par les fabricants d'armes américains Smith &amp; Wesson et Winchester à la fin des années 1980. Cette munition est principalement employée aux États-Unis par les forces de l'ordre qui l'ont adoptée à l'initiative du FBI. Elle utilise des balles d'un diamètre de 0.40 pouce (soit 40 centièmes de pouce) d'un poids variant de 105 à 200 grains (6,8 à 13,0 g). Elle ne porte aucune désignation métrique officielle, mais elle est parfois appelée 10 × 22 mm. 
Confronté au problème de « faible puissance d'arrêt » du 9 mm Parabellum après une grave fusillade à Miami le 11 avril 1986 lors de laquelle les agents spéciaux Benjamin P. Grogan et Jerry L. Dove (tous deux équipés de pistolets Smith &amp; Wesson Model 459 en 9 mm Parabellum) sont abattus et plusieurs autres grièvement blessés, le FBI cherche une munition plus performante et adopte à la fin des années 1980, une version allégée du 10 mm Auto tiré par le pistolet Smith &amp; Wesson 1076. 
Malgré l'échec technique du S&amp;W 1076, son fabricant lance une version civile de la nouvelle munition appelée .40 S&amp;W. Ses dimensions sont intermédiaires entre le 9 mm Parabellum et le .45 ACP, le recul qu'elle développe, très proche pour les deux chargements cités ici, est toutefois supérieur au 9 mm parabellum tout en demeurant inférieur à celui du .45 ACP. L'énergie cinétique est en revanche supérieure aux deux munitions dans son chargement le plus rapide (d'environ 25 %) et sensiblement équivalent au 9 mm et .45 ACP dans son chargement le plus lent. Le 10 mm auto ayant des performances balistiques supérieures, les partisans de ce calibre surnomment le .40 S&amp;W « short and weak », soit « court et faible ».

Cette nouvelle munition connut un rapide succès en Amérique du Nord, notamment avec le Glock 22 lancé en 1990, qui est le pistolet le plus répandu chez les policiers des États-Unis. La compacité relative de la munition permit aux fabricants d'armes chambrées en 9 mm Parabellum de proposer à peu de frais des versions de leurs modèles en calibre .40 S&amp;W, au prix d'une capacité de chargeur légèrement réduite. Ainsi, il existe dans ce calibre :
    des pistolets produits par les principaux fabricants d'armes (Smith &amp; Wesson, Glock, SIG Sauer, Heckler &amp; Koch, Walther, Beretta, CZ, Steyr, etc.) ;
    des carabines semi-automatiques de police (Beretta Cx4 Storm, Ruger PC4, Taurus CT .40) ;
    des pistolets-mitrailleurs (Taurus/FAMAE MT .40, HK MP5/40 et UMP-40).

Ces armes sont destinées en premier lieu aux SWAT et à leurs équivalents sud-américains (notamment au Brésil).
Les caractéristiques du.40 S&amp;W peuvent varier en fonction des chargements et de la longueur du canon de l'arme qui la tire, elle présente néanmoins comme caractéristiques significatives :

    diamètre de la balle de 10 mm ;
    douille en cuivre longue de 22 mm ;
    balle chemisée de 8,7 g pour une vitesse à la bouche de 400 m/s soit 696 J ;
    balle chemisée de 11,6 g pour une vitesse initiale de 290 m/s soit 487 J.

https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/.40_S%26W
</FR>
</loc>