<loc>
<IT>
Controversa la nascita e il nome, questa munizione ha una storia molto intrigante, ideata dalla Smith &amp; Wesson e quindi denominata .41 SW Mag. (1963) venne prodotta dalla Remington dal 1964 e denominata .41 Rem.Mag. nome che viene riconosciuto tuttora. Altra storia interessante riguarda il primo film di Clint Eastwood "Ispettore Callaghan: Il Caso Scorpio è Tuo!" (1971)  dove l'ispettore Callaghan doveva avere una "robusta" S&amp;W mod.29 in .44 Magnum ma l'arma non era disponibile, cosi alla produzione 
fu consegnata una S&amp;W mod.57 in .41 Magnum che esteticamente è uguale alla "29" un segreto a conoscenza di pochi. La .41 Mag. nasce dalla sorella .410 Eimer, una cartuccia sperimentale che non vide mai la luce. Il diametro del proiettile è leggermente superiore ai classici .41" (9,83mm.) mentre la .41 Rem.Mag ha un diametro di 10,41mm. La .41 nasce su esigenza della polizia USA di avere una munizione con potere d'arresto superiore alla .357 Mag. ma non ingovernabile come una .44 Mag. 
La .41 sembrava un ottimo compromesso e per lungo tempo fu usata con buoni risultati, ma film e mercato finirono per sacrificarla alla maggiore .44. 

http://www.tiropratico.com/ammunition/pagine/41remmag.html


La cartuccia calibro .41 Remigton Magnum venne commercializzata dalla Smith &amp; Wesson nel 1964 insieme al revolver modello 57. Questa cartuccia venne originariamente concepita e realizzata per colmare la differenza (in termini di energia cinetica) che esisteva tra il .357 Magnum ed il .44 Magnum (v. voci a se). Inizialmente erano disponibili SOLO due tipi di caricamenti per questa cartuccia, uno ad alta velocità con palla semiblindata per impieghi venatori, ed uno a bassa velocità con palla in Piombo per impieghi di carattere generale. 
Quest'ultima munizione era anche destinata, nell'ottica degli ideatori, ad essere impiegata dalle Forze di Polizia per i loro compiti istituzionali. Dal punto di vista pratico, il .41 Magnum soddisfò le attese dal momento che offriva una maggiore energia cinetica rispetto al .357 Magnum, ma generava meno rinculo rispetto ad un .44 Magnum. Tuttavia, invece di acqusire una diffusione sempre maggiore tra le Forze di Polizia, la cartuccia si diffuse sempre di più tra i cacciatori di quei Paesi (primo fra tutti gli USA) 
in cui era consentito svolgere attività venatoria con le armi corte. Questo non era stato previsto dai tecnici della Smith &amp; Wesson!! Il problema fu in parte dovuto al fatto che il primo caricamento a comparire sul mercato (che per un po' di tempo rimase anche l'unico) non faceva altro che duplicare le prestazioni del .44 Magnum. Fu forse per questo motivo che i responsabili delle varie Forze di Polizia americane dettero, fin da subito, SCARSA importanza a questa cartuccia.

https://www.grurifrasca.net/oldsite/Sito/Ricarica/pistole/41Rmag.html
</IT>
<EN>
The .41 Remington Magnum or 10.4×33mmR as it is known in unofficial metric designation, is a center fire firearms cartridge primarily developed for use in large-frame revolvers, introduced in 1964 by the Remington Arms Company, intended for hunting and law enforcement purposes. 
In 1963, Elmer Keith and Bill Jordan, with some help from Skeeter Skelton, petitioned Smith &amp; Wesson, Remington, and Norma to produce a pistol and ammunition in .41 caliber which would fall between the extant .357 Magnum and .44 Magnum cartridges in ballistic performance, and at the same time address perceived shortcomings with those loads. While as early as 1955 Keith had suggested a new, medium-powered ".41 Special" cartridge, this idea was passed over in favor of the higher-powered "Magnum" option, 
and the Special survives only as a custom wildcat cartridge, bearing roughly the same relation to the .41 Remington Magnum as the .38 Special does to the .357 Magnum and as the .44 Special does to the .44 Magnum.
The .357 Magnum suffered from restricted terminal ballistic effectiveness in the early 1960s, as jacketed hollow point bullets were not yet commonly available, and the manufacturer's standard loadings consisted of simple lead bullets. The powerful .44 Magnum, primarily a heavy hunting round, was considered overkill for police use, generating too much recoil for control under rapid fire. In addition, the revolvers chambered for the .44 were considered too large, bulky, and heavy for police carry.
Keith's original vision called for dual power levels in the .41, a heavy magnum load pushing a 210-grain (14 g) JHP at a muzzle velocity of 1300–1400 feet per second (ft/s), and a milder police loading which was to send a 200-grain (13 g) semiwadcutter downrange at around 900 ft/s.
These plans went awry due to an ongoing fascination in the firearms community with high-powered cartridges; Remington was swayed by this community's influence and instead of following Keith's blueprint chose to emphasize the performance of the new cartridge. As a result, the .41 "Magnum" load was released at an advertised 1500 ft/s, and even the "light" police loading was introduced with a 210 grain lead semiwadcutter "warmed up" to about 1,150 ft/s. 
Unfortunately, the police load as delivered was regarded as overpowered by most law enforcement agencies, many of whom were still using .38 Special revolvers.
Additionally, Smith &amp; Wesson simply adapted their large N-frame revolvers for the new cartridge, which did not address size and weight concerns. The Model 58, targeted for the law enforcement market, was introduced on July 10, 1964. Weighing in at 41 ounces, the Model 58 compared unfavorably with other popular revolvers available at the time, such as Smith's own 34 ounce Model 10 in .38 Special.
These combined factors mostly eliminated the .41 Magnum from consideration for its intended market as a law enforcement firearm, although it continued to be touted as such and was adopted by a few law enforcement agencies. Ultimately, the greater round capacities of most semi-automatic, magazine fed handguns has eclipsed the traditional 6 shot revolver for law enforcement work though revolvers in general are still more prevalent in the field. 
Smith &amp; Wesson produced a high-end, premium revolver in .41 Magnum caliber, the Model 57, almost identical to the .44 Magnum-chambered Model 29. Magnum Research's Desert Eagle division produced a .41 Remington Magnum in their semi-automatic Mark VII. Sturm Ruger began producing their Blackhawk series single action revolver in the mid-1960s in .41 Magnum and is still in production today. 
A couple of manufacturers have produced lever-action rifles chambered in .41 Magnum. Marlin produced four variants of its Model 1894, including the 1894S (20" barrel, blued, straight stock), 1894FG (20" barrel, blued, pistol-grip stock), 1894SS LTD (16" barrel, stainless steel, straight stock) and 1894 CCL (20" octagonal barrel, blued, straight stock.) However, they do not currently offer any model chambered for it. Only Henry currently produces one, having introduced a .41 Magnum variant of their Big Boy Steel model in 2016.

https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/.41_Remington_Magnum
</EN>
<DE></DE>
<ES>
El .41 Remington Magnum es un cartucho para revólver estrenado en 1964 por la Smith &amp; Wesson, para su revólver Modelo 57. Con él se pretendía cubrir el hueco entre el .357 Magnum y el .44 Magnum con un calibre intermedio entre ambos.
El .41 Magnum nunca ha sido demasiado popular. Esto es así porque para la defensa personal, con un .357 Magnum es más que suficiente, mientras que para la caza mayor, se queda corto en comparación con el .44 Magnum. A medio camino entre los dos, no compite con ninguno en sus respectivas parcelas. Yéndose al limbo de la tierra de nadie.
Sin embargo, para personas que por algún motivo deseen un calibre muy potente, pero no consideren manejable el .44 Magnum, es una buena opción. Con 210 gramos de peso, es capaz de desarrollar una velocidad de 400 m/s y 1000 Julios. 

https://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/.41_Remington_Magnum
</ES>
<FR>
Le .41 Remington Magnum, ou simplement .41 Magnum, est un calibre de cartouche essentiellement employé pour les revolvers. Cette munition a été développée à partir de 1963 avec la volonté de s'insérer entre la 357 magnum et la 44 magnum. 

https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/.41_Magnum
</FR>
</loc>