<loc>
<IT>
La .44 Magnum è una cartuccia per arma corta prodotta da Smith &amp; Wesson negli U.S.A. a partire dal 1955.
Realizzata con il contributo di Elmer Keith ed è stata considerata per molto tempo la più potente cartuccia realizzata per arma corta. 
Deriva dalla calibro ".44 Special" per allungamento del bossolo ad una lunghezza di 32,64 mm. Inizialmente la pallottola aveva un peso di 250 grani che fu poi ridotto a 240 (circa 15,6 grammi). Per la cartuccia .44 Magnum fu creato il revolver “Smith &amp; Wesson 29” chiamato anche "revolver dalle cinque viti", o "S&amp;W modello .44 Magnum". 
Ha avuto molto successo specialmente negli U.S.A. dove sono molto apprezzati i grossi calibri (in America del Nord con queste cartucce è permessa anche la caccia con il revolver). In Europa il successo è stato minore, poiché, essendo permessa la caccia solo con l'arma lunga, si trova più conveniente usare munizioni di maggior potenza (per il cinghiale, per es., si preferisce la .30-06 Springfield). 
Per l'arma corta molti ritengono che la cartuccia in questione sia di una certa potenza e di non facile gestibilità, preferendole ad es. la .357 Magnum, dotata anch'essa di buona potenza, ma più gestibile. 

https://it.wikipedia.org/wiki/.44_Magnum
</IT>
<EN>
The .44 Remington Magnum, or simply .44 Magnum (10.9×33mmR), and frequently .44 Mag, is a rimmed, large-bore cartridge originally designed for revolvers. After its introduction, it was quickly adopted for carbines and rifles. Despite the ".44" designation, guns chambered for the .44 Magnum round, and its parent, the .44 Special, use 0.429 in (10.9 mm) diameter bullets.
The .44 Magnum is based on the .44 Special case but lengthened and loaded to higher pressures for greater velocity (and thus, energy). The .44 Magnum has since been eclipsed in power by the .454 Casull, and most recently by the .460 S&amp;W Magnum and .500 S&amp;W Magnum, among others; nevertheless, it has remained one of the most popular commercial large-bore magnum cartridges. 
When loaded to its maximum and with heavy, deeply penetrating bullets, the .44 Magnum cartridge is suitable for short-range hunting of all North American game—though at the cost of heavy recoil and muzzle flash when fired in handguns, less so in carbines and rifles.
The .44 Magnum delivers a large, heavy bullet with high velocity for a handgun. In its full-powered form, it produces so much recoil and muzzle blast that it is generally considered to be unsuitable for use as a police weapon. Rapid fire is difficult and strenuous on the user's hands, especially for shooters of smaller build or with small hands.
Although marketed as a .44 caliber, the .44 Magnum and its parent .44 Special are actually .429-.430 caliber. The .44 designation is a carryover from the early measurements of "heeled" bullets, used in the later 19th century. In those times, bullets were measured on the outside of the cartridge, not the inside of the cartridge. 
After the .44 S&amp;W Russian was developed, the forefather of the .44 Special and thus the .44 Magnum, the measurement of bullet caliber was taken from inside of the cartridge, resulting in .429 caliber. Instead of confusing buyers who were used to .44 caliber revolvers, the original .44 designation was kept for market recognition.
Some gun styles are more comfortable to use when shooting this caliber. Many shooters find the rounded grip shape of the single action better for handling heavy recoil than the grip shape of double-action revolvers, which have a shoulder on top of the grip. Many shooters consider the ideal type of grip for heavy recoiling guns to be the longer "Bisley" style single action grip, and it can be found on single actions from Ruger (models marked "Bisley") and Freedom Arms, as well as many custom makers

https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/.44_Magnum
</EN>
<DE>
Die .44 Remington Magnum, meist nur .44 Magnum oder 44er Magnum genannt, ist eine leistungsstarke Patrone für Kurzwaffen. Sie wurde in erster Linie für die Verwendung in Revolvern ausgelegt, daher besitzt die Patronenhülse einen überstehenden Rand. Es wurden aber auch einige Pistolen und Unterhebelrepetierer entwickelt, die die .44 Magnum verschießen können. Der Name gibt das nominelle Kaliber der Patrone an, das 0,429 Zoll (10,8966 mm) beträgt, der Zusatz Magnum weist auf höhere ballistische Leistungen innerhalb dieser Kaliberklasse hin. 
Von den späten 1920er Jahren bis 1955 experimentierte Elmer Keith mit Patronen des Kalibers .44 Special, da er diese als ideale Revolver-Patrone betrachtete. Er ging nach der Methode Versuch und Irrtum vor. Dabei füllte er immer mehr Schießpulver in die Hülsen. Über seine Erfolge schrieb er zahlreiche Artikel, Briefe und Bücher. Daraufhin entwickelte Remington 1955 die Patrone .44 Magnum. Gleichzeitig präsentierte der Waffenhersteller Smith &amp; Wesson aus Springfield, Massachusetts, mit dem Modell 29 erstmals einen sechsschüssigen Revolver der Kaliberbezeichnung .44 Magnum. 
Richtig populär wurde die .44 Magnum durch den Film Dirty Harry. Zu ihrer Markteinführung war sie die stärkste Patrone für Faustfeuerwaffen, wurde aber von der bereits 1959 vorgestellten .454 Casull übertroffen, wobei letztere wiederum moderneren Patronen wie der .460 S&amp;W Magnum und der .500 S&amp;W unterlegen ist. Die in manchen Filmen getätigten Aussagen zur absoluten Überlegenheit der .44 Magnum resultieren daraus, dass das SAAMI die .454 Casull erst 1997 als Standardpatrone akzeptiert hat.
In Abhängigkeit von der Laborierung und vor allem der Lauflänge der verwendeten Schusswaffe erzielen Patronen des Kalibers .44 Magnum Geschossenergien an der Mündung von knapp unter 1000 bis knapp über 1500 Joule. Gebräuchliche Lauflängen liegen zwischen 3 und 12 Zoll, üblich sind 6 bis 6½ Zoll, entsprechend 152–165 mm.
Erst in jüngerer Vergangenheit haben sich auch halbautomatische Selbstladepistolen wie zum Beispiel der Desert Eagle von Israel Military Industries für bekannte Magnum-Kaliber wie .44 am Markt etabliert.
Wegen ihrer Größe, ihres Gewichtes und ihres extremen Schussverhaltens eignen sich Revolver des Kalibers .44 Magnum kaum zum ständigen Führen, etwa im Bereich des Personenschutzes. Ihre Verwendung beschränkt sich häufig auf das Sportschießen und den jagdlichen Einsatz (z. B. zur Abgabe des Fangschusses). Zum Schutz gegen Geschosse des Kalibers .44 Magnum ist eine beschusshemmende Weste der Kategorie NIJ 0101.04 Typ IIIA bzw. SK 2 nach TR PFA erforderlich. 

https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/.44_Magnum
</DE>
<ES>
El .44 Remington Magnum, o simplemente .44 Magnum, 10,95 × 33 mmR según el sistema métrico, es un cartucho para revólver diseñado por Remington para el revólver Modelo 29 de Smith &amp; Wesson en 1955.
El .44 Remington Magnum, o simplemente .44 Magnum, es un cartucho de gran calibre diseñado originalmente para revólveres. Tras su introducción fue rápidamente adoptado para su uso en carabinas y fusiles. A pesar de la designación ".44", todas las armas diseñadas para el cartucho .44 Magnum, y su antecesor, el .44 Special, utilizan proyectiles de 0,429 pulgadas de diámetro aproximadamente. (10,9 mm).
El .44 Magnum se basa en un casquillo alargado de .44 Special, con una superior carga de pólvora para una mayor energía. Poco después de su introducción, el .44 Magnum fue eclipsando en el poder al cartucho .454 Casull, y otros, y sigue siendo el más popular cartucho Magnum de gran calibre. Cuando se carga al máximo y con un proyectil de gran peso y máxima penetración, el cartucho .44 Magnum es adecuado para la caza de todas las especies de América del Norte, a costa de un gran retroceso y fogonazo. 
Sin embargo, los cartuchos con cargas de baja velocidad y balas ligeras tienen menos retroceso y son más precisos al disparar. 
Se trata, básicamente, de un .44 Special que en lugar de alcanzar una velocidad de salida de 250 metros por segundo alcanza los 450 metros por segundo. Fue diseñado para la caza mayor con pistola de animales de la envergadura del reno o el oso.
El .44 Magnum no es un calibre adecuado para la defensa personal de la mayoría de personas, porque su gran potencia provoca un gran retroceso, lo que hace que sea difícil de manejar para casi cualquiera. Además, existen calibres más modestos pero que cumplen bien con la tarea de derribar un blanco humano, sin tener que ser inmanejables.
Con el paso del tiempo, además de revólveres también lo han usado algunas carabinas y pistolas semiautomáticas.

https://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/.44_Magnum
</ES>
<FR>
La cartouche .44 Magnum a un calibre réel de 10,92 millimètres et sa désignation métrique est 11 × 33 mm R. Sa particularité, héritée de la cartouche .44-40 Winchester, est de pouvoir être tirée dans un revolver (par exemple, le Smith &amp; Wesson Model 29, le Colt Anaconda, le Taurus Raging Bull…) comme dans une carabine (la Winchester 94, la Rossi Puma, la Ruger Deerfield…) ainsi que dans quelques pistolets semi-automatiques dont le célèbre Desert Eagle. 
La cartouche de .44 Magnum a été développée par la firme américaine Remington, après la Seconde Guerre mondiale, dans le but d'offrir une munition polyvalente, très puissante, pour la chasse du grand gibier nord-américain et européen (chevreuil, cerf de Virginie et cerf, notamment).
Immortalisé au cinéma au poing de Clint Eastwood en 1971, le S&amp;W Model 29 de calibre .44 Magnum est resté de 1955 à 1982 le plus puissant revolver au monde fabriqué en série, jusqu'à l'apparition des calibres .454 Casull (11,43 mm, mais fort peu commercialisé alors), .50 Action Express (12,7 mm) en 1989, et du .500 S&amp;W Magnum en 2003.
Le .44 Magnum demeure une munition très puissante, destinée avant tout à la chasse et au tir à la silhouette métallique (jusqu'à 200 mètres) ou sur quilles. C'est un calibre trop gros (11 mm) pour le tir de compétition UIT-ISSF en gros calibres (de 7,62 à 9,65 mm) pour la discipline « pistolet sport » à 25 mètres, où il serait trop fatigant à utiliser sur 60 coups.
On peut utiliser la cartouche de .44 Special (qui est la munition dont elle est issue) dans les revolvers chambrant la .44 Magnum, mais pas la cartouche .44-40 Winchester. 

https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/.44_Magnum
</FR>
</loc>