<loc>
<IT>
La .45 ACP (Automatic Colt Pistol) è un tipo di munizione per pistola sviluppata e prodotta negli USA.
Venne ideato insieme con la pistola semiautomatica Colt modello 1905, a seguito di una richiesta specifica dell'esercito statunitense. 
La cartuccia ha un bossolo in ottone di tipo rimless, con innesco large pistol di tipo Berdan o Boxer. Nella configurazione standard monta una palla FMJ (Full Metal Jacket) da 230 grani, ma possono essere utilizzate palle di diverso profilo e peso, sia in piombo che blindate.
La cartuccia .45 ACP è dotata di un elevatissimo potere d'arresto, una buona precisione ed un rinculo relativamente contenuto; caratteristiche che ne fanno uno dei calibri più apprezzati nella difesa personale, soprattutto negli Stati Uniti. I lati negativi risiedono nella scarsa forza di penetrazione e nella gittata modesta, se paragonato ad esempio al 9mm x 19 Parabellum. 
Un'apposita commissione (Thompson-La Garde) si occupò di valutare il calibro migliore per sostituire il .38 Colt, caratterizzato da uno scarso potere di arresto (stopping power). La commissione decise, dopo alcune prove non esenti da errori, di adottare per l'U.S. Army la cartuccia .45 ACP prodotta dalla Winchester Repeating co. e dalla Colt mfg co., insieme alla pistola che l'ha resa celebre, la Colt 1911. È rimasta in dotazione all'esercito statunitense per oltre 80 anni, per poi essere sostituita dal calibro 9 mm Parabellum nel 1985. 
Sebbene non sia più la munizione d'ordinanza adottata dall'esercito statunitense, il .45 ACP continua a far parte della dotazione di reparti speciali quali la Delta Force, i Navy SEALs ed anche la SWAT. Sul mercato civile il .45 ACP è ancora apprezzato dagli statunitensi, ed è per questo motivo una delle munizioni più diffuse e di più facile reperibilità, anche dal punto di vista della attrezzatura e componentistica per la ricarica. Infine è da molti considerata la cartuccia prediletta per difesa personale, in particolare nella configurazione JHP (Jacketed Hollow Point, blindata a punta cava).
In Italia non è stata permessa la vendita del .45 ACP fino al 1996, perché considerato munizionamento di arma da guerra, portando allo sviluppo, specifico per il mercato italiano, della cartuccia .45 HP, molto simile (21 mm è la lunghezza del bossolo dell'HP contro i 22 mm di quello dell'ACP, il diametro è identico 11,43 mm). 

https://it.wikipedia.org/wiki/.45_ACP
</IT>
<EN>
The .45 ACP (Automatic Colt Pistol) or .45 Auto (11.43×23mm) is a handgun cartridge designed by John Moses Browning in 1904, for use in his prototype Colt semi-automatic pistol. After successful military trials, it was adopted as the standard chambering for Colt's M1911 pistol. The round was developed due to a lack of stopping power experienced in the Moro Rebellion using the .38 Long Colt. This experience and the Thompson–LaGarde Tests of 1904, led the Army and the Cavalry to decide a minimum of .45 caliber was required in a new handgun.
The standard issue military .45 ACP round has a 230-grain bullet that travels at approximately 830 feet per second when fired from the government issue M1911A1 pistol. It operates at a relatively low maximum chamber pressure rating of 21,000 psi (145 MPa) (compared to 35,000 psi/241 MPa for 9mm Parabellum), which due to a low bolt thrust helps extend service life of weapons. Due to standard pressure .45 ACP rounds fired from handguns and submachine guns are inherently subsonic, and are useful in suppressed weapons to eliminate the sonic boom.
Today, most NATO militaries use sidearms chambered for the 9×19mm Parabellum cartridge, but the effectiveness of the .45 ACP cartridge has ensured its continued popularity with large caliber sport shooters, especially in the United States. In 1985, the .45 ACP M1911A1 pistol was replaced by the Beretta M9 9mm pistol as the main sidearm of the U.S. military, which in turn was replaced with the SIG Sauer P320 designated M17 for the full size and M18 for the compact. 
The .45 ACP is an effective combat pistol cartridge that combines accuracy and stopping power for use against human targets. It has relatively low muzzle blast and flash, and it produces a stout, but manageable recoil in handguns, made worse in compact models. The standard issue military .45 ACP round has a 230-grain bullet that travels at approximately 830 feet per second when fired from the government issue M1911A1 pistol and approximately 950 feet per second from the M1A1 Thompson submachine gun. The cartridge also comes in various specialty rounds of varying weights and performance levels.
It operates at a relatively low maximum chamber pressure rating of 21,000 psi (145 MPa) (compared to 35,000 psi/241 MPa for 9mm Parabellum and .40 S&amp;W, 37,500 psi/259 MPa for 10mm Auto, 40,000 psi/276 MPa for .357 SIG), which due to a low bolt thrust helps extend service life of weapons in which it is used. Some makers of pistols chambered in .45 ACP do not certify them to use Plus P ammunition.
In its non-expanding full metal jacket (FMJ) version, the .45 ACP cartridge has a reputation for effectiveness against human targets because its heavy mass has the capacity to penetrate tissue deeply and damage the central nervous system, and its large 11.5mm diameter creates a more substantial permanent wound channel than other calibers, which can lower blood pressure rapidly if critical organs of the circulatory system are hit.
In its expanding hollow point form, it is also particularly effective against human targets. In tests against ballistic gelatin, a 185 grain hollow point traveling at 1,050 feet per second expanded to about .76 inches. This is a significantly large permanent wound cavity for a handgun projectile. For those who follow the energy dump and/or hydrostatic shock theories of wounding ballistics, this is ideal. 
While slightly decreasing penetration and likewise the chance of hitting a vital organ, a large diameter wound will cause more blood loss. There is also a reduced likelihood of overpenetration, meaning that it is more likely that the projectile will transfer all of its kinetic energy to the intended target, thus more reliably incapacitating them.
Drawbacks for military use include the cartridge's large size, weight, increased material costs in comparison to the smaller, flatter shooting NATO standard 9×19mm Parabellum cartridge, which uses less powder, brass, and lead per round. Standard 9mm NATO ammunition has limited armor penetration capability − a deficiency with .45 ACP whose large, slow bullet does not penetrate armor to any great extent. The low muzzle velocity also makes the bullet drop over long ranges, making hits more difficult; however, it is important to note that the vast majority of self-defense situations involving handguns typically occur at close ranges.
Recent testing of the three major police and military calibers by the Federal Bureau of Investigation found that the .45 ACP was no more effective with regard to terminal ballistics than either 9 x 19mm Parabellum or .40 S&amp;W. After two years of testing, one of the final FBI comments was that services that adopt (or stay with) .40 S&amp;W or .45 ACP did so at the risk of increased recoil and a possible reduction in accuracy as 9 x 19mm with premium quality ammunition had nearly exactly the same performance. A factor rated by the recent FBI testing was accuracy and time to recover. The .45 ACP handguns ranked last, largely due to increased recoil.
Because of its large diameter and straight-walled design, the .45 ACP geometry is the highest power-per-pressure production, repeating round in existence. This is because of the higher powers achievable with .45 Super, and +P loads. Because of these inherent low pressures of the standard pressure round, however, compensators and brakes have little effect until +P and Super loads are utilized.

https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/.45_ACP
</EN>
<DE>
Der Munitionstyp .45 ACP („0.45 inch Automatic Colt Pistol“) wurde erstmals bei der US-amerikanischen Pistole Colt M1911 verwendet. Sein Kaliber (Geschossdurchmesser) beträgt 0,45 Zoll oder umgerechnet 11,43 mm.
Die Patrone wurde von John Moses Browning im Jahre 1905 entwickelt. 
In den frühen 1900er-Jahren zeigte sich in der Kavallerie der US-Streitkräfte, dass die neu eingeführte .38er-Kaliber-Munition im Gefecht nicht die alte .45er-Kaliber-Munition ersetzen konnte. Die Mannstoppwirkung der .38er lag zu niedrig, und die Kavallerie verlangte eine Munition, deren Mannstopp-Leistung auf dem Niveau der alten .45er Colt lag.
Colt und Browning arbeiteten im Jahre 1904 an einer .41er Patrone. Als die Kavallerie im Jahre 1905 nach einer .45er verlangte, wurde der .41er Prototyp vergrößert. Das Originalprojektil hatte ein Gewicht von 13 g (200 grain) und eine Mündungsgeschwindigkeit von 275 m/s. Später wurde sie auf ein Gewicht von 15 g (230 grain) mit einer Mündungsgeschwindigkeit von 260 m/s modifiziert.
Die .45er ACP liegt somit in der Leistung mit der .40 S&amp;W gleichauf und leicht unter der der .45 Colt.
Diese Patrone ist sehr effektiv zur Selbstverteidigung, da sie eine starke Mannstopp-Wirkung hat. Der Rückstoß und das Mündungsfeuer der Munition sind vergleichsweise gering. Wegen ihrer geringen Durchschlagswirkung eignet sie sich aber nur bedingt zur Bekämpfung von Gegnern, die Schutzkleidung tragen. Das Gewicht und die Materialkosten sind im Vergleich zur 9-mm-Patrone höher.
Als Dienstkaliber in den US-amerikanischen Streitkräften sowie bei den Polizeien der Kommunen und der Bundesstaaten sowie der US-Regierung wurde die .45 ACP größtenteils durch das Kaliber 9 × 19 mm ersetzt (außer bei einigen Spezialeinheiten, die modifizierte 1911A1-Pistolen, HK-SOCOM-Mk. 23 und die HK P12 verwenden). 

https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/.45_ACP
</DE>
<ES>
El .45 ACP (Automatic Colt Pistol), también llamado .45 Auto o 11,43 x 23, es un cartucho desarrollado por J. M. Browning en 1905 para la pistola M1911. Adoptado oficialmente en 1911 por el Ejército de los Estados Unidos, estuvo en servicio hasta 1985, fecha en la que fueron sustituidos por el 9 x 19.​ Este cambio se produjo por varios motivos. El calibre 9 mm es el usado en toda la OTAN; tiene un retroceso más suave, por tanto resulta más manejable y necesita menos entrenamiento; 
sin que el tamaño de la empuñadura resultara excesivo, una pistola de 9 mm moderna puede cargar 15 cartuchos frente a las 7 de la clásica M1911; el 9 mm perfora mejor que el .45; la munición resulta más barata y, al ser más ligera y pequeña, ofrece ventajas logísticas. Sin embargo, muchos militares estadounidenses siguen prefiriendo la contundencia del .45.
El cartucho .45 ACP tiene su origen en las amargas experiencias del Ejército estadounidense en Filipinas, donde los revólveres del .38 Corto muchas veces no eran capaces de detener de un disparo a un atacante decidido y, a menudo, bajo los efectos de alguna droga. Debido a esto, se tuvieron que reutilizar los viejos revólveres "del oeste" que disparaban el .45 Colt. Un estudio posterior concluyó que el calibre .45 era el único aceptable si se quería un arma capaz de derribar de un disparo a cualquier hombre.​ A comienzos de siglo XX, el Ejército de los Estados Unidos adoptó una pistola semiautomática, la M1911, que usaba el cartucho .45 ACP, de eficacia similar al .45 Colt de revólver.
El .45 ACP paseó su contundente eficacia, en las pistolas y subfusiles estadounidenses en ambas guerras mundiales, y por Corea y Vietnam.
En los Estados Unidos es un cartucho popular entre civiles y hay departamentos de policía que, abandonando el 9 x 19 Parabellum, han adoptado el .45 ACP. 

https://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/.45_ACP
</ES>
<FR>
Le .45 ACP (Automatic Colt Pistol) ou .45 Auto, ou encore 11,43, est un calibre de cartouche développé par John Browning en 1904 pour son prototype de pistolet semi-automatique .45, qui donnera naissance au Colt M1911 (« Colt 45 ») en 1911.
Cette munition est surtout employée aux États-Unis où elle constitue une solide tradition. De nombreux pistolets et quelques pistolets mitrailleurs sont chambrés pour cette munition. Cette munition est également tirée dans quelques revolvers à l'aide de clips, notamment les Smith &amp; Wesson M1917 et 625. 
La désignation .45 renvoie à des pouces (0,45 pouce soit 45 centièmes de pouce), ce qui correspond à un diamètre de balle de 11,43 mm. La désignation métrique de la munition est 11,43 × 23 mm. Elle est appelée « 11,25 mm » en Argentine et en Norvège.
Dérivée du .38 ACP, elle répondit à la demande expresse de la cavalerie américaine qui avait testé au tout début des années 1900 des revolvers de calibre 9 mm en remplacement de ses modèles chambrés en .45 Colt (également nommé .45 Long Colt). Colt et Browning travaillaient en 1904 sur une arme chambrée en .41, soit un calibre d'environ 10 mm, qu'ils déclinèrent en 1905 en .45 sur la demande de la cavalerie. La première munition, comprenant une balle de 13 g animée d'une vitesse à la bouche de 275 m/s, laissa rapidement place à une balle de 15 g à 260 m/s.
Le .45 ACP, en raison de sa balle lourde et lente, provoque un recul (c'est-à-dire une quantité de mouvement) important comparativement à l'énergie cinétique qu'il développe. Son diamètre élevé limite la capacité des armes (le chargeur d'un Colt M1911 ne contient que 7 cartouches) et nécessite plus de ressources de production, ce qui constitue un inconvénient important en temps de guerre. Sa faible vélocité fut un inconvénient majeur durant la Seconde Guerre mondiale car elle limitait la portée des pistolets mitrailleurs américains tels que le M1 et le M3A1 à une cinquantaine de mètres, soit une allonge environ deux fois inférieure à celle du MP40 utilisé par les forces allemandes.
Toutefois, l'importance de son calibre et sa puissance modérée présentent plusieurs avantages :
    son projectile de fort diamètre transmet, à taux d'expansion égal, davantage d'énergie à la cible qu'un plus petit calibre. Cela augmente les chances d'endommager un organe vital, ce qui se traduit par un bon pouvoir d'arrêt ;
    sa puissance modérée ne provoque pas d'importantes flammes de bouche et détonation ;
    elle développe une pression en chambre inférieure à celle d'autres munitions d'armes de poing donc ménage l'arme comme le tireur (en causant un recul moins violent que les munitions comparables) ;
    elle réduit la capacité du projectile à traverser la cible, fait intéressant car un blessé nécessitera alors une intervention médicale plus lourde, un chirurgien devant extraire la balle qui ne sera pas ressortie d'elle-même ;
    sa balle ayant une vitesse sub-sonique rend possible l'utilisation efficace d'un modérateur de son sans besoin d'utiliser des cartouches spécifiques.
Véritable tradition américaine, elle est en concurrence avec le 9 mm Parabellum qui a tendance à s'imposer dans les armées. L'armée américaine abandonna ainsi le vénérable Colt M1911 pour le M9 au cours des années 1980 à la suite de quoi de nombreuses unités spéciales se dotèrent à nouveau d'armes chambrées en .45 ACP. 

https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/.45_ACP
</FR>
</loc>