<loc>
<IT>
La cartuccia calibro .460 Smith &amp; Wesson Magnum (N.B. questa cartuccia è altresì nota come .460 S&amp;W Magnum, .460 Revolver Magnum, 12,7x46R o come 12,7x46 Rimmed Magnum) è un derivato parziale della cartuccia calibro .45 Long Colt, ottenuto per semplice allugamento del corpo del bossolo fino a raggiungere una lunghezza complessiva di 45,45mm. In altre parole, questa cartuccia è stata creata nello STESSO modo in cui è stata realizzata la cartuccia calibro .454 Casull. Storicamente parlando, il .460 S&amp;W Magnum è stato sviluppato nei primissimi anni del XXI secolo dai tecnici della S&amp;W, ma è stato commercializzato solo nel 2005. L'idea era quella di realizzare una NUOVA cartuccia  per arma corta, ESTREMAMENTE potente, da utilizzare per la caccia (N.B. ovviamente solo nei Paesi ove ciò è consentito !!). Questa nuova cartuccia impiegava palla del diametro nominale di 11,7mm (N.B. in realtà il diametro è di 11,48mm, cioè di 45 centesimi di pollice !!) ed era basata su di un convenzionale bossolo da revolver (rimmed case). Lo sviluppo di questa nuova munizione dalle prestazioni del tutto esuberanti, ha richiesto la realizzazione di un nuovo telaio (frame), diverso e più robusto rispetto al convenzionale telaio N (N-frame) da lungo tempo impiegato dalla S&amp;W per i suoi revolver più potenti. Il caricamento originale sviluppato in fase prototipale impiegava una palla da 200grs. (12,9 GRAMMI) spinta a circa 700m/s, il che significava avere a disposizione oltre 320Kgm alla bocca (N.B. vale a dire circa 3175 Joule !!). Così com'era avvenuto per il .500 S&amp;W magnum, anche in questo caso lo sviluppo venne affidato dalla S&amp;W alla Cor-Bon di Detroit (Stato del Michigan, USA).

(https://www.grurifrasca.net/oldsite/Sito/Ricarica/pistole/460SW.html)
</IT>
<EN>
The .460 S&amp;W Magnum round is a powerful revolver cartridge designed for long-range handgun hunting in the Smith &amp; Wesson Model 460 revolver.
The .460 S&amp;W round is a lengthened, more powerful version of the popular .454 Casull, itself a longer and more powerful version of the .45 Colt. For this reason, the .460 S&amp;W Magnum could be considered an example of a "super magnum". Consequently, firearms that fire .460 S&amp;W are usually capable of firing the less powerful .454 Casull, .45 Colt, and .45 Schofield rounds, but this must be verified with each firearm's manufacturer. For instance, some lever-action firearms are designed to handle cartridges within a certain length and bullet profile range. 
The reverse, however, does not apply: .45 Schofield, .45 Colt, and .454 Casull handguns generally cannot safely fire .460 S&amp;W rounds — nor can they even chamber the .460 S&amp;W because of the longer case length. It is also the most versatile big bore revolver being able to fire four standardized cartridges, as well as lesser known rimmed and straightwall cartridges of .45 caliber that predate the .45 Colt. The .460 Smith and Wesson Magnum is built to handle both long-range hunting and Dangerous Game hunting and defensive performance.

Smith &amp; Wesson says that the .460 S&amp;W is the highest velocity revolver cartridge in the world, firing bullets at up to 2,409 feet per second (734 m/s). The .460 cartridge achieves high velocities by operating at chamber pressures (65,000 psi max) normally reserved for magnum rifle cartridges. The recoil when shooting .45 Colt ammunition out of the S&amp;W .460 firearm is comparable to recoil from a 9mm or .380 load, due to the weight of the gun and lower chamber pressures. Since firearms chambered in .460 S&amp;W magnum can also fire cartridges of dissimilar trajectories, such as .45 Colt, S&amp;W provides an extra additional rear sight with the gun to compensate for bullet drop down range, depending on the user's load and shooting applications. 
With Buffalo Bore's loadings, the .460 S&amp;W can achieve 2,826 ftxlbf (3,832 J) of energy by driving a 300 grain .452 caliber bullet at 2,060 ft/s (630 m/s) and 2,860 ftxlbf (3,880 J) of energy by driving a heavier 360 grain .452 caliber bullet at 1,900 ft/s (580 m/s). For comparison, Hornady's 9249 load for the .500 S&amp;W Magnum cartridge offers slightly more energy at the muzzle, achieving 2,868 ftxlbf (3,888 J) by driving a 300 grain (19 g) FTX bullet at 2,075 ft/s (632 m/s). Buffalo Bore's loading for the .500 S&amp;W Magnum cartridge offers much less energy at the muzzle, achieving only 2,579 ftxlbf (3,497 J) by driving a 440 grain .500 caliber bullet at 1,625 ft/s (495 m/s).

(https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/.460_S%26W_Magnum)
</EN>
<DE>
Die .460 S&amp;W Magnum ist eine leistungsstarke Patrone und wird aus Revolvern verschossen. Leistungsgesteigerte Patronen dieser Art werden in Schießsportdisziplinen wie „Metallic Silhouette“ und in einigen Staaten zur Jagd eingesetzt. Beim BDMP Deutschland (Bund der Militär- und Polizeischützen e. V.) wird sie in den Disziplinen „Single Action Revolver“ und „Super Magnum“ geschossen. 
Nach der Vorstellung des X-Frame (extra großer Revolverrahmen) von Smith &amp; Wesson für das Kaliber .500 S&amp;W Magnum im Jahre 2003 war es nur eine Frage der Zeit, bis andere auf diesem Rahmen basierende Revolver erschienen (460XVR und 460V). S&amp;W wählte hier ein .45er Kaliber. Für die .460 S&amp;W Magnum wurde die Hülse der .454 Casull verlängert, um mehr Platz für das Pulver zu schaffen. Die .454 Casull ist wiederum eine verlängerte Version der .45 Colt. Revolver im Kaliber .460 S&amp;W Magnum können somit auch Patronen der Kaliber .454 Casull und .45 Colt verschießen. 

(https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/.460_S%26W_Magnum)
</DE>
<ES>
El .460 S&amp;W Magnum es un cartucho potente para revólver diseñado para caza con arma corta a larga distancia, y para el Smith &amp; Wesson M460. Fue diseñado en el año 2005.
Smith &amp; Wesson afirma que el .460 S&amp;W es el cartucho de revólver de más alta velocidad del mundo, disparando balas a 2330 pies por segundo (710 m/s). Con la nueva carga de Bore Buffalo, el .460 S&amp;W puede conseguir casi 2900 pie-libras de energía enviando una bala de 360 granos a 1900 ft/s (579 m/s).​ Por comparación, el .500 S&amp;W Magnum ofrece ligeramente más energía en boca, enviando una bala de 350 granos a 1975 ft/s (601 m/s) para un total de 3031 pie-libras.

(https://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/.460_S%26W_Magnum)
</ES>
<FR>
La .460 S&amp;W Magnum est une cartouche à grand vélocité destinée à la chasse longue distance à l'arme de poing et chambrée dans les revolvers S&amp;W modèle M460 et 460XVR à carcasse X, ainsi que la carabine à levier de sous garde Modèle 90 produite par Big Horn Armory depuis 2015 sur la base des Winchesters modèles 1886 et 1892 avec une carcasse renforcée. Annoncée en 2005 et développée en commun par Hornady (en) et Smith &amp; Wesson sur la base de la .454 Casull allongée de 10mm, elle-même développée sur la base du .45 Colt créé en 1872 et mise en service en 1873 dans la US Army.

(https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/.460_S%26W_Magnum)
</FR>
</loc>