<loc>
<IT>
La cartuccia calibro .475 Linebaugh (N.B. questa cartuccia è nota, molto più raramente, come .475 Magnum Revolver, 12x35mm Magnum oppure come 12x35R) è stata sviluppata durante gli anni '80 del XX secolo per opera di J. Linebaugh di Maryville (Stato del Missouri, USA), il quale voleva realizzare una NUOVA cartuccia per arma corta (N.B. e per la precisione, una cartuccia da revolver !!) destinata ESCLUSIVAMENTE all'impiego VENATORIO. Tecnicamente parlando si tratta di un derivato parziale del bossolo del .45 - 70 Government, che è stato tagliato a 35,56mm di lunghezza e modificato in maniera tale da accogliere palle da 12,07mm di diametro (.475"). La cartuccia è stata concepita per utilizzare palle di peso compreso tra 370 e 440grs., anche se le palle che vanno per la maggiore sono quelle di 400grs. di peso. A livello prototipale la cartuccia venne sviluppata in un telaio di un revolver Ruger modello "Bisley" unito ad un tamburo rinforzato a cinque camere, una canna da 140mm (5,5") con un passo di 1 giro in 457mm (cioè di 1 giro in 18"), il tutto con l'impugnatura di un revolver Ruger modello "Blackhawk". Con questa combinazione, le velocità andavano da 455 m/s (con le palle da 370grs.) a 415 m/s (con le palle da 440grs.). La sua prima commercializzazione avvenne nel 1988, anche se agli inizi si trattava più che altro di un prodotto di nicchia, e per tanto era estremamente difficile da trovare. Attualmente la cartuccia è camerata SOLO in appositi revolver che vengono prodotti o dalla Linebaugh Custom Revolver oppure dalla Freedom Arms (la stessa azienda che ha contribuito alla commercializzazione del calibro .454 Casull ). Stante l'enorme livello di energia cinetica sviluppato da questa cartuccia, si consiglia di non usare mai armi con canna inferiore ai 200mm di lunghezza. 

(https://www.grurifrasca.net/oldsite/Sito/Ricarica/pistole/475Linebaugh.html)
</IT>
<EN>
The .475 Linebaugh is an extremely potent rimmed revolver cartridge developed by John Linebaugh in the late 1980s. The cartridge is based on the .45-70 Government case cut down to 1.4 inches and loaded with .475-inch-diameter (12.1 mm) bullets weighing from 320 grains (21 g) to 440 grains (29 g). Although the .45 Silhouette cartridge is also derived from a .45-70 trimmed down to 1.5 inches, the .475 Linebaugh saw the same case modified to accept .475 caliber bullets, resulting in significantly different ballistic performance.
The then-new .475 Linebaugh was first announced in the May 1988 issue of Guns &amp; Ammo in an article written by Ross Seyfried. 

The .475 Linebaugh is primarily intended for hunting big game or as a backup when confronting dangerous animals. A 370-grain (24 g) bullet starting out at 1,495 feet per second (456 m/s) develops 1,840 foot-pounds force (2,490 J) of energy, and a 440-grain (29 g) bullet at 1,360 feet per second (410 m/s) develops 1,800 foot-pounds force (2,400 J). In comparison to another popular magnum revolver cartridge, the .454 Casull, the Casull's 300-grain (19 g) .454 caliber bullet at 1,650 feet per second (500 m/s) and 1,800 foot-pounds force (2,400 J) of energy is surpassed with the Linebaugh's loading of a 370-grain (24 g) .475 caliber bullet at 1,495 feet per second (456 m/s) and 1,840 foot-pounds force (2,490 J) of energy. The .475 Linebaugh and the .454 Casull are ballistically similar and both can also be loaded to higher pressures, but the .475 Linebaugh still has an edge on the latter.
As with most large magnum revolver cartridges, the .475 Linebaugh produces a significant amount of muzzle blast and felt recoil. In 2003, Ruger introduced a new cartridge called the .480 Ruger, which is essentially a shortened .475 Linebaugh that operates at 4% lower pressure, 48,000 vs. 50,000 for the Linebaugh. This results in a more comfortable shooting experience with only a minor loss in performance. Just as the .38 special cartridge will chamber and fire in revolvers chambered for the more powerful .357 magnum, the .480 Ruger will chamber and fire in revolvers chambered for the .475 Linebaugh. However, as the pressures show, the two are much closer in power than are the actual "Special" cartridges compared with their "magnum" counterparts.
The .475 Linebaugh remains a relatively obscure cartridge, no doubt owing in part to the introduction of Smith &amp; Wesson's more powerful .460 S&amp;W Magnum and .500 S&amp;W Magnum cartridges, .500 S&amp;W being the most powerful handgun cartridge in the world to date. 

(https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/.475_Linebaugh)
</EN>
<DE>N/A</DE>
<ES>N/A</ES>
<FR>N/A</FR>
</loc>