<loc>
<IT>N/A</IT>
<EN>
The .17 Hornady Mach 2, or .17 HM2, is a rimfire cartridge introduced in 2004 by the ammunition manufacturer Hornady, 
following the successful launch in 2002 of the .17 HMR. The .17 HM2 is based on the .22 Long Rifle "Stinger" case, 
necked down to .17 caliber (4.5 mm) and using a bullet weighing less than half the weight of a typical .22 Long Rifle bullet. 
The weight of the bullet is a key part of achieving the very high velocity for a rimfire round. 
It weighs only 17 grains (1.10 g) vs 30-40 grains (1.94-2.59 g) of a typical .22 LR bullet. The .17 HM2 may or may not live up to its "Mach 2" name,
depending on geographic location and conditions, with velocities out of a rifle of 2,100 ft/s (640 m/s). 
The velocity is nearly double that of a standard .22 LR, which results in a much flatter trajectory out to its 175-yard (160 m) effective range.

https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/.17_HM2
</EN>
<DE>N/A</DE>
<ES>
El .17 Hornady Mach 2 o .17 HM2 es un cartucho de percusión anular introducido en 2004 por la fábrica de municiones Hornady, 
tras el exitoso lanzamiento del .17 HMR. El cartucho está basado en la vaina del .22 Long Rifle Stringer, 
agolletado en el cuello hasta calibre .17 (4.5 mm), las balas usadas en este cartucho pesan menos de la mitad de las balas comunes usadas en .22 Long Rifle. 
La bala ultraligera de 17 granos es fundamental para lograr su velocidad de 640 m/s (cercano a match 2), 
que es casi el doble de velocidad de un .22 Long Rifle estándar con bala de 40 granos, lo que le hace tener una trayectoria 18 cm más plana a 
140 metros que un .22 Long Rifle estándar.​
La bala de 17 granos tiene un coeficiente balístico de 0.125 y una densidad seccional de 0.155, mientras que la bala de 15.5 granos 
tiene un coeficiente balístico de 0.115 y una densidad seccional de 0.075.

https://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/.17_Mach_2
</ES>
<FR>
La .17 Mach 2 ou or .17 HM2 est une munition avec un diamètre de 4,4 mm ; 
la cartouche de .17 Mach 2 contient une balle de 1,1 gramme propulsée à 530 mètres par seconde et délivrant 155 joules (15,8 kgm). 
Elle est à percussion annulaire. 
Le .17 Hornady Mach 2, ou .17 HM2, est une cartouche introduite en 2004 par le fabricant de munitions Hornady, 
à la suite du lancement réussi en 2002 du HMR .17. Le .17 HM2 est basé sur le boîtier "Stinger" de la munition en .22, 
ajusté au calibre .17 (4,5 mm) et utilisant une balle pesant moins de la moitié du poids d'une balle typique .22lr. 

https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/.17_Mach_2
</FR>
</loc>