<loc>
<IT>N/A</IT>
<EN>
The .204 Ruger is a centerfire rifle cartridge developed by Hornady and Ruger. At the time of its introduction in 2004, 
the .204 Ruger was the second highest velocity commercially produced ammunition and the only centerfire cartridge produced commercially for bullets of 
.204 inch/5 mm caliber. Ruger's claim to being the velocity king with the .204 was based on two points.
First, no other high performance 20 caliber cartridge was commercially produced. Second, the ammunition used to achieve the 4225 ft/s was available only 
from Hornady using a special powder not available to the general public. Note that handloaders typically achieve velocities more in the area 
of 4,100 ft/s (1,200 m/s) using a 32-grain (2.1 g) bullet. Handloads using a 40-grain (2.6 g) bullet in other commercial cartridges 
such as the .22-250 Remington also achieve velocities similar to those of the .204 Ruger. The advantage of the .204 Ruger is that it achieves 
these velocities with less powder, less recoil, and less heat than the larger cartridges. The 204 Ruger has a maximum range of 
approximately 500 yards (460 m). Hornady now offers a 24-grain lead free cartridge that claims 4400 fps from a 26" barrel. However, 
Hornady's 35 gr NTX .22-250 claims 4450 fps from a 24" barrel. 

https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/.204_Ruger
</EN>
<DE>
Die Patrone .204 Ruger ist eine sehr schnelle und präzise Büchsenpatrone. Die .204 Ruger stammt von der .222 Remington Magnum ab, 
welche eine Hülsenlänge von 47 mm aufweist. Die .204 Ruger hat natürlich die gleiche Hülsenlänge und nicht, wie bisher angegeben 49,99 mm. 
Die Angabe in der englischen Wikipedia-Version war diesbezüglich richtig! 

https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/.204_Ruger
</DE>
<ES>N/A</ES>
<FR>
La munition .204 Ruger a été créée par Hornady (États-Unis) en 2003 depuis la .222 magnum Laiton 47 mm bouteillé à gorge.
Balle 2,1 g - 1 288 m/s - 1,719 J. 

https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/.204_Ruger
</FR>
</loc>