<loc>
<IT>
La cartuccia calibro .22 - 250 Remington è un derivato parziale della cartuccia .250 - 3000 Savage, noto originariamente con il nome di ".22 Standard Varminter", realizzato da J. Gebby negli anni '60 del XX secolo. Più precisamente, Gebby realizzò tre cartucce, tutte molto simili tra di loro, denominate rispettivamente :
- .22 Standard Varminter (un derivato del .250 - 3000 Savage)
- .22 Senior Varminter (un derivato del .257 Roberts)
- .22 Junior Varminter (un derivato del .38 - 40 Ballard)

L'idea era quella di creare tre cartucce diverse per originare tre livelli di prestazioni diversi in modo da soddisfare il più elevato numero di cacciatori / tiratori. Il campo di applicazione elettivo di queste cartucce doveva essere il Bench - Rest, anche se erano possibili applicazioni nel settore venatorio. La Remington comprese l'importanza dell'invenzione di Gebby e, nel 1965, fece propria una delle sue creazioni, commercializzandola con la denominazione di .22 - 250 Remington.

(https://www.grurifrasca.net/oldsite/Sito/Ricarica/fucili/22-250R.html)
</IT>
<EN>
The .22-250 Remington is a very high-velocity (capable of reaching over 4000 feet per second), short action, .22 caliber rifle cartridge primarily used for varmint hunting and small game hunting, though it finds occasional use on deer.
This cartridge is also sometimes known as the .22 Varminter or the .22 Wotkyns Original Swift. Along with the .220 Swift, the .22-250 was one of the high-velocity .22 caliber cartridges that developed a reputation for remote wounding effects known as hydrostatic shock in the late 1930s and early 1940s.
The .22-250 started life as a wildcat cartridge developed from the .250-3000 Savage case necked down to take a .224 caliber bullet. In the early days of the cartridge there were several different versions that varied only slightly from one to the next, including one developed in 1937 by Grosvenor Wotkyns, J. E. Gebby and J. B. Smith who named their version the 22 Varminter.
The .22-250 is similar to, but was outperformed by the larger .220 Swift cartridge. However, it is in much wider use and has a larger variety of commercially available factory ammunition than the Swift. This makes it generally cheaper to shoot. The smaller powder load also contributes to more economical shooting for users who load their own ammunition. Despite common myths regarding longer barrel life on a 22-250 vs the Swift or other calibers, that is directly related to shooter habits, allowing the barrel to cool between volleys and the speed of the bullet, an important factor for high-volume shooters. 
Both the Swift and the 22-250 shoot at very similar velocities and bullet weights so barrel wear when used and cooled equally is identical between the two calibers. Due to its rimless case the 22-250 also feeds from a box magazine with ease.
In 1937 Phil Sharpe, one of the first gunsmiths to build a rifle for the .22-250 and long time .220 Swift rifle builder, stated, "The Swift performed best when it was loaded to approximately full velocity," whereas, "The Varminter case permits the most flexible loading ever recorded with a single cartridge. It will handle all velocities from 1,500 ft/s up to 4,500 ft/s."
Sharpe credited the steep 28-degree shoulder for this performance. He insisted that it kept the powder burning in the case rather than in the throat of the rifle, as well as prevented case stretching and neck thickening. "Shoulder angle ranks along with primer, powders, bullets, neck length, body taper, loading density and all those other features," he wrote. "The .22 Varminter seems to have a perfectly balanced combination of all desirable features and is not just an old cartridge pepped up with new powders."
Accuracy was consistently excellent, with little need for either case trimming or neck reaming, and Sharpe pronounced it "my choice for the outstanding cartridge development of the past decade." He finished by saying he looked forward to the day when it would become a commercial cartridge.

(https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/.22-250_Remington)
</EN>
<DE>N/A</DE>
<ES>N/A</ES>
<FR>N/A</FR>
</loc>