<loc>
<IT>N/A</IT>
<EN>
The .220 Swift (5.56×56mmSR) is a semi-rimmed rifle cartridge developed by Winchester and introduced in 1935 for small game and vermin hunting. 
It was the first factory loaded rifle cartridge with a muzzle velocity of over 4,000 ft/s (1,200 m/s).
The velocity that ranges from 2000 km/h (1200 mph or 550 m/s)up to about 4500 km/h (2800 mph or 1250 m/s. The Swift is a large cased .224 caliber cartridge
 and bullet that was created for small game such as prairie dogs, groundhogs and other vermin (or "varmints" in the US) such as marmots. When introduced 
 it was 1,400 ft/s (430 m/s) faster than its nearest varmint-hunting competitor, which was the .22 Hornet (also .224 caliber). 
It was found to be an extremely accurate cartridge as well. The .220 Swift remains the fastest commercial cartridge in the world, with a published 
velocity of 4,665 ft/s (1,422 m/s) using a 29 grain bullet and 42 grains of 3031 powder. The original factory load from Winchester provided a 
48-grain (3.1 g) bullet launched at 4,100 feet per second (1,250 m/s). Handloaders could marginally improve on this but only at maximum loads. 
The Swift can be loaded with light bullets to reach 4,400 ft/s (1,300 m/s). In recent times 75-grain (4.9 g) .224" bullets have been developed for use 
in high velocity .22 caliber rifles for taking larger game and long-distance shooting. Heavier bullets perform best in rifles that have an appropriate 
rifling twist rate taking into consideration the diameter, length, and other physical properties of the projectile. 

https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/.220_Swift
</EN>
<DE>N/A</DE>
<ES>N/A</ES>
<FR>
Le .220 Swift (nom de son inventeur) est une cartouche de chasse de petit calibre (5,6 mm / .22) possédant une grande vitesse à la bouche. 
Selon Le Chasseur français, il convient au petit gibier à grande distance et dans certains cas le chevreuil. 
Il est fabriqué industriellement en Suède et aux États-Unis. 

    Masse de la balle : 3,2 g
    Vitesse
        à la bouche : 1 152 m/s
        résiduelle à 100 m : 1 002 m/s
        résiduelle à 300 m : 749 m/s
    Énergie
        initiale : 2123 joules
        résiduelle à 100 m : 1 606 J
        résiduelle à 300 m : 898 J
		
https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/.220_Swift
</FR>
</loc>