<loc>
<IT>
Il .22 Hornet o 5,6 × 35mmR è una cartuccia da fucile introdotto in commercio nel 1930. È molto più potente del .22 WMR e del .17 HMR, 
ottenendo maggiore velocità quando viene sparata grazie a un proiettile con un peso due volte quello del HMR .17. 

https://it.wikipedia.org/wiki/.22_Hornet
</IT>
<EN>
The .22 Hornet or 5.6×35mmR is a varminting, small-game hunting, survival and competition centerfire rifle cartridge commercially introduced in 1930. 
It is considerably more powerful than the rimfire .22 WMR and the .17 HMR, achieving higher velocity with a bullet twice the weight of the .17 HMR bullet. 
The Hornet also differs very significantly from these in that being a centerfire cartridge makes it handloadable and reloadable, 
and thus much more versatile. It was the smallest commercially available .22 caliber centerfire cartridge until the introduction of the FN 5.7×28mm. 

Factory ammunition is widely available from all major manufacturers, generally with bullets weighing 34, 35, 45, or 46 grains (2.2, 2.3, 2.9, or 3.0 g), 
with bullets invariably either hollow point or soft point. Muzzle velocity typically is in the 2,500 to 3,100 ft/s (760 to 940 m/s) range, 
and muzzle energy is just over 700 ft·lbf (950 J) for factory ammo fired from a rifle. 
(Velocities and energies are less when Hornet ammunition is fired from short-barreled firearms.) Published handload data from major handloading-product 
companies shows how versatile the .22 Hornet can be. According to the Hodgdon Powder Company reloading data, the heavier bullets show a serious affinity 
for Lil'Gun smokeless powder to produce much higher velocities than other powder with heavy bullets in this small case.

https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/.22_Hornet
</EN>
<DE>
Die Patrone .22 Hornet ist eine Zentralfeuerpatrone, die für die Jagd und das Sportschießen verwendet wird. Das Geschosskaliber beträgt 5,7 mm, 
die Geschossmasse liegt zwischen 2,5 und 3,5 g. Es sind die unterschiedlichsten Geschosskonstruktionen erhältlich.
Auf der Abbildung rechts ist eine Patrone mit Hohlspitzgeschoss (mit ballistischer Haube) und mit einem Teilmantelgeschoss (Deformationsgeschoss) 
dargestellt. Die linke Patrone wurde von Hand geladen und ist eine Spezialpatrone für die Kleinwildjagd. 

Besondere Eigenschaften
    sehr geringer Rückstoß
    geringe Geräuschentwicklung
    sehr gute Präzision
    verwendbar bis ca. 150 m
    gute Leistung durch hohe Geschwindigkeit (700–800 m/s)
	
Die vergleichsweise geringe Geräuschentwicklung machen die .22 Hornet zu einer idealen Patrone, die vorzugsweise genutzt wird, 
wenn der Schussknall störend ist (z. B. Jagd in und nahe bei bewohnten Bereichen) und auf Kleinwild gejagt wird. Dabei ist von großem Vorteil, 
dass die Patrone bis 100 m Kleinwild sicher und waidgerecht tötet. Dies trifft auf die sonst gerne verwendete Patrone .22 lfB nicht zu 
(jagdlich vertretbare Schussentfernung bis ~ 50 m). Die Patrone .22 WMR ist mit ihren Eigenschaften zwischen den beiden vorgenannten Patronen einzuordnen. 

https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/.22_Hornet
</DE>
<ES>N/A</ES>
<FR>
Créée en 1930 par Winchester, la .22 Hornet est une munition pour la chasse des petits nuisibles et le tir de précision jusqu'à 200 m. 
Les ogives utilisées sont de même diamètre que celles de la 22LR. 

Cotes CIP

    Longueur de la douille : 35,64 mm
    Diamètre du projectile : 5,70 mm
    Diamètre du collet : 6,16 mm
    Longueur de la cartouche : 43,76 mm

https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/.22_Hornet
</FR>
</loc>