<loc>
<IT>
La .22 WMR (Winchester Magnum Rimfire) è una cartuccia a percussione anulare da carabina e revolver. 
Utilizza generalmente proiettili incamiciati che possono raggiungere velocità sull'ordine dei 500 m/s in carabina.
Molti revolver camerati in questo calibro sono dotati di un tamburo supplementare per l'utilizzo del più economico .22 Long Rifle. 

https://it.wikipedia.org/wiki/.22_WMR
</IT>
<EN>
The .22 Winchester Magnum Rimfire, also called .22 WMR, .22 Magnum, .22 WMRF, .22 MRF,[2] or .22 Mag, is a rimfire cartridge. 
Originally loaded with a bullet weight of 40 grains (2.6 g) delivering velocities in the 2,000 feet per second (610 m/s) range from a rifle barrel, 
.22 WMR is now loaded with bullet weights ranging from 50 grains (3.2 g) at 1,530 feet per second (470 m/s) to 30 grains (1.9 g) 
at 2,200 feet per second (670 m/s). The .22 WMR uses a larger case than the more popular .22 Long Rifle, both in diameter and length. 
The .22 WMR case is a lengthened version of the older .22 WRF. In the most common modern loadings, the combination of more powder and higher 
sustained pressures gives velocities of 1,875 feet per second (572 m/s) from a rifle using a 40-grain (2.6 g) bullet, and 1,500 feet per second (460 m/s) 
from a handgun. Because of its larger size, a .22 WMR round will not fit into the chamber of a .22 LR firearm. It is dangerous to chamber .22 LR rounds 
in a .22 WMR firearm. Doing so can result in injury from high pressure hot gas leaking around the LR case, which is too small for a .22 WMR chamber. 

https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/.22_Winchester_Magnum_Rimfire
</EN>
<DE>
Die .22 Winchester Magnum Rimfire (WMR), auch .22 WMR, .22 Magnum, .22 Mag., Hunter's Pet, ist eine Patrone für Kleinkaliber-Handfeuerwaffen sowohl 
für Büchsen als auch als Faustfeuerwaffen. Die Patrone ist eine 1959 auf dem Jahrestreffen der NRA in Washington von dem Unternehmen Winchester 
entstandene Randfeuerpatrone, welche mit drei Geschossgewichten zu 30 grain, 40 grain und 50 grain ausgeführt wurde. 
Die Munition war Nachfolger der .22 WRF. Die Unternehmen Ruger und Smith &amp; Wesson brachten unmittelbar nach ihrer Einführung passende Revolver 
hierfür heraus. Erst 1960 folgte Winchester mit einem passenden Gewehr, der Winchester Model 61. Die .22 WMR wird auch heute noch als Schonzeitkaliber 
für die Jagd auf Klein- und Raubwild benutzt. Die Patrone ist leistungsstärker als die .22 lfB. Die .22 WMR unterscheidet sich von der .22-lfB-Patrone 
in Hülsendurchmesser und Hülsenlänge. Weitere verwandte Patronen finden sich in der Liste von Winchester-Magnum-Patronen. 

https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/.22_Winchester_Magnum
</DE>
<ES>
El .22 Winchester Magnum Rimfire, comúnmente llamado .22 WMR, .22 Magnum o simplemente .22 Mag, es un cartucho de percusión anular para fusil. 
Originalmente montaba una bala de 2,6 g (40 granos) entregando velocidades de salida del proyectil de 610 m/s (2000 fps), 
también se le montan balas de 3,2 g (50 granos) a 470 m/s (1530 fps) y 1,9 g a 670 m/s (2200 fps). 
Desarrollado como un cartucho para la caza menor y de alimañas hasta los 100 m, es lo bastante preciso como para ser adecuado para el tiro deportivo. 
Su pequeño tamaño y mayor potencia respecto a otros cartuchos del mismo calibre, hizo que se fabriquen algunos modelos de pistola muy pequeños para defensa 
personal que lo disparan. Según fuentes de fuerzas antiterroristas, es uno de las pocos cartuchos de pistola capaces de traspasar chalecos antibalas 
de nivel 3. Aunque es claramente más potente que otros cartuchos de pequeño calibre, no suele ser capaz de derribar de un solo disparo salvo impactos 
en zonas concretas. Dispara una bala de 5,7 mm de diámetro y 2,6 gramos de peso, a una velocidad inicial de 615 m/s, desarrollando 491 Julios. 

https://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/.22_Winchester_Magnum_Rimfire
</ES>
<FR>N/A</FR>
</loc>