<loc>
<IT>N/A</IT>
<EN>
The 243 Winchester Super Short Magnum or 243 WSSM is a rifle cartridge introduced in 2003. It uses a .300 WSM (Winchester Short Magnum) case shortened and 
necked down to accept a .243in/6mm diameter bullet, and is a high velocity round based on ballistics design philosophies that are intended 
to produce a high level of efficiency. The correct name for the cartridge, as listed by the Sporting Arms and Ammunition Manufacturers' Institute (SAAMI), 
is 243 WSSM, without a decimal point.[3] Winchester has discontinued the manufacture of 243 WSSM ammunition. 
As of the first half of 2016, Winchester/Olin did manufactured and release for sale some WSSM ammunition. The product is only manufactured periodically, 
often on inconsistent intervals. The 243 WSSM is an addition to the Winchester Super Short Magnum (WSSM) family of cartridges, 
which also include the .223 WSSM and the .25 WSSM, and the idea behind the 243 WSSM was to develop a compact, higher velocity version of the well-established 
and internationally popular .243 Winchester unveiled by Winchester in 1955. The 243 WSSM was first introduced in 2003. The 243 WSSM's case is unusually short 
and fat in profile, contrasting markedly with most other rifle cartridges, and is intended to take advantage of what ballisticians have shown 
is the more uniform and efficient burning of propellant powder when it is held in a short, fat stack by the cartridge case.
ompared to other factory 6mm sporting cartridges the 243 WSSM is capable of functioning in the AR-15. Other factory produced 6mm cartridges like the 243 Win.
and 6mm Rem. are both too long for the AR-15 and require the AR-10 platform. The 243 WSSM is 3/8 inch shorter than the 243 Win. giving the 243 WSSM 
the ability to fit in a super-short action rifle. Thus 243 WSSM rifles can be lighter, have stiffer actions and have faster actions to cycle.
The 243 WSSM gives generally a 10% increase in velocity over the 243 Win.

https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/.243_Winchester_Super_Short_Magnum
</EN>
<DE>N/A</DE>
<ES>N/A</ES>
<FR>N/A</FR>
</loc>