<loc>
<IT>N/A</IT>
<EN>
The .25-20 Winchester, or WCF (Winchester center fire), was developed around 1895 for the Winchester Model 1892 lever action rifle. It was based on necking down the .32-20 Winchester. In the early 20th century, it was a popular small game and varmint round, developing around 1,460 ft/s with 86-grain bullets. But two years earlier Marlin Firearms Co. had already necked down the .32-20 Winchester, 
and called it the .25-20 Marlin. It was first chambered in Model 1889 lever action Marlins long before Winchester did the same thing and put their name on the .25-20.
While the SAAMI pressure rating is a full 28,000 CUP, modern ammunition is often loaded lighter in deference to the weaker steels used on many of the original guns. The early black powder cartridges were loaded to about 20,000 psi, but the SAAMI rating is close to that of the high velocity smokeless rounds produced later. The high velocity loadings developed 1,732 ft/s.
It was easy and economical to reload and was once a favorite with farmers, ranchers, pot hunters, and trappers. Though the .25-20 has been used on deer and even claimed the James Jordan Buck, a whitetail deer of long standing record in 1914, it is now rarely used on large-bodied game due to its sedate ballistics and light bullet construction, which make humane one-shot kills unlikely.
The .25-20 Winchester is sometimes confused with the similarly named .25-20 Single Shot; the two cartridges are markedly different and do not interchange with one another. 

https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/.25-20_Winchester
</EN>
<DE>
Die ab 1895 produzierte .25-20 Winchester-Patrone wurde für den Winchester Model 1892 Unterhebelrepetierer anfangs als Schwarzpulverpatrone entwickelt. 
Für die .25-20 Winchester Zentralfeuerpatrone im Kaliber .258 (6,6 mm) wurde eine Hülse gleicher Länge wie die der .44-40 WCF und der .32-20 WCF-Patrone verwendet. Sie hatte den Durchmesser der .32-20 und war vorne verjüngt (Flaschenhalshülse). Das Geschoss von 86 Grains hatte mit einer Schwarzpulverladung von 20 Grains eine etwas höhere Mündungsgeschwindigkeit als die .32-20. Beim Verschießen der Patrone mit dem Gewehr war der Rückstoß kaum spürbar, was ein schnelleres Schießen erlaubte.
Die Patrone wurde nach der Jahrhundertwende auch mit rauchlosem Pulver geladen und jagdlich für Kleinwild verwendet. Außer dem von John Browning entwickelten „Model 1892“ brachten Winchester und andere Anbieter eine ganze Reihe von Jagdwaffen für diese Patrone heraus. 

https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/.25-20_Winchester
</DE>
<ES>N/A</ES>
<FR>N/A</FR>
</loc>