<loc>
<IT>N/A</IT>
<EN>
The .25-35 Winchester, or WCF (Winchester Center Fire) was introduced in 1895 by Winchester for the Winchester Model 1894 &amp; Savage Model 99 lever action rifles. The case was based on the .30-30 cartridge. 
Significantly more powerful than the .25-20 Winchester, the .25-35 WCF can be used to hunt small deer at 200 yards and medium-sized deer at 100 yards, however, some consider it better suited to small predators such as coyotes instead. It was a popular round in the Winchester Model 1885 High Wall single-shot rifle. No production rifles had been made in .25-35 WCF since 1964 until 2005 when Winchester resumed chambering their Model 94 rifles in this cartridge.
Winchester ammunition has kept the cartridge in production in the U.S.A. 
The 6.5×52mmR is a European cartridge that is a close variant of the .25-35 Winchester. It should not be considered identical to the .25-35 Winchester and is not treated as such by the Commission Internationale Permanente pour l'Epreuve des Armes à Feu Portatives (CIP), 
which has released separate specifications for each cartridge. The 6.5×52mmR has its origins in Germany and was introduced by RWS and is chambered in many drilling and single-shot rifles. Any interchangeability between the two cartridges is solely dependent on individual chamber tolerances and should not be assumed. 

https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/.25-35_Winchester
</EN>
<DE>
.25-35 Winchester oder WCF (Winchester Center Fire) ist eine Gewehrpatrone, die erstmals 1895 von Winchester für das Unterhebelgewehr Winchester Model 1894 vorgestellt wurde. Die Hülse der Patrone basiert auf der Patrone .30-30. In Europa ist sie auch als 6,5×52R bekannt.
Die .25-35 Winchester war als Patrone zur Jagd auf Rehwild sehr beliebt. 
Winchester baute das Gewehr 1894 in diesem Kaliber von 1895 bis in die 1940er-Jahre. Ab 2005 wurde von Winchester das Modell 1894 wieder in diesem Kaliber angeboten. Winchester und RWS waren lange Jahre die einzigen Hersteller der Munition.
Auch wenn .25-35 Winchester und 6,5 × 52 mm R von den Abmessungen fast gleich sind, so ist beim Einsatz der .25-35 Win in einer 6,5 × 52 mm R große Vorsicht geboten. Der höchstzulässige Gebrauchsgasdruck der .25-35 Winchester liegt mit 3400 bar weit über dem für die 6,5 × 52 mm R zulässigen Gasdruck von 2450 bar.

https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/.25-35_Winchester
</DE>
<ES>N/A</ES>
<FR>N/A</FR>
</loc>