<loc>
<IT>N/A</IT>
<EN>
The .257 Weatherby Magnum is a .257 Caliber (6.35 mm) belted bottlenecked cartridge. It is one of the original standard length magnums developed 
by shortening the .375 H&amp;H Magnum case to approx. 2.5 in (64 mm). Of the cartridges developed by Roy Weatherby, the .257 Weatherby Magnum was known 
to have been his favorite, and the cartridge currently ranks third in Weatherby cartridge sales, 
after the .30-378 Weatherby Magnum and the .300 Weatherby Magnum. The .257 Weatherby Magnum is among one of the flattest shooting commercial cartridges. 
It is capable of firing a 115 gr (7.5 g) Nosler Ballistic Tip bullet at 3,400 ft/s (1,036 m/s) generating 2,952 ft⋅lbf (4,002 J) of energy which is comparable 
to factory loadings of the .30-06 Springfield and the .35 Whelen in terms of energy.
Discrepancies between the metric and U.S. diameters of the bullet may cause some confusion. A .257 bullet has a metric bullet diameter of 6.53 mm. However, 
in Europe cartridge designation nomenclature for a large part relies on the bore diameter. As the bore diameter of the rifle is .250 inches 
this would make the .257 Weatherby Magnum a 6.35 mm caliber cartridge rather than a 6.5mm caliber cartridge. 

The .257 Weatherby is known for its long range performance and is considered an accurate flat shooting cartridge. Initially due to the cartridge's high velocity
the cartridge exhibits less bullet drop than most other cartridges. However, due to lower ballistic coefficients of these bullets, 
velocity (and therefore energy) is shed more quickly. Weatherby's B25780TTSX, B257100TSX and the N257115BST ammunition have point blank ranges 
of 369 yd (337 m), 350 yd (320 m) and 323 yd (295 m) respectively. Thus no hold over is necessary when shooting at game at these ranges given that the rifles is 
zeroed correctly to accomplish this task.
The .257 Weatherby offers a 300–400 ft/s (91–122 m/s) over the 25-06 Remington cartridge which translates to around 600 ft x lbf (810 J) greater energy than 
the latter cartridge. Comparing the Remington's Premium PRC2506RA ammunition for the 25-06 Remington Weatherby's N257115BST .257 Weatherby bullet when zeroed 
for 200 yd (180 m) drops less than 30 in (76 cm) while the 25-06 Remington drop slightly over 44 in (110 cm) at 500 yd (460 m). 
When sighted in for 300 yd (270 m) the bullet of Weatherby's N257115BST ammunition has only dropped 21.9 in (56 cm) at 500 yd (460 m) 
and retains 1,347 ft x lbf (1,826 J) energy. Compared to the Winchester's .270 WSM SXP270S ammunition show a bullet drop of 24.5 in (62 cm) 
but retains 1,552 ft x lbf (2,104 J). The N257115BST bullet retains enough energy to be effective on deer out to 550 yd (500 m) while the SXP270S's 
bullet extends this range out by a further 100 yd (91 m) although both the Weatherby's and Winchester's ammunition start with roughly the same muzzle energy.
Weatherby guarantees a 1.5 MOA accuracy with their ammunition in a Weatherby rifle, .99 MOA or better with their Sub-MOA Vanguard rifles, and .99 MOA or better 
with the new Vanguard Series 2 Rifles.

https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/.257_Weatherby_Magnum
</EN>
<DE>N/A</DE>
<ES>N/A</ES>
<FR>N/A</FR>
</loc>
