<loc>
<IT>N/A</IT>
<EN>
The .264 Winchester Magnum is a belted, bottlenecked rifle cartridge. Except for the .244 H&amp;H Magnum and .257 Weatherby Magnum, 
it is the smallest caliber factory cartridge derived from the 2.85 in (72 mm) Holland &amp; Holland belted magnum case. It was introduced in the late 1950s 
and early 1960s with the .338 Winchester Magnum and the .458 Winchester Magnum as one of a family of short-cased 2.5 in (64 mm) belted magnum cartridges 
developed by Winchester based on the .375 Holland &amp; Holland parent case. It was officially introduced to the public by Winchester in 1959. 
After many years of dwindling use it began enjoying a mild resurgence in popularity in the mid-2000s among long range rifle enthusiasts and reloaders due 
to the high ballistic coefficient of the heavier 6.5mm bullets and increasing popularity of cartridges such as 6.5mm Creedmoor, .260 Remington, 6.5 Grendel, 
benchrest and wildcat cartridges in 6.5mm. 

The .264 Winchester Magnum gained a reputation as a very flat shooting cartridge. 
When introduced, it was first chambered in the Winchester Model 70 Westerner rifle, which was intended for longer range shooting more common 
in the Western United States. At present Remington, Winchester, HSM, and DoubleTap Ammunition produce ammunition for this cartridge. 
Manufacturers offer a 140 gr (9.1 g) bullet at 3,030 ft/s (920 m/s). This ammunition has a maximum point blank range of 300 yd (270 m) 
when sighted in at 250 yd (230 m). Some ammunition offers premium 140 gr (9.1 g) Nosler Partition and 125 gr (8.1 g) Accubond bullets driven 
at 3,100 ft/s (940 m/s) and 3,250 ft/s (990 m/s) through a 24-inch (610 mm) barrel.
While readily available factory ammunition for the cartridge is for the most part fairly basic, handloaders can gain a step up in performance with bullets 
with better ballistic coefficients and weights to extend the performance of the cartridge. For this reason, this cartridge is better suited for shooters
who are willing to make their own ammunition rather than those who purchase over the counter ammunition. 

https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/.264_Winchester_Magnum
</EN>
<DE>
Die .264 Winchester Magnum gehört zu einer von Winchester im Jahre 1956 begonnenen Familie von leistungsstarken Winchester-Magnum-Patronen, die alle auf einer 
ähnlichen Gürtelhülse basieren. Die Hülse ist im Wesentlichen die der Patrone .375 Holland &amp; Holland Magnum, die auf 64 mm verkürzt wurde.
Sie wurde 1958 zusammen mit der Patrone .338 Winchester Magnum vorgestellt.[2] Weitere verwandte Patronen finden sich in der Liste 
von Winchester-Magnum-Patronen. 

https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/.264_Winchester_Magnum
</DE>
<ES>
El .264 Winchester Magnum es un cartucho con cinturón, fabricado por Estados Unidos. Aparte del .257 Weatherby Magnum, es el cartucho de calibre más pequeño de 
fábrica que utiliza una longitud estándar (2,5 in (64 mm)). Se introdujo, junto con el .338 Winchester Magnum y el .458 Winchester Magnum, 
como uno de una serie de cartuchos cortos (2,5 in (64 mm)) desarrollados por Winchester. Se presentó oficialmente al público por Winchester en 1958.
El .264 Winchester Magnum es un cartucho que se ha normalizado por SAAMI, que publicó las especificaciones recomendadas para el cartucho. 
SAAMI recomienda un barril de ranura con una velocidad de giro de 230 mm, un diámetro interior de 0,256 en (6,5 mm) y un diámetro de la ranura 
de .264 en (6,7 mm) con cada ranura que tiene una anchura de 0,090 en (2,3 mm). La presión máxima recomendada para el cartucho es 64.000 psi (4.400 bar). 

https://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/.264_Winchester_Magnum
</ES>
<FR>N/A</FR>
</loc>
