<loc>
<IT>N/A</IT>
<EN>
The .276 Enfield (7×60mm) was an experimental rebated rim bottlenecked centerfire military rifle cartridge developed in conjunction 
with the Pattern 1913 Enfield (P'13) rifle. Development was discontinued by the onset of World War I. (Not to be confused with .276 Pedersen.)
The .276 Enfield was designed with the intent of being more powerful than the .303 British cartridge used in the Lee–Enfield rifles and to be at least similar 
in size and performance to other large, powerful early 20th century military rifle cartridges, like the .280 Ross, 7.92×57mm Mauser, .30-06 Springfield and 
7.5×55mm Swiss GP11. Before arriving on the RL18000C 1913 trials round, dozens of .256 and .276 cartridge case and projectile iterations were developed 
and tested over several years. The longest .276 cartridge iterations featured an overall length of 3.587 in (91.11 mm) and a case length of 2.76 in (70.10 mm).
Cartridge case design RL18000 emerged as the likely final choice with various .276 spitzer bullets of 165 gr (10.69 g), 175 gr (11.34 g) and 188 gr (12.18 g). 
The Small Arms Committee decided all were generally acceptable, but preferred the 165 gr (10.69 g) projectile design as the trajectory was flatter 
to 800 yd (732 m) than the 175 gr (11.34 g) projectile. They recommended that one thousand rifles should be made up for troop trials. To allow for the larger 
dimensions and higher muzzle energy .276 cartridge a new experimental rifle was developed. The experimental Pattern 1913 Enfield rifle featured a modified 
Mauser-type action that was very substantial and designed to be stronger than the Lee–Enfield action. While the .303 British round has a larger-diameter 
projectile than the .276 Enfield, the .276 Enfield cartridge case is larger and contains more propellant developing higher chamber pressures and higher muzzle 
velocities; as such, it is more powerful than the .303 British. The .303 Mk VII round introduced in 1910, for instance, has a projectile weight 
of 174 gr (11.28 g) and a muzzle velocity of 2,441 ft/s (744 m/s), while the .276 has a projectile weight of 165 gr (10.69 g) and a muzzle velocity 
of 2,785 ft/s (849 m/s) and a trajectory vertex at 800 yd (732 m) of 5.23 ft (1.59 m). The combination of a slimmer more aerodynamic projectile - 
reverse engineering the trajectory from the previous paragraph indicates a ballistic coefficient (G1 BC) of approximately 0.55 - with a higher sectional 
density propelled at a higher muzzle velocity and designed to travel at faster velocities gave the .276 Enfield better ballistics than the .303 British. 
The .276 Enfield was also rimless to ensure greater reliability in magazine-fed weapons, a problem with the older .303 British round. However, due to the 
approach of World War I, the .276 Enfield was not implemented for military service. 

https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/.276_Enfield
</EN>
<DE>N/A</DE>
<ES>N/A</ES>
<FR>N/A</FR>
</loc>