<loc>
<IT>N/A</IT>
<EN>
The .277 FURY, also known as the .277 SIG FURY, is a centerfire rifle cartridge announced by SIG Sauer in late 2019. It utilizes a hybrid case of brass and steel to support a chamber pressure of 80,000 pounds per square inch (550,000 kPa). The high chamber pressure enables a projectile speed of 3,000 feet per second (910 m/s) from a 16-inch (410 mm) barrel.
The cartridge uses a case that is the same length and diameter as the .308 Winchester. Each cartridge consists of a steel base coupled to a brass body via a locking washer. Bullets are either 135 grains (8.7 g) "match grade" or 140 grains (9.1 g) "hunter tipped".
SIG Sauer claims that the cartridge has performance superior to the 6.5mm Creedmoor, exhibiting 6 to 9 feet (1.8 to 2.7 m) less bullet drop at 1,000 yards (910 m), while delivering 20–25% greater energy.

https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/.277_FURY

In early October 2018 the Army issued a DRAFT Prototype Opportunity Notice (PON) for Next Generation Squad Weapons (NGSW). The draft NGSW PON detailed “how the Government intends to award up to three prototype Other Transaction Agreements (OTAs), with each Offeror developing two weapon variants and a common cartridge for both weapons, utilizing Government provided 6.8 millimeter projectiles. 
The weapons include the Next Generation Squad Weapon-Rifle (NGSW-R) and the Next Generation Squad Weapon-Automatic Rifle (NGSW-AR),” according to fbo.gov. “The NGSW-R is the planned replacement for the M4/M4A1 Carbine and the NGSW-AR is the planned replacement for the M249 Squad Automatic Weapon (SAW) in the Automatic Rifleman Role in Brigade Combat Teams (BCT).”
Initially, five companies were selected by the NGSAR program to produce six prototypes: AAI Corporation Textron Systems; FN America LLC; General Dynamics-OTS Inc.; PCP Tactical, LLC; and SIG Sauer, Inc. FN America was allowed to produce two prototypes.
Currently, SIG is moving forward with civilian versions of its 6.8mm cartridge developed for the competition, the 277 SIG Fury. This cartridge utilizes a hybrid case technology made from brass and other materials. The combination is rated to handle 80,000 psi of chamber pressure. By comparison, “magnum” cartridges typically produce a maximum of 62,000 psi.

https://www.tactical-life.com/gear/ammo/277-sig-fury-hybrid-case-design/
</EN>
<DE>N/A</DE>
<ES>N/A</ES>
<FR>N/A</FR>
</loc>