<loc>
<IT>N/A</IT>
<EN>
The .280 British was an experimental rimless bottlenecked intermediate rifle cartridge. It was later designated 7 mm MK1Z, and has also been known as 7 mm NATO, .280/30, .280 Enfield, .280 NATO, 7 mm FN Short, and 7×43mm.
Like most armed forces in the immediate post-World War II era, the British Army began experimenting with lighter rounds after meeting the German StG 44 in combat. The Army began development in the late 1940s, with subsequent help from Fabrique Nationale in Belgium and the Canadian Army. The .280 British was tested in a variety of rifles and machine guns including the EM-2, Lee–Enfield, FN FAL, Bren, M1 Garand and Taden gun.
Despite its success as an intermediate cartridge, the .280 British was not considered powerful enough by the U.S. Army and several variants of the .280 British were created in an attempt to appease the U.S. Army. However, the U.S. Army continued to reject these variants, ultimately adopting the cartridge that was then designated the 7.62×51mm NATO. 

https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/.280_British
</EN>
<DE>N/A</DE>
<ES>
El .280 British fue un cartucho para fusil fabricado en el Reino Unido. Fue designado más adelante 7 mm MK1Z, y también se ha conocido como 7 mm OTAN, .280/30, .280 Enfield, .280 OTAN, 7 mm corto FN, y 7 x 43. Fue diseñado por el ejército británico en la década de 1940, con la ayuda posterior de FN Herstal en Bélgica y en el ejército canadiense.1​ Los cartuchos .280 British fueron probados en una gran variedad de fusiles y ametralladoras, 
incluyendo el EM-2, el Lee-Enfield, el FN FAL, el Garand M1, la Bren y la Taden. A pesar de su éxito como un cartucho intermedio, el Ejército de los Estados Unidos no consideró al .280 British como un cartucho lo suficientemente potente y se crearon diversas variantes de este cartucho en un intento por convencer al Ejército de los Estados Unidos. Sin embargo, el ejército estadounidense continuó rechazando estas variantes y finalmente adoptó el 7,62 x 51 OTAN. 

https://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/.280_British
</ES>
<FR>N/A</FR>
</loc>