<loc>
<IT>
Nata nel 1963 possiede fondello ribassato (uguale a quello del .30-06), mentre il bossolo ha il classico diametro di una magnum. I dati balistici però sono sovrapponibili a quelli del .280 Rem. Il successo tutto Americano è dovuto alla possibilità di camerare questa cartuccia nelle armi a leva, sistema amato oltreoceano.

http://www.tiropratico.com/ammunition/pagine/284winchester.html
</IT>
<EN>
The .284 Winchester is a commercially unsuccessful cartridge that has enjoyed a resurgence due to interest from long-range competitive shooters. Introduced by Winchester in 1963, the .284 Winchester was designed to achieve .270 Winchester and .280 Remington performance from the new Winchester Model 100 autoloader and Winchester Model 88 lever-action rifles.
The end result was a 7 mm cartridge with about the same overall length as the .308 Winchester but with a wider body, that yields a powder capacity about the same as that of the .270 Winchester and .280 Remington.
Americans would define the shoulder angle at alpha/2 = 35 degrees. The common rifling twist rate for this cartridge is 254 mm (1 in 10 in), 6 grooves, Ø lands = 7.00 mm, Ø grooves = 7.19 mm, land width = 2.79 mm and the primer type is large rifle.
According to the official C.I.P. guidelines the .284 Winchester case can handle up to 440 MPa (63,816 psi) piezo pressure. In C.I.P. regulated countries every rifle cartridge combo has to be proofed at 125% of this maximum C.I.P. pressure to certify for sale to consumers.
The SAAMI pressure limit for the .284 Winchester is set at 56,000 PSI, piezo pressure.
When the cartridge over all length is maintained, deeper-seating is necessary with long heavier bullets. This reduces usable powder capacity and hence performance compared to longer cartridges like the .280 Remington.
The American .280 Remington cartridge is probably the closest ballistic twin of the .284 Winchester. When compared to the .284 Winchester the .280 Remington has a slightly different maximum allowed chamber pressure and case capacity. 

https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/.284_Winchester
</EN>
<DE>N/A</DE>
<ES>
El .284 Winchester es cartucho para rifles fabricado por Estados Unidos. Introducido por Winchester en 1963, el .284 Winchester fue diseñado tomando como base los modelos .270 Winchester y .280 Remington. El resultado final fue un cartucho de 7 mm con aproximadamente la misma longitud total que la .308 Winchester pero con un cuerpo más ancho.
Suele ser utilizado para la caza de ciervos y cabras. El cartucho se utiliza a veces para el tiro largo y en cierto tipo de competiciones de largo alcance, donde los participantes suelen utilizar gran cantidad de municiones. Para esta aplicación, el .284 Winchester se carga con 175 y 180 gramos de bala de muy baja resistencia.​ El Winchester .284 Winchester no es popular en Europa, donde compite con el 7x64mm, en los que es casi idéntico balísticamente. 
En comparación con el .284 Winchester, el 7 × 64mm tiene un menor CIP máximo permitido en presión de la cámara. 

https://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/.284_Winchester
</ES>
<FR>N/A</FR>
</loc>