<loc>
<IT>N/A</IT>
<EN>
300 Whisper:
The '.300 Whisper', a CIP standard, is one of many cartridges designed to shoot heavier bullets (200–250 grains) at subsonic velocities.
.300 Whisper is also known as .300 Fireball or .300-221. The 300 AAC Blackout is the most successful 30 caliber cartridge with these design parameters 
and been widely accepted whereas the .300 Whisper has fallen into disuse.
The .300 Whisper was originally based on the .221 Fireball case necked up to .30 caliber. However, reloaders have found the .223 Remington or 5.56×45mm NATO 
works well when shortened and resized to .30 caliber. Firing in the .300 Whisper chamber results in a slightly sharper shoulder. Magnum pistol powders such as 
H110 work well for supersonic loads. Sierra 240 grain (16 g) jacketed bullets work well if the barrel has a 1:8 twist. Barrels with a 1:10 twist will stabilize 
220 grain (14 g) bullets at subsonic speeds. 125 grain (8 g) bullets will reach 2,400 ft/s (730 m/s). 

https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/.300_Whisper

300 AAC 'Blackout':
The .300 AAC Blackout (designated as the 300 BLK by the SAAMI and 300 AAC Blackout by the C.I.P.), also known as 7.62×35mm is an intermediate cartridge 
developed in the United States by Advanced Armament Corporation (AAC) for use in the M4 carbine. Its purpose is to achieve ballistics similar to the 7.62×39mm 
cartridge, or even more similarly, the 7.92×33mm Kurz cartridge in an AR-15 while using standard AR-15 magazines at their normal capacities. 300 BLK ammunition 
cannot be used in a rifle chambered for 7.62×40mm Wilson Tactical. It is mainly derived from the .300 Whisper concept, but differs in having been submitted 
to the SAAMI. 

The 300 AAC Blackout was designed to achieve energies similar to the 7.62×39mm Soviet in an AR-15 while using standard AR magazines at their full capacity. 
The 7.62 Soviet's cartridge taper prevented reliable feeding in AR magazines and created wear on the bolt. From the 14.5 in (370 mm) barrel of the M4 Carbine, 
the M855 5.56×45mm round has an effective point target range of 500 meters. The bullet has significant drop, drift, and energy loss at that distance. 
From a 16 in (410 mm) barrel, a 125 gr (8.1 g) 300 BLK round has a lower velocity and similar bullet drop and drift at shorter distances. 
However, it has the same amount of energy at 700 meters that the M855 has at 500 meters. In terms of hit probability, the Blackout has an effective range of 
460 meters. From a 9 in (230 mm) barrel, the 125 gr BLK round has the same muzzle energy as the M855 from the M4, and 5 percent more energy at 440 meters. 
In comparison with 7.62×39mm rounds, 300 BLK rounds with varying loads have a better ballistic coefficient and more energy out of similar length barrels. 
300 BLK rounds like the Barnes TAC 110 grain, have "barrier blind" performance, being capable of penetration through several inches of different hard targets. 
300 BLK allows a user to have one firearm with the capability of switching between subsonic, supersonic VMAX or barrier penetrating ammunition all with just 
the change of a magazine. It is able to replace the H&amp;K MP5 for close quarters, and with just a magazine change, bring the fight to longer distances, 
outperforming the M4 carbine. The .30 caliber cartridge has an 89.1 percent increase in frontal bullet area over the 5.56×45mm, and so leaves a larger wound 
cavity in soft targets. It also penetrates deeper and initially yaws faster. 300 BLK rounds are effective out of barrels as short as 4.5 in (110 mm). 
Weapons chambered for the round can be as light, compact, and quiet when suppressed as submachine guns like the 9×19mm MP5, 5.7x28mm FN P90, and 4.6×30mm MP7 
while having more energy and accuracy at longer range.

https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/300_AAC_Blackout
</EN>
<DE>N/A</DE>
<ES>N/A</ES>
<FR>N/A</FR>
</loc>