<loc>
<IT>
Il .300 Winchester Magnum (noto anche come .300 Win Mag, 300WM o 7,62 × 67mm) è una cartuccia da carabina, introdotta dalla Winchester Repeating Arms Company 
nel 1963. Il .300 Winchester Magnum è una cartuccia magnum progettata per adattarsi a un fucile standard. Si basa sul .375 H&amp;H Magnum, il quale è stato 
accorciato e abbassato per ridurre il proiettile alla grandezza del calibro 30 (7,62 mm).
Il .300 Winchester è estremamente versatile ed è stato adottato da una vasta gamma di utenti tra cui cacciatori, tiratori scelti, unità militari e dipartimenti 
di polizia. Il .300 Win Mag è il più popolare calibro .30 magnum per i cacciatori americani, nonostante sia superato dalle prestazioni dei più potenti .300 e 
.30-378 Weatherby Magnums e il più recente .300 Remington Ultra Magnum. È utilizzato per la caccia alle alci, in quanto possono offrire migliori prestazioni a 
lungo raggio con un peso della pallottola migliore rispetto alla maggior parte delle altre cartucce calibro .30. I reparti militari e delle forze dell'ordine 
hanno adottato la cartuccia per il tiro dalla distanza e nel tiro a segno. A dimostrazione della sua accuratezza, sin dalla sua introduzione ha vinto diverse 
competizioni nel tiro a segni da 1000 yard (910 m).

https://it.wikipedia.org/wiki/.300_Winchester_Magnum
</IT>
<EN>
The .300 Winchester Magnum (also known as .300 Win Mag or 300WM) (7.62×67mmB) is a belted, bottlenecked magnum rifle cartridge that was introduced by Winchester
Repeating Arms Company in 1963. The .300 Winchester Magnum is a magnum cartridge designed to fit in a standard rifle action. It is based on the .375 H&amp;H Magnum, 
which has been blown out, shortened, and necked down to accept a .30 caliber (7.62 mm) bullet.
The .300 Winchester is extremely versatile and has been adopted by a wide range of users including hunters, target shooters, military units, and law enforcement 
departments. Hunters found the cartridge to be an effective all-around choice with bullet options ranging from the flatter shooting 165 grain to the harder 
hitting 200+ grain selections available from the factory. The .300 Win Mag remains the most popular .30 caliber magnum with American hunters, despite being 
surpassed in performance by the more powerful .300 and .30-378 Weatherby Magnums and the newer .300 Remington Ultra Magnum. It is a popular selection 
for hunting moose, elk, and bighorn sheep as it can deliver better long range performance with better bullet weight than most other .30 caliber cartridges. 
Military and law enforcement departments adopted the cartridge for long range sniping and marksmanship. As a testament to its accuracy, since its introduction 
it has gone on to win several 1,000-yard (910 m) competitions.
The .300 Winchester uses the same case head design of the .375 H&amp;H Magnum, its parent cartridge. The taper of the cartridge was reduced to provide the cartridge 
with more volume so as to increase its potential powder capacity. The lengthening of the case and the move of the shoulder forward over the 
.338 Winchester Magnum allowed for the reaming of the .308 Norma Magnum or .30-338 Winchester chamber to dimensions of the .300 Winchester Magnum. 
The down side was a neck which was shorter than the caliber of the bullet it fired, which meant that the bullet had to be seated more deeply in the case. 

https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/.300_Winchester_Magnum
</EN>
<DE>
Die .300 Winchester Magnum, auch 7,62 × 67 mm, ist die letzte in einer Serie von Gewehr-Patronen mit Gürtelhülsen, 
die das Unternehmen Winchester Repeating Arms Company ab 1956 kurz nacheinander in seiner Magnum-Serie herausbrachte. Sie ist eine auf das Kaliber 
.300 (7,62 mm) eingezogene und auf die Länge 66,5 mm gekürzte Version der .375 H&amp;H. 
Die .300 Winchester Magnum ist für europäisches Hochwild einsetzbar und wird im deutschsprachigen Raum auch für starkes Niederwild eingesetzt. 
Der Einsatz auf Raubwild und Raubzeug ist jagdlich nicht geläufig. 
Im militärischen Bereich wird diese Patrone unter anderem im Scharfschützengewehr G22 der Bundeswehr, mit Vollmantel-Weichkern- oder Vollmantel-Hartkerngeschoss 
(AP, Armour Piercing) verwendet. Entwickelt und hergestellt werden diese von der MEN – Metallwerk Elisenhütte GmbH.

https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/.300_Winchester_Magnum
</DE>
<ES>
El .300 Winchester Magnum (conocido como .300 Win Mag), o 7,62 x 67 en el sistema métrico, es un popular cartucho Magnum para fusil, introducido por la 
Winchester Repeating Arms Company en 1963 como parte de la familia de cartuchos Winchester Magnum.Es un cartucho preciso, de largo alcance y con una trayectoria 
relativamente estable. Al igual que otros cartuchos de la familia Winchester Magnum, el .300 está basado en un casquillo Holland &amp; Holland acortado.
El .300 Winchester Magnum continúa siendo el más popular cartucho .30 Magnum entre los cazadores estadounidenses, a pesar de ser eclipsado en desempeño 
por el más potente .300 Weatherby Magnum y el más reciente .300 Remington Ultra Magnum.​ Es un cartucho de popular elección para cazar uapities y muflones, 
porque tiene un mejor desempeño a largas distancias que los cartuchos calibre 7,62 mm convencionales. 

https://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/.300_Winchester_Magnum
</ES>
<FR>
La cartouche .300 Winchester Magnum (aussi connu en tant que .300 Win Mag ou .300WM) est une cartouche créée par Winchester Repeating Arms Company en 1963 
en tant que cartouche Magnum. Elle est basée sur la cartouche .375 H&amp;H Magnum qui a été modifiée pour accepter une balle de calibre 30 (7,62×67 mm en 
dénomination métrique). C'est une cartouche populaire pour la chasse au grand gibier tels que cervidés en Europe ou en Amérique du Nord. Par ailleurs, 
dans les années 1980, les Marines ont testé et adopté cette cartouche pour un usage militaire. 

https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/.300_Winchester_Magnum
</FR>
</loc>