<loc>
<IT>N/A</IT>
<EN>
The .32-20 Winchester, also known as .32 WCF (Winchester center fire), was the first small-game lever-action cartridge that Winchester produced. It was initially introduced as a black-powder cartridge in 1882 for small-game, varmint hunting, and deer. Colt produced a single-action revolver chambered for this cartridge a few years later.
The name .32-20 refers to the 32 caliber bullet of .312-inch-diameter (7.9 mm) and standard black-powder charge of 20 grains (1.3 g). 
This cartridge was sometimes used for deer hunting in the past, and William Lyman, the designer of rifle sights, said of it: "For large game, of course, a .32-20 W.C.F. cartridge is rather small, but it comes nearer to being an all-around cartridge in my opinion than any other." Many now consider it too light and low-powered for deer and better suited to small game and metallic silhouette. It has a good reputation for accuracy in rifles as well as the few handguns that have been chambered for it. 
Because of its low power, it destroys very little meat, making it a good hunting round for appropriately sized game, up to about 100 yards (91 m). The cartridge is now approaching obsolescence, as shooters turn to other similar but more powerful and flexible loads. The power level of more modern .32s, such as the .32 H&amp;R Magnum and the .327 Federal Magnum, equal or surpass the .32-20 in modern firearms.
Although it is an inexpensive cartridge to reload, care must be taken by the reloader because of the extremely thin walls of the cartridge case. Energy and pressure levels for handloading are determined based on the strength and condition of the firearm action to be used. Because most firearms chambered for this cartridge are older (e.g. early model Winchester Model 73 and 92 rifles as well as older Colt and Smith &amp; Wesson revolvers) factory ammunition usually has reduced pressures from what can be achieved through handloading. 
Most factory ammunition exhibits ballistics of about 1,200 ft/s (370 m/s) and 325 ft x lbf (441 J) of energy at the muzzle with a 100-grain (6.5 g) bullet from an 18 to 20 inch rifle barrel. The performance characteristics of the cartridge listed in the sidebar should be considered maximum performance parameters obtainable, and even then only with a modern weapon designed for higher pressure loads. 
Factory-type loads - and reloads mimicking factory type loads - are the safe maximum loads for use in older weapons chambered for this cartridge, as most of the weapons the cartridge is chambered. Few if any companies still manufacture hunting weapons in this caliber. 

https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/.32-20_Winchester
</EN>
<DE>
Die ab 1882 produzierte .32-20 WCF-Patrone (.32-20 Winchester Center Fire) wurde wie die .44-40-WCF- und die .38-40-WCF-Patrone für das Winchester-Mod.-73-Gewehr entwickelt. Wie die Patronen im größeren Kaliber war sie eine für ihre Zeit leistungsfähige Zentralfeuerpatrone. 1895 brachte Winchester eine kleinere Verwandte der .32-20 auf den Markt, die .25-20 Winchester mit einer auf der .32-20 basierenden, dem kleineren Kaliber angepassten Patronenhülse.
Für die .32-20 WCF-Patrone im Kaliber .313 (7,95 mm) wurde eine Hülse gleicher Länge wie die .44er Hülse verwendet, sie hatte jedoch einen kleineren Durchmesser und war vorne verjüngt. Das Geschoss von 100 Grains hatte etwa die gleiche Mündungsgeschwindigkeit wie die größeren Patronen. Beim Verschießen der Patrone mit dem Gewehr war der Rückstoß kaum spürbar, beim Revolver war er wesentlich geringer, 
was ein schnelleres Schießen erlaubte. Wie ihre größeren Schwestern war sie ursprünglich für das Winchester-Mod.-73-Gewehr vorgesehen, später brachte Winchester auch andere Modelle auf den Markt für die .32-20. Ab 1887 stellte auch Colt den Single Action Army in diesem Kaliber her, und 1888 folgte der Colt Model 1878 Double Action. Sowohl Colt als auch Smith &amp; Wesson stellten bis in die neuere Zeit auch Revolver mit ausschwenkbarer Trommel für diese für das sportliche Schießen geeignete Patrone her.
Auch der Colt-Lightning-Vorderschaftsrepetierer war im Kaliber .32-20 erhältlich. Andere Hersteller waren Marlin mit Unterhebelrepetierern und Remington mit dem Rolling-Block-Einzellader. Die Patrone wurde nach der Jahrhundertwende auch mit rauchlosem Pulver geladen und jagdlich für Kleinwild verwendet. Mit dem von John Browning entwickelten „Model 1892“ brachte Winchester einen Unterhebelrepetierer auf den Markt, der auch für das Verschießen von rauchlosen Patronen geeignet war.
Bei den von Winchester laborierten .32-20-Patronen mit rauchlosem Pulver wurden anfangs die außenballistischen Daten der Schwarzpulverpatronen beibehalten, später wurde auf stärkere Ladungen übergegangen. Die Produktion wurde 1937 eingestellt, nach dem Krieg jedoch mit dem Aufkommen des Cowboy Action Shooting wieder aufgenommen. 

https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/.32-20_WCF
</DE>
<ES>N/A</ES>
<FR>
La cartouche de chasse .32-20 Winchester fut conçue en 1882 pour la Winchester 1873. Elle était initialement chargée de 20 grains de poudre noire. Elle fut adoptée par de nombreux revolvers (dont le Colt Single Action Army) et carabines de chasse de fabrication américaine et espagnole jusqu'à la fin des années 1930. Son étui de laiton a une forme de bouteille. 

https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/.32-20_Winchester
</FR>
</loc>