<loc>
<IT>N/A</IT>
<EN>
The .338 Winchester Magnum is a .338 in (8.6 mm) caliber, belted, rimless, bottlenecked cartridge introduced in 1958 by Winchester Repeating Arms. 
It is based on the blown-out, shortened .375 H&amp;H Magnum. The .338 in (8.6 mm) is the caliber at which medium-bore cartridges are considered to begin. 
The .338 Winchester Magnum is the first choice among professional brown bear (specifically grizzly bear) guides in Alaska to back up clients where a powerful 
stopping caliber is required on charging bears. It is also the most popular medium-bore cartridge in North America and has the most widely available choice in 
rifles among medium bore rifles. The action length is the same as a .30-06 and most major rifle manufacturers in the United States chamber rifles for the 
cartridge including the semi-automatic Browning BAR Mk II Safari, making it a very powerful combination against charging dangerous game. The cartridge was 
intended for larger North American big-game species and has found use as for the hunting of thin-skinned African plains-game species.
The .338 Winchester Magnum follows the modern cartridge designs in that the cartridge case features a case with minimal taper so as to maximize case capacity 
yet providing reliable feeding and extraction. The .338 Winchester Magnum is based on the .375 H&amp;H Magnum, which was shortened to 2.500 in (63.5 mm), 
blown out and necked down to hold a .338 in (8.6 mm) bullet. The case has a capacity of 86.0 grain of H2O (5.58 cm3). The cartridge follows the design of the 
standard length Weatherby Magnum cartridges such as the .257 Weatherby Magnum, .270 Weatherby Magnum and the 7 mm Weatherby Magnum for which Winchester had 
supplied basic brass until 1948. Both the Commission Internationale Permanente pour l'Epreuve des Armes à Feu Portatives(CIP) and the Sporting Arms and 
Ammunition Manufacturers' Institute (SAAMI) govern and regulate the specifications regarding the .338 Winchester Magnum. SAAMI and the CIP recommend a 6-groove 
barrel with a twist rate of one revolution, in a 10 in (250 mm) barrel with a bore Ø of .330 in (8.4 mm) and a groove diameter of Ø of .338 in (8.6 mm), 
with each groove having a width of .110 in (2.8 mm). The SAAMI-recommended average pressure for the cartridge is 64,000 psi (4,400 bar). 
The CIP enforces a 4,300-bar (62,000 psi) pressure limit for the cartridge. 

https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/.338_Winchester_Magnum
</EN>
<DE>
Die Patrone .338 Winchester Magnum ist eine leistungsstarke Gewehrpatrone. Die .338 Winchester Magnum gehört zu einer von Winchester im Jahre 1956 begonnenen 
Familie von leistungsstarken Winchester-Magnum-Patronen, die alle auf einer ähnlichen Gürtelhülse basieren. Die Hülse entspricht der  
Patrone .375 Holland &amp; Holland Magnum, die auf 8,6 mm verjüngt und auf 64 mm verkürzt wurde. Als Urvater der .338 Winchester Magnum kann die von Charlie O'Neil 
Elmer Keith und Don Hopkins entwickelte Wildcat .334 OKH angesehen werden. Diese basierte auf der Hülse der Patrone .300 H&amp;H Magnum, die wiederum auf der 
Hülse der .375 Holland &amp; Holland Magnum basierte. Die .338 Winchester Magnum ist eine für ein .338er-Geschoss aufgeweitete .334 OKH. Sie wurde 1958 zusammen 
mit der Patrone .264 Winchester Magnum vorgestellt. Sie sollte die Lücke zwischen den Patronen im Kaliber .30 und denen des Kalibers .375 Holland &amp; Holland 
schließen. Weitere verwandte Patronen finden sich in der Liste von Winchester-Magnum-Patronen. 

https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/.338_Winchester_Magnum
</DE>
<ES>N/A</ES>
<FR>
Le .338 Winchester Magnum est un modèle de cartouche destinée à la carabine de chasse modèle 70 Alaskan.
La cartouche .338 Winchester Magnum voit le jour en 1959. Elle est dérivée de la cartouche .458 Winchester Magnum, l'ouverture de l' étui ayant été rétrécie à 
8,585 mm et le culot de l'étui ayant été renforcé à la base. Cette cartouche, particulièrement recommandée pour la chasse, est très rarement utilisée 
pour le tir sportif. 
Les caractéristiques de la cartouche .338 winchester Magnum sont :

    poids de la balle 200 grains (13,0 g) ;
    VO m/s 900 ;
    EO 5,265 joules.

https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/.338_Winchester_Magnum
</FR>
</loc>