<loc>
<IT>
La cartuccia calibro .358 Norma Magnum rappresenta la risposta tecnologica della Norma  al successo commerciale di munizioni come il .300 od il .338 Winchester Magnum. L'idea dei tecnici della Norma era quella di creare una cartuccia di tipo magnum capace di lanciare palle da 250grs. di peso ( 16,2 GRAMMI) a circa 850 m/s entro canne da 610mm (24") di lunghezza. Il tutto doveva però avvenire in armi con azioni di tipo standard (standard type action), cioè capaci di impiegare cartucce di lunghezza NON superiori a quella del .30-06 Springfield e NON in azioni di tipo magnum (magnum-type action)!! 
Questa munizione esistette come cartuccia sperimentale (wildcat) per circa una paio d'anni, vale a dire dal 1958 al 1960. Poi, nei primi anni '60 del XX secolo la Norma commercializzò prima i bossoli vergini e poi, poco dopo, le munizioni vere e proprie. I ricaricatori più esperti noteranno sicuramente che il .358 Norma Magnum è MOLTO simile al 35-338 (nota anche come .35-.338 Winchester Magnum), una cartuccia sperimentale oggi scomparsa, che era basata sul bossolo del .338 Winchester Magnum modificato per accogliere proiettili da 9mm (.355") di diametro.

(https://www.grurifrasca.net/oldsite/Sito/Ricarica/fucili/358NM.html)
</IT>
<EN>
The .358 Norma Magnum is a rifle cartridge introduced in 1959 by Norma. The cartridge is closely related to the .308 Norma Magnum. Both calibers share the same dimensions of the case head as the .300 H&amp;H Magnum, but have far less body taper, resulting in the same internal capacity in a shorter case. The cartridge case is the longest that will comfortably fit in a standard Mauser action, or any rifle action designed to chamber the 30-06. The .358 NM was the first .35 caliber cartridge commercially developed and sold to the American market since the decline of the .35 Newton in the late 1920s. 

Though introduced by a Swedish company, the .358 Norma Magnum was designed for American hunters, due to Norma's chief designer Nils Kvale's close contacts with American colleagues. It is intended as a cartridge for the largest of North American game - elk, moose, brown bear, Bighorn Sheep, and bison, and shoots fast and flat enough to be useful to 400 to 500 yards on game the size of American elk (Wapiti). While it is needlessly powerful for deer-sized game, it can be used, at least with the heavier (and therefore slower) .358 bullets on such game without destroying too much meat. It would work well, with properly designed bullets, on most large African species. But laws prohibiting the use of bullets smaller than 0.375-inch (0.95 cm) on dangerous game, in most African countries, limit its use to "plains game," including the largest antelope, the one-ton eland.
The .358 Norma is what is known as a "short magnum," designed to work in long rifle actions; many 30-06 rifles such as the 1903 Springfield rifle have been rebarreled to the much-more powerful .358 Norma. Norma's factory ammunition for the .358 Norma drives a 250-grain bullet at 2880 fps and produces more than 4,600 ft-lbs (foot-pounds) of kinetic energy at the muzzle, while delivering a foot-ton of energy 500 yards downrange.
</EN>
<DE>N/A</DE>
<ES>N/A</ES>
<FR>N/A</FR>
</loc>