<loc>
<IT>
La cartuccia .375 Holland &amp; Holland Magnum è una munizione da fucile o carabina usata per la caccia grossa. 
Sviluppata in Inghilterra dalla Holland &amp; Holland di Londra nel 1912 per la caccia nell'Africa coloniale britannica e in altri paesi dove si trovano prede 
particolarmente pericolose ed aggressive, ebbe rapidamente un notevole successo data la sua versatilità e il non eccessivo stress meccanico che provocava nelle 
armi. Dotata di potenza sufficiente per abbattere gli animali di maggior mole poteva essere anche usata su selvaggina più piccola senza causare danni rovinosi 
alla preda. Fu introdotta anche negli Stati Uniti d'America intorno all'inizio degli anni venti ed in Europa continentale dopo la fine della seconda guerra 
mondiale. Oggi molte fabbriche costruiscono fucili e carabine in questo calibro che rimane uno dei più apprezzati per la caccia grossa. 
Il bossolo è di tipo "a bottiglia", leggermente conico e "cinturato" (cioè con un anello di rinforzo presso la base), con la spalla piuttosto smussata 
(circa 15º) ed ha una lunghezza di 72,4 mm. La lunghezza totale della cartuccia può variare a seconda del tipo di palla montata ma è generalmente intorno ai 
90 mm. Con palle di peso variabile dai 250 ai 300 grani (1 grano = 0,0648 g) e velocità dai 700 agli 800 (e oltre) metri al secondo, può sviluppare energie 
superiori ai 600 chilogrammetri (5886 Joule). 

https://it.wikipedia.org/wiki/.375_Holland_%26_Holland_Magnum
</IT>
<EN>
The .375 H&amp;H Magnum also known as .375 Holland &amp; Holland Magnum is a medium-bore rifle cartridge introduced in 1912 by London based gunmaker Holland &amp; Holland.
The .375 H&amp;H cartridge featured a belt to ensure the correct headspace, which otherwise might be unreliable, given the narrow shoulder of the cartridge case. 
The cartridge was designed to use cordite which was made in long strands – hence the tapered shape of the case, which, as a beneficial side effect also helped 
in smooth chambering and extraction from a rifle's breech. The .375 H&amp;H often is cited as one of the most useful all-round rifle cartridges, especially in 
shooting large and dangerous game. With bullet weights ranging from 270 grains (17 g) to 350 grains (23 g), it has the necessary punch for small to medium game, 
as well as large, thick-skinned dangerous game. The most common bullet weight available in this caliber is 300 grains (19 g). In many regions with thick-skinned 
dangerous game animals, the .375 H&amp;H is seen as the minimum acceptable caliber, and in many places (primarily in Africa) it is now the legal minimum for hunting 
such game. African game guides, professional hunters, and dangerous game cullers have repeatedly voted the .375 H&amp;H as their clear preference for an all-round 
caliber if they could have only one rifle. Alaskan game guides have expressed a similar preference for brown bear and polar bear country.
Unlike many other calibers, .375 H&amp;H Magnum rifles achieve nearly the same point of impact over a wide range of bullet weights at all commonly used distances. 
This simplifies a hunter's choice in selecting different bullet weights, based upon the game hunted, by requiring fewer scope or sight adjustments, 
which further serves to popularize the .375 H&amp;H Magnum among professional hunters.
When the .375 H&amp;H Magnum was released in 1912 it was loaded with three bullet weights: a 235 gr (15.2 g) at 2,800 ft/s (850 m/s), 270 gr (17 g) at 2,650 ft/s 
(810 m/s)and a 300 gr (19 g) at 2,500 ft/s (760 m/s).[12] However, today, with the availability of a wide range of powders, velocities gains of 150–200 ft/s 
(46–61 m/s) can be realized. Acceptable bullet weights for the .375 H&amp;H Magnum range from 200 gr (13 g) to 380 gr (25 g). The lighter bullets, those weighing 
210 gr (14 g) to 235 gr (15.2 g) are suitable for lighter plains game. Bullets weighing between 250 gr (16 g) to 285 gr (18.5 g) can be used on heavy bodied 
plains game. Bullets weighing 285 gr (18.5 g) to 300 gr (19 g) should be reserved for heavy dangerous game.
Today, a typical factory load such as Remington’s R375M1 or Federal’s ammunition will launch a 270 gr (17 g) spitzer bullet at 2,690 feet per second (820 m/s) 
with 4,337 ft x lbf (5,880 J) of energy at the muzzle. This load has approximately the same trajectory as the 180-grain (12 g) bullet from a .30-06 Springfield. 
However while the .30-06 generates only about 2,914 ft x lbf (3,951 J) compared with the .375 H&amp;H. The 270 gr (17 g) spitzer bullet at .375 H&amp;H velocities has a 
maximum point blank range (MPBR) of about 260 yd (240 m) when sighted in at about 220 yd (200 m). The typical 300 gr (19 g) ammunition manufactured by Federal 
and Remington have a muzzle velocity of 2,530 feet per second (770 m/s) churning out 4,263 ft x lbf (5,780 J) of energy. The 300 gr (19 g) ammunition has a 
bullet trajectory similar to that of the .308 Winchester firing a 180 gr (12 g) bullet. The trajectory allows for a MPBR of about 245 yd (224 m) when zeroed in 
for 210 yd (190 m). Hornady new Superformance line of cartridges provides a leap in performance to the .375 H&amp;H cartridge. The Superformance line uses powders 
specifically blended for each cartridge. Hornady’s 375 H&amp;H 270 gr SP-RP Superformance ammunition fires a 270 gr (17 g) bullet at 2,800 ft/s (850 m/s) for while 
the 375 H&amp;H 300 gr DGS Superformance fires a 300 gr (19 g) bullet at 2,670 ft/s (810 m/s) generating 4,699 ft⋅lbf (6,371 J) and 4,748 ft⋅lbf (6,437 J) of energy 
respectively. The 9.3×64mm Brenneke cartridge is the closest European continental ballistic twin of the .375 Holland &amp; Holland Magnum. When compared to the 
.375 Holland &amp; Holland Magnum the 9.3×64mm Brenneke uses a bullet of a slightly smaller diameter of .366 in (9.3 mm) versus the .375 H&amp;H which uses a .375 in 
(9.5 mm) bullet a difference of only .009 in (0.23 mm).

https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/.375_H%26H_Magnum
</EN>
<DE>
Die .375 Holland &amp; Holland Magnum ist eine weit verbreitete Gewehrpatrone, die in der Jagd vielseitig eingesetzt werden kann. Für die Großwildjagd gilt die 
.375 Holland &amp; Holland Magnum als gerade noch ausreichend. Sie wurde 1912 von der britischen Firma Holland &amp; Holland als .375 Belted Rimless Nitro-Express auf 
den Markt gebracht. Für diese Patrone wurden viele Gewehre (z. T. auch Pistolen) gebaut. Für Kipplaufwaffen ist auch eine als .375 H&amp;H Magnum flanged benannte 
Randpatrone verfügbar. 

https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/.375_Holland_%26_Holland_Magnum
</DE>
<ES>N/A</ES>
<FR>
Le calibre .375 Holland &amp; Holland Magnum a été créé par la société britannique Holland &amp; Holland en 1912 sous le nom de .375 Belted Rimless Nitro-Express. 
Cette cartouche est connue pour être utilisée lors des safaris en Afrique, plus précisément pour la chasse au gros gibier du Big Five. Elle est également 
employée pour la chasse et l'autodéfense contre les ours en Amérique du Nord. 

https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/.375_Holland_%26_Holland_Magnum
</FR>
</loc>