<loc>
<IT>
Il .408 Cheyenne Tactical (abbreviato anche in .408 Chey Tac e .408CT, altresì noto per un certo periodo in Germania come 10,3 × 77 mm Vulkan), è una cartuccia 
rimless (senza collarino né belt) a collo di bottiglia ed è nata per l'uso a lunghissima distanza come cartuccia da tiratore scelto. L'uso è sia militare 
che in ambito civile, vista la precisione anche a distanze estreme, per la disciplina del tiro a lunga distanza. 
È necessario precisare che il .408 Chey Tac non è normato né dalla C.I.P. (Commissione Internationale Permanente, per l'Europa) né dalla SAAMI 
(Sporting Arms and Ammunition Manufacturers' Institute, per gli U.S.A.); è quindi una cosiddetta cartuccia wildcat e tutte le misure sono indicative. 
Normalmente si impiegano canne con un passo di rigatura di 1-13” dotate di 8 righe destrorse. Impiega normalmente inneschi di dimensione Standard Large Rifle 
(in allestimento magnum per una miglior combustione della notevole carica di lancio) e sono in corso sperimentazioni su un innesco intermedio tra quello del 
.50 BMG e quello standard, con un diametro di 6,35 mm. 

https://it.wikipedia.org/wiki/.408_Chey_Tac
</IT>
<EN>
The .408 Cheyenne Tactical designated 408 Chey Tac (10.36×77mm) by the C.I.P.[2] is a specialized rimless, bottlenecked, centerfire cartridge for military 
long-range sniper rifles that was developed by Dr. John D. Taylor and machinist William O. Wordman. The round was designed with a possible military need for a 
cartridge for anti-personnel, anti-sniper and anti-materiel roles with a (supersonic) precision range of 2,200 yards (2,000 m). It is offered as a competitor to 
the most common military NATO long-range service cartridges such as .338 Lapua Magnum and the .50 BMG. 
The .408 Cheyenne Tactical became officially registered by the Commission Internationale Permanente pour l'Epreuve des Armes à Feu Portatives (C.I.P.) on 
15 May 2013 ending its status as a wildcat cartridge. The .408 Cheyenne Tactical has 10.32 ml (159 grains H2O) cartridge case capacity. 
Americans would define the shoulder angle at alpha/2 ≈ 22.13 degrees. The common rifling twist rate for this cartridge is 330.2 mm (1 in 13 in), 8 grooves, 
Ø lands = 10.16 mm (0.400 in), Ø grooves = 10.36 mm (0.408 in), land width = 2.57 mm (0.1 in) and the primer type is large rifle. According to the official 
C.I.P. (Commission Internationale Permanente pour l'Epreuve des Armes à Feu Portatives) rulings the .408 Cheyenne Tactical can handle up to 440.00 MPa 
(63,817 psi) Pmax piezo pressure. In C.I.P. regulated countries every rifle cartridge combo has to be proofed at 125% of this maximum C.I.P. pressure to certify 
for sale to consumers. This means that .408 Cheyenne Tactical chambered arms in C.I.P. regulated countries are currently (2016) proof tested at 550.00 MPa 
(79,771 psi) PE piezo pressure. The cartridge delivers accurate (sub-MOA) performance from a sniper rifle. The Lost River Ballistic Technologies/Jamison 
International 419-grain (26.95 g) very-low-drag bullet is the standard, long-range sniping load. Lost River Ballistic Technologies also designed a 305 grain 
(19.76 g) bullet for the Battlefield Domination Round (BDR). The BDR is loaded with a 305 grain (19.76 g) bullet (claimed G1 BC = 0.612) and is intended for 
short and medium range application using the point-blank range aiming method.

https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/.408_Cheyenne_Tactical
</EN>
<DE>
Die .408 Chey Tac ist eine Hochleistungspatrone, die 1998 von John D. Taylor und Willi Wordman entwickelt wurde. Sie soll die Lücke zwischen der .338 Lapua Magnum 
und der .50 BMG schließen, wobei sie ab größeren Reichweiten die höchste Geschossenergie aller bekannten Gewehrmunitionen besitzt. Verschossen wird diese 
Spezialmunition mit Gewehren wie dem CheyTac Intervention, dem RND Edge 2500 oder dem österreichischen Voere X3. Das Ziel der Entwicklung war, eine kompakte 
Präzisionswaffe für extreme Reichweiten zu entwerfen. Die bisher angebotenen Lösungen verwenden das Standardkaliber .50 BMG, das ursprünglich für schwere 
Maschinengewehre konzipiert wurde. Für die genannte Aufgabe eignet sich eine .50er-Patrone gut, das schwere Geschoss verliert durch seine aerodynamische Form 
wenig an Geschwindigkeit und ist unempfindlich gegenüber Windabdrift, bewirkt jedoch einen erheblichen Rückstoß. Die neue Patrone sollte den Rückstoß zumindest 
mildern, trotzdem auf große Entfernungen vergleichbare Energiereserven und Genauigkeit bieten. Dazu wurde ein besonders langes und aerodynamisch günstiges 
Geschoss entworfen, das sich auch jenseits der 2000-m-Grenze mit Überschallgeschwindigkeit bewegt. Damit ist auch die kinetische Energie des Projektils ab 700 m 
höher als die des .50er-Geschosses. Die effektive Kampfentfernung wird mit 1500 bis 2500 m angegeben. 

https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/.408_Chey_Tac
</DE>
<ES>N/A</ES>
<FR>
La 408 Cheyenne Tactical, plus connue sous le nom de .408 Chey Tac, est la cartouche utilisée par le fusil de précision américain CheyTac M200 Intervention. 
Très puissante, elle est destinée au tir de précision à longue distance ; elle est à ce titre une concurrente de la 12,7 mm et de la .338 Lapua Magnum. 
Le 29 octobre 2016, un tireur de précision français (Benjamin Gineste) a établi le record du monde de tir longue distance avec une carabine "Custom" chambrée en 
.408 CheyTac. Le tireur a reussi à mettre 3 tirs dans une cible située à une distance de 3695m. 

https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/.408_Chey_Tac
</FR>
</loc>