<loc>
<IT>
La cartuccia calibro .44-40 Winchester (N.B. nota anche come .44 WCF, .44 Winchester Center Fire o, più raramente, con la denominazione metrica di 10,8x33mm o di 11x33mm) è, assieme al .45 Long Colt ed al .45-70 Government (V. voce a se) una delle pochissime cartucce ad aver superato in maniera pressochè  indenne il passaggio dal munizionamento a polvere nera (black-powder ammo) al munizionamento a polvere infume (smokeless ammo).

https://www.grurifrasca.net/oldsite/Sito/Ricarica/pistole/44-40.html
</IT>
<EN>
The .44-40 Winchester, also known as .44 Winchester, .44 WCF (Winchester Center Fire), and .44 Largo (in Spanish-speaking countries) was introduced in 1873 by the Winchester Repeating Arms Company. It was the first metallic centerfire cartridge manufactured by Winchester, and was promoted as the standard chambering for the new Winchester Model 1873 rifle. As both a rifle and a handgun caliber, the cartridge soon became widely popular, so much so that the Winchester Model 1873 rifle became known as "The gun that won the West."
The initial standard load for the cartridge was 40 grains (2.6 g) of black powder propelling a 200-grain (13 g) round nose flat point bullet at approximately 1,245 ft/s (379 m/s). Winchester catalogues listed velocities of 1,300 ft/s (400 m/s) by 1875. In 1886 U.M.C. also began offering a slightly heavier, 217-grain (14.1 g), bullet at 1,190 ft/s (360 m/s), also with 40 grains (2.6 g) of black powder. Winchester soon began to carry the 217-grain (14.1 g) loading as well, but in 1905 U.M.C. discontinued the heavier load. 
In 1895 Winchester introduced a 200-grain (13 g) cartridge bulk loaded with 17-grain (1.1 g) of DuPont No. 2 smokeless powder and a bullet for 1,300 ft/s (400 m/s), and in 1896 U.M.C. followed suit with a 217-grain (14.1 g) bullet at 1,235 ft/s (376 m/s) Soon both companies were offering the cartridge with lead "metal patched" (i.e. copper jacketed with lead points), and full metal jacket versions. Taking advantage of the stronger-action designs of the Winchester model 1892 and the Marlin 1894 lever action rifles, 
in 1903 Winchester began offering a higher performance version of the loading called the W.H.V. (Winchester High Velocity), with a velocity of 1,540 ft/s (470 m/s) with a 200-grain (13 g) copper-jacketed bullet from a 24-inch (610 mm) barrel length, U.M.C. and Peters Cartridge Company soon introduced equivalents. Over the years a number of different bullet weights and styles have been offered, including 122, 140, 160, 165, 166, 180 and 217-grain (14.1 g) in lead, soft- and hollow-point, full metal case, blanks and shotshells. 
The most common current loading is a 200-grain (13 g) bullet at 1,190 ft/s (360 m/s). By 1942, more modern cartridges had all but eclipsed the .44-40, but it regained some popularity in the 1950s and 1960s when Colt began once again to manufacture the Single Action Army and Frontier. More recently, the .44-40 has had a resurgence due to the popularity of metallic silhouette and cowboy action shooting, which inspired the introduction of a low-velocity 225-grain (14.6 g) gallery load, the heaviest factory bullet ever available for the cartridge.

https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/.44-40_Winchester
</EN>
<DE>
Die 1873 eingeführte .44-40 WCF-Patrone (.44-40 Winchester Center Fire) war die Nachfolgerin der .44-Henry-Patrone mit Randfeuerzündung. Im Gegensatz zu dieser war sie eine für ihre Zeit leistungsfähige Zentralfeuerpatrone. Entwickelt wurde sie für das Winchester-Gewehr Model 73, den Nachfolger des Model 66. Bereits 1874 wurde die gleich stark geladene .38-40 WCF-Patrone in einem etwas kleineren Kaliber auf den Markt gebracht. 
Aus Gewehrläufen verschossene 200-Grains-Geschosse erreichen eine Mündungsgeschwindigkeit von circa 1310 ft/s (400 m/s), aus einem 7-1/2"-Revolverlauf sind es ungefähr 975 ft/s (297 m/s) Quelle: Ballistics of Winchester Western cartridges 1956, Patronenbezeichnung W4440. Daneben werden auch stärkere Laborierungen für Langwaffen „for rifles only“ hergestellt. Wiederlader fertigen sich ihre Munition aus Präzisions- und Wirtschaftlichkeitsgründen gern selbst. 
Die zu ladende Menge von rauchlosem Pulver beträgt je nach Art des Pulvers und Geschosses nur noch 7 bis 23 Grains anstatt 40 Grains Schwarzpulver. Aus alten Originalwaffen dürfen nur mit Schwarzpulver gefüllte Patronen oder schwach geladene Patronen mit dafür vorgesehenem rauchlosem Pulver verschossen werden. Aus originalen Colt-Single-Action-Army-Revolvern darf rauchlose Munition nur verschossen werden, wenn diese die Prüfmarke VP (in Dreieckform) am Abzugsbügel haben. 

https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/.44-40_WCF
</DE>
<ES>N/A</ES>
<FR>
La cartouche .44-40 Winchester Center Fire fut conçue pour la Winchester 1873. Elle remplaça la munition .44 Henry. Son appellation vient de l'association de son calibre ( .44" ) et de sa charge de poudre ( À l'origine 40 grains de poudre noire ). 
Balistique:
    Masse de la balle : 12,96 g
    Charge de poudre : 2,6 g
    Vitesse initiale : 396 m/s
    Énergie initiale : 1 016 joules

https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/.44-40_WCF
</FR>
</loc>