<loc>
<IT>
Il calibro .410 o conosciuto anche come calibro 36 magnum è una cartuccia per fucili a canna liscia.
Solitamente per le cartucce per armi leggere a canna liscia la misura del calibro è il calibro nominale, detto in inglese gauge (come la calibro 12), il cui valore è inversamente proporzionale al calibro effettivo. Per la .410 il calibro invece è in frazioni di pollice, misurando appunto 0,410 pollici, cioè circa 10,4 mm. La misura del .410 nel calibro nominale sarebbe 67,2. Il nome alternativo, calibro 36 magnum, riferirebbe al calibro nominale, ma in realtà il calibro 36 avrebbe un diametro della canna effettivo di 12,9 mm.
Viene utilizzato per la caccia ai migratori sia da appostamento che alla cerca, i migratori cacciati con questo piccolo ma abbastanza efficace calibro sono: allodole, merli, tordo bottaccio, tordo sassello, cesene e colombacci. Il .410 viene utilizzato anche alla stanziale come fagiani e lepri. Il 36 magnum ovvero il .410 ha varie dosi di piombo che possono variare che vanno dai 15 grammi ai 24, ma la dose ideale per ottenere le massime prestazioni 
è dai 18-19 grammi di piombo che possono raggiungere la velocità di 380 m/s quasi la velocità di un calibro 12. Al giorno d'oggi ci sono molte fabbriche d'armi che hanno iniziato a produrre armi con questo calibro. 

https://it.wikipedia.org/wiki/Calibro_.410
</IT>
<EN>
The .410 bore or .410 gauge, is the second-smallest caliber of shotgun shell commonly available. A .410 bore shotgun loaded with shot shells is well suited for small game hunting and pest control. The .410 started off in the UK as a garden gun along with the .360 and the No.3, No.2 and No.1 bore rimfires. .410 shells have similar base dimensions to the .45 Colt cartridge, allowing many single-shot firearms, as well as some derringers chambered in that caliber, to fire .410 shot shells without any modifications. 
Lancaster's pattern centerfire and pinfire .410 shot cartridges first appeared in Eley Brothers Ltd. flysheets in 1857. By 1874, Eleys were advertising modern centerfire .410 cartridges. It appears to have become popular around 1900, although it was recommended as "suited to the requirements of naturalists, garden guns and for such weapons as walking-stick guns", presumably for self-defense, in 1892 by W. W. Greener. The first ammunition was 2.0 inches (50.8 mm) long, 
compared with the modern 2.5 (63.5 mm) and 3.0-inch (76 mm) sizes. Aluminum shells are available but are not reloadable, as are paper or plastic shells. Full length brass shells can be found and are reloadable. Brass shells can be made from .444 Marlin rifle cartridges, and these are reloadable. 
.410 shotguns loaded with shot shells are well suited for small game hunting and pest control; including rabbits, squirrels, snakes, rats, birds, etc. A .410 loaded with 1/4 ounce slugs is effective against larger animals such as coyotes and deer. 
While a .410 is inferior to the traditional 12-gauge shotshell for defensive use, a number of companies market defensive guns chambered in .410, such as the Mossberg 500 Home Security Model, the Smith &amp; Wesson Governor, and the Taurus Judge revolver. Defensive ammunition such as buckshot, slugs and combination loads are common. American Derringer and Winchester market ammunition loaded with five 000 buckshot pellets in 3-inch (76 mm) shells and three pellets in 2.5-inch (64 mm) shells.
Combination shells such as Winchester Supreme Elite .410 shells are loaded with three 71 grain disks and twelve BB pellets. 

https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/.410_bore
</EN>
<DE>N/A</DE>
<ES>N/A</ES>
<FR>N/A</FR>
</loc>