<loc>
<IT>
La cartuccia calibro .500 Smith &amp; Wesson Magnum (N.B. questa cartuccia è altresì nota come .50 S&amp;W Magnum, .50 Revolver Magnum, 12,7x41R o come 12,7x41Rimmed Magnum) è stata sviluppata nei primissimi anni del XXI secolo dai tecnici della S&amp;W, ma è stata commercializzata solo nel 2003. L'idea era quella di realizzare una NUOVA cartuccia da utilizzare per la caccia (N.B. ovviamente solo nei Paesi ove ciò è consentito !!). Questa nuova cartuccia impiegava palla da 12,7mm di diametro 
(N.B. cioè da .50 centesimi di pollice, da cui la denominazione di .500 S&amp;W Magnum) ed era basata su di un convenzionale bossolo da revolver (rimmed case). Lo sviluppo di questa nuova munizione dalle prestazioni del tutto ESUBERANTI (N.B. la palla da 440grs. di peso viene lanciata a circa 495 m/s, cui corrispondono oltre 355 Kgm di energia cinetica alla bocca !!), ha richiesto la realizzazione di un nuovo telaio (frame), denominato "telaio X" (X-frame), DIVERSO e più ROBUSTO rispetto al convenzionale "telaio N" (N-frame) 
da lungo tempo impiegato dalla S&amp;W per i suoi revolver più potenti. Tecnicamente perlando, si tratta di un derivato parziale della cartuccia calibro .500 Linebaugh (V. voce a se), che a sua volta deriva dal bossolo del .348 Winchester (V. voce a se) tagliato e modificato fino ad accogliere un proiettile del diametro di 12,7mm (N.B. se le due cartucce vengono osservate la loro parentela è molto evidente !!). Così com'è avvenuto per il .460 S&amp;W magnum (V. voce a se), 
anche in questo caso lo sviluppo venne affidato dalla S&amp;W alla Cor-Bon di Detroit (Stato del Michigan, USA).

https://www.grurifrasca.net/oldsite/Sito/Ricarica/pistole/500SW.html
</IT>
<EN>
The .500 S&amp;W Special is a large high-powered revolver cartridge. It was designed and produced by Cor-Bon/Glaser (at Smith &amp; Wesson's request) in 2004.
It is a shorter version of the .500 S&amp;W Magnum with a drastically reduced load, much as the .38 Special is to the .357 Magnum. However, unlike the .38 Special and .357 Magnum, the .500 Special came after the .500 Magnum. 
The purpose of the .500 Special is to be able to shoot less punishing loads, with a muzzle energy closer to that of the .44 Magnum cartridge, in firearms chambered for the .500 S&amp;W Magnum. It is possible that firearms chambered for only the .500 S&amp;W Special will be developed. Smith &amp; Wesson has been urged by author and gun rights activist John Ross to produce their largest "X-Frame" in a shorter version to handle this cartridge. Ballistics are slightly superior to the .480 Ruger.

https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/.500_S%26W_Special

The .500 S&amp;W Magnum (12.7×41mmSR) is a fifty-caliber semi-rimmed handgun cartridge developed by Cor-Bon in partnership with the Smith &amp; Wesson "X-Gun" engineering team for use in the Smith &amp; Wesson Model 500 X-frame revolver and introduced in February 2003 at the SHOT show. It has two primary design purposes: as a hunting handgun cartridge capable of taking all North American game species, and to be the most powerful production handgun cartridge to date. 
The .500 S&amp;W Magnum is considered the most powerful commercial sporting handgun cartridge by virtue of the muzzle energy it can generate. Cor-Bon (now a Dakota Ammo brand) who together with Smith &amp; Wesson developed the .500 S&amp;W Magnum cartridge, offers several loads which include a 325 gr (21.1 g) at 1,800 ft/s (550 m/s), a 400 gr (26 g) at 1,625 ft/s (495 m/s) and a 440 gr (29 g) at 1,625 ft/s (495 m/s). 
Compared to the next most powerful commercial sporting handgun cartridge, the .460 S&amp;W Magnum, which can launch a 325 gr (21.1 g) at 1,650 ft/s (500 m/s) or a 395 gr (25.6 g) at 1,525 ft/s (465 m/s). The .500 S&amp;W Magnum comes into its own when used with heavier bullets, particularly those with weights of 500 gr (32 g) or greater. When possible these bullets should be seated as far out as possible to take advantage of the complete cylinder length, so as to maximize the powder capacity which the case can provide. 
Several manufacturers currently produce the S&amp;W .500 Magnum cartridge, with some of the top-performing rounds delivering 3,031 ft⋅lbf (4,109 J) of energy with a 350-grain (23 g) bullet traveling at 1,975 feet per second (602 m/s). It is claimed to be the most potent commercially available handgun cartridge on the market and provides power similar to long-established wildcat cartridges such as the .375 JDJ (J. D. Jones) and pistol loadings of the .45-70 Government. 
Indeed, some rounds use bullets weighing almost 1 oz. (28 g ~ 440 gr.), which are sent at about 1,500 ft/s (460 m/s) – essentially the same performance of a 12 gauge shotgun slug. Bullet weights available for this cartridge range from a 265-grain (17.2 g) jacketed hollow point to a 700-grain (45 g) hardcast lead bullet. Moderate velocity, heavy bullet loads for the .500 S&amp;W Magnum are similar in performance to the black powder .50-70 Government. The heaviest weight bullet, produced by Underwood Ammo, 
is a hardcast lead bullet weighing 700 grains, about the same weight of a common .50 BMG projectile. This bullet, launched at a little over 1,200 ft/s (370 m/s) produces around 2,100 ft x lbf (2,800 J). While in terms of sheer muzzle energy, it is one of the softer rounds, this loading is actually the most preferred for hunting big game, as the bullet has excellent sectional densities, allowing for deep penetration and high expansion. 
Low recoil or reduced recoil ammunition is manufactured by the Grizzly Cartridge Company and Winchester. The low recoiling ammunition reduces the recoil by lowering the velocity of the projectile and/or the mass of the projectile. Winchester's reduced recoil X500SW ammunition propels a 350 gr (23 g) bullet at 1,400 ft/s (430 m/s). Although such ammunition is considered low recoiling, due to having about one-third of the recoil energy of full-power .500 S&amp;W ammunition, 
even these are a significant step up from most of the .44 Magnums, as they produce twice the recoil energy of the latter cartridge. Cor-Bon introduced the .500 S&amp;W Special in 2004 as a lower energy and lower recoiling alternative to the .500 S&amp;W Magnum cartridge. This cartridge is compatible with handguns chambered for the .500 S&amp;W Magnum and fires a 350-grain (23 g) bullet at 1,250 feet per second (380 m/s).  
These low recoiling alternatives to the full-power .500 S&amp;W Magnum, significantly reduce the felt recoil in the shorter 4-inch-barrel (100 mm) handguns. At present, only Cor-Bon, manufactures ammunition for the .500 S&amp;W Special in three load configurations.  The .500 S&amp;W Magnum has a very high recoil energy and recoil velocity. The high energy and velocity of the recoil will cause the muzzle to rise when shooting the cartridge. 
Smith &amp; Wesson incorporated design features to help mitigate both the perceived and actual recoil of their Model 500 Smith &amp; Wesson revolver chambered for the .500 S&amp;W Magnum. The revolver is equipped with a compensator and Hogue Sorbothane grips. The revolver's considerable weight of 56–82 ounces (1,600–2,300 g) plays a role in moderating the recoil of the cartridge.
A double-discharge effect is sometimes observed with the cartridge. The heavy recoil causes some shooters to inadvertently squeeze the trigger as a reflexive action to hold on to the revolver soon after the discharge of the previous round. Furthermore, some shooters have experienced the cylinder unlocking and rotating after the firing of cartridge which is a partial manifestation of the same phenomenon.

https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/.500_S%26W_Magnum
</EN>
<DE>
.500 S&amp;W Magnum ist eine Revolvermunition mit einem Kaliber von 12,7 mm wie bei der Pistolenmunition .50 Action Express, das die Firma CORBON im Auftrag von Smith &amp; Wesson für ihren Model 500 Revolver entwickelt hat. 
Nur eine Handvoll Waffen wurden vorgestellt, die für dieses massive Magnum-Kaliber ausgelegt waren, einschließlich der X-Frame S&amp;W Model 500 von Smith &amp; Wesson, der Biggest, finest revolver, der Taurus Raging Bull und der deutsche Janz JTL-E 500. Jede der Waffen fasst nur fünf Schuss, da sonst keine ausreichende Wandstärke der Revolvertrommel gegeben wäre. 
Es ist eines der stärksten Faustfeuerwaffen-Kaliber, das in Serie hergestellt wird. Mit einem 400-grain-Geschoss erreicht das Geschoss eine Mündungsgeschwindigkeit von etwa 490 m/s, mit einem 325-grain-Geschoss sogar eine Geschwindigkeit von 549 m/s. Mit den jeweiligen Patronen wird eine Mündungsenergie von über 3100 Joule erreicht.
Im Vergleich zur .460 S&amp;W Magnum (v0 ca. 650 m/s) ist die .500 Smith &amp; Wesson rund 100 Joules stärker, aber bedeutend langsamer, was die .460 präziser macht für Distanzen zwischen 100 und 200 m. 

https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/.500_S%26W
</DE>
<ES>
El .500 S&amp;W Magnum es un cartucho desarrollado por Cor-Bon en colaboración con la empresa Smith &amp; Wesson para su empleo en el revólver S&amp;W Modelo 500. El cartucho se introdujo en febrero de 2003 en la feria SHOT. Su principal propósito fue el diseño de un cartucho para revólver de cacería capaz de abatir todas las piezas de la fauna estadounidense. 
Smith &amp; Wesson había estado a la vanguardia en el desarrollo de cartuchos de arma corta de largo alcance, tales como el .357 Magnum y .44 Magnum. Sin embargo, desde 1960 la empresa había desarrollado en asociación con Remington, otro tipo de cartucho denominado .454 Casull, que eclipsó al .44 Magnum. Desde entonces, otros cartuchos más potentes habían sido desarrollados por otro tipo de empresas.
El .500 S&amp;W Magnum y fue diseñado desde el principio para ser un cartucho de revólver más potente. El gerente de productos de S &amp; W, Herb Belin, propuso la idea de desarrollar el revólver y el cartucho. Con el apoyo del equipo de ventas, el proyecto fue aprobado por el presidente Bob Scott. La munición fue desarrollada por Cor-Bon, en colaboración con el equipo de ingeniería de S &amp; W, Mikuta Bret y Oakley Tom. Once meses más tarde, el 9 de enero de 2003, el equipo dio a conocer el .500 S&amp;W Magnum. 

https://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/.500_S%26W_Magnum
</ES>
<FR>
Le .500 S&amp;W Magnum est une munition pour revolver de très gros calibre, développée par Smith &amp; Wesson et présentée le 9 janvier 2003.
C'est alors la plus puissante munition pour arme de poing de série. Seules quelques armes sont chambrées dans ce calibre, parmi lesquelles le S&amp;W Modèle 500, le Magnum Research BFR ou le Taurus Raging Bull. 
Balistique:
    Calibre : 12,7 mm x 41 mm
    Masse de la balle : de 21 g (325 grains) à 45 g (700 grains)
    Vitesse à la bouche : 550 m/s
    Énergie à la bouche : 3901 J

https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/.500_S%26W_Magnum
</FR>
</loc>