<loc>
<IT>
La .50-70 Government era una munizione bordata a percussione centrale da fucile in uso presso l'Esercito statunitense sino al tardo '800 e primi del '900.
Era la cartuccia a polvere nera per il fucile Springfield Trapdoor e venne rimpiazzata successivamente nel 1873 dalla cartuccia .45-70 Government e poi dalla .30-06 per il fucile Springfield M1903 (basato sul Krag-Jorgensen). Commercialmente era indicata con il nome .50-70-450, cioè:
    calibro .50 pollici (12,7 mm)
    70 grani (4,5 g) di polvere nera
    pallottola da 450 grani (29 g)
Oggi non è più in produzione, quindi il peso del proiettile può essere variato se caricato a mano. 

https://it.wikipedia.org/wiki/.50-70_Government
</IT>
<EN>
The .50-70 Government (also called the .50-70 Musket and .50 Government) is a black powder cartridge adopted in 1866 for the Springfield Model 1866 Trapdoor rifle. 
Derived from the .50-60-400 Joslyn, the cartridge was developed after the unsatisfactory results of the .58 rimfire cartridge for the Springfield Model 1865 Trapdoor rifle.
The .50-70 Government cartridge became the official cartridge of the US military until replaced by the .45-70 Government in 1873. The .50-70 cartridge had a pressure limit of 22,500 PSI.
The official designation of this cartridge at the time of introduction was "US center-fire metallic cartridge", and the commercial designation .50-70-450, standing for :
    caliber .50
    powder charge 70 grains (4.5 g) black powder
    bullet weight 450 grains (29 g)
Ammunition with a black powder charge is currently available commercially from Buffalo Bore. Reloaders have experimented with a variety of bullet weights from 425 to 600 grains (39 g) in weight. Additionally, the US Navy contracted with Remington to produce several thousand Rolling Block carbines chambered for a reduced load version of this cartridge which was officially produced for use only in carbines. This reduced load cartridge used a shortened .50-70 with a 430-grain (28 g) bullet and 45 grains (2.9 g) of black powder.
The US Navy also purchased Remington Rolling Block rifles chambered for the full size .50-70 cartridge. The US Army also ordered both Rolling Block rifles and carbines in caliber .50-70 and also made some Rolling Blocks at their Springfield Armory facility in this caliber. The US Army also had a large supply of percussion-fired Sharps carbines at the close of the Civil War and had the Sharps Rifle company convert about 31,000 of those to caliber .50-70 for cavalry use. 
Meanwhile, the army, which had exited the Civil War with an inventory of almost a million percussion-fired muzzle loaders converted Springfield Model 1863 and Model 1864 muskets to metallic cartridge ammunition using the Allin conversion (trapdoor) method, as well as cadet rifles. The first of the .50-70 conversions was the Springfield Model 1866. Newer improved versions were made and used by the army through 1873. After 1873, with the advent of the 45-70 cartridge, the army declared the .50-70 to be surplus and while some rifles in .50-70 were issued to Indian scouts, 
the bulk were simply sold off as surplus. In the US Navy however, the 50-70 cartridge and the guns associated with it remained in use until the late 1880s.
Buffalo Bill Cody used a Springfield Model 1866 in caliber .50-70 while hunting buffalo to feed the track workers of the Kansas Pacific Railroad (later Union Pacific Eastern Division). General G. A. Custer was known to have and use a sporterized Rolling Block in caliber .50-70 and was believed to have it with him at the Battle of the Little Big Horn.
As army General Sheridan had embarked on a plan to eliminate the bison during the course of the American Indian Wars, the .50-70 rifles were also issued, or purchased, by buffalo hunters for use in eliminating the vast Bison herds. Sharps began manufacturing sporterized rifles in .50-70 (and later .50-90, .50-110, etc.) and with improved sights for longer range shots for use by the buffalo hunters.
In 1867 the .50-70 cartridge in US Army Model of 1866 Springfield rifles played a pivotal role in holding off an attacking force of 300-1000 Lakota Sioux Indians during the Wagon Box Fight.
Modern made functional replicas of caliber .50-70 historical rifles have been imported into the US by such firms as Davide Pedersoli and A. Uberti, Srl. (a Beretta subsidiary). The caliber of .50-70 still enjoys some use and popularity from sportsmen and cowboy action shooters. 

https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/.50-70_Government
</EN>
<DE>
Die .50-70 Government war die erste Zentralfeuer-Ordonnanzpatrone der US-Armee. Sie wurde von Steven Vincent Benét am Frankford Arsenal (Pennsylvania) entwickelt. Sie ersetzte die für die Allin Conversion Model 1865 Rifle entwickelte .58-60-500 Randfeuerpatrone. Sie wurde 1866 eingeführt und bis zur Ablösung durch die – auch heute noch beliebte – .45-70 Government 
im Jahre 1873 beibehalten, jedoch auch später noch in den Indianerkriegen verwendet. Die Benét-Patrone war mit Schwarzpulver geladen; im Gegensatz zu den modernen Zentralfeuerpatronen hatte sie kein von außen eingesetztes Zündhütchen, der Zündsatz befand sich wie bei Randfeuerpatronen im Innern der Hülse. Erst später, mit dem Aufkommen der Messinghülsen, wurden Zündhütchen verwendet. 
Die für das Springfield Model 1866 entwickelte Patrone wurde auch in den Indianerkriegen von Kavallerietruppen verwendet, die mit Sharps-Militärkarabinern ausgerüstet waren; bei diesen Waffen handelte es sich Umbauten früherer Modelle. Gesamthaft wurden etwa 27.000 dieser Sharps New Model Conversion 1865 und Sharps New Model 1869 ausgegeben. Dazu kamen etwa 500 von der Springfield Armory umgeänderte Remington-Gewehre, die Model 1870 Rolling Block U.S. Navy Rifle für die Marine.
Firmen wie Peabody, Remington, Sharps und andere stellten Waffen dieses Kalibers für die Büffel- und Großwildjagd her. 

https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/.50-70_Government
</DE>
<ES>
El .50-70 Government fue un cartucho adoptado en 1866 para el fusil Springfield Modelo 1866. El cartucho fue desarrollado después de los resultados insatisfactorios del cartucho de percusión anular .58 para el fusil Springfield Modelo 1866.
El cartucho .50-70 Government se convirtió en el cartucho oficial del Ejército estadounidense, hasta su reemplazo por el .45-70 Government en 1873. El cartucho .50-70 Government tenía un límite de presión de 22.500 PSI.
La denominación oficial de este cartucho en el momento de la introducción era «US Center-fire Metallic Cartridge», y la denominación comercial .50-70-450, significa:
    Calibre .50 (12,7 mm)
    Carga propulsora de 4,5 g (70 granos) de pólvora negra
    Peso de de la bala 29 g (450 granos)
Como este cartucho ya no se produce, los tiradores que recargan sus cartuchos han experimentado con balas cuyo peso varía desde 29 g hasta 39 g. Hay evidencia que se produjo de forma oficial una variante con carga propulsora reducida de este cartucho para emplearse en las carabinas Sharps modificadas para cartucho metálico, así como en los fusiles de entrenamiento. Esta variante montaba una bala que pesaba 28 g y tenía una carga propulsora de 2,9 g de pólvora.
Buffalo Bill Cody utilizó un fusil Springfield Modelo 1866 que disparaba este cartucho para cazar bisontes y abastecer de carne a los trabajadores del Kansas Pacific Railway que tendían los rieles.

https://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/.50-70_Government
</ES>
<FR>N/A</FR>
</loc>