<loc>
<IT>
La .50 Action Express (chiamata anche "AE" o 12,7 x 33 mm) è una cartuccia per pistola, creata nel 1988 da Evan Whildin. La .50 AE è una delle cartucce per pistola più potenti in circolazione.
La IMI Desert Eagle fu la prima pistola camerata in .50 AE. La cartuccia ha un fondello ridotto (rebated rim) dello stesso diametro del .44 Magnum, che permette alla pistola di essere convertita con un semplice cambio della canna e del caricatore.
L'introduzione della cartuccia negli Stati uniti ebbe un inizio difficoltoso, poiché le leggi per armi non sportive non permettevano proiettili di diametro superiore ai 0.500 pollici. La cartuccia originale aveva un diametro di 0.500" con rigatura convenzionale, 
che fu poi cambiata in rigatura poligonale con l'introduzione della Desert Eagle. Questo risolse il problema della legge sul calibro, ma portò la pistola ad essere considerata un "Destructive Device" secondo il regolamento del ATF. Il diametro nominale fu ridotto da 0.510" agli attuali 0.500", in più il bossolo venne reso leggermente conico.
Il rinculo di un .50 AE sparato da una Desert Eagle è elevato, e leggermente più potente di un .44 Magnum, come se il peso e il meccanismo automatico del arma riuscissero ad ammorbidirlo.
Altre pistole camerate in .50 AE sono l'AMT AutoMag V e il LAR Grizzly Win Mag. 

https://it.wikipedia.org/wiki/.50_Action_Express
</IT>
<EN>
The .50 Action Express (AE, 12.7×33mm) is a large-caliber handgun cartridge. Developed in 1988 by American Evan Whildin of Action Arms, the .50 AE is one of the most powerful pistol cartridges in production.
The Arcadia Machine and Tool AMT Automag V was the first handgun chambered for the .50 AE. The actual cartridge has a .547 inch (13.9 mm) diameter base, with a rebated rim. The rim diameter of the .50 AE is the same as the .44 Remington Magnum cartridge. A Mark XIX Desert Eagle in .50 AE can be converted to .44 with nothing more than a barrel and magazine change.
The introduction of the .50AE in the US was met with a rocky start. US laws state that non-sporting firearms may not be over 0.500" in bore diameter (measured land to land) to meet Title I regulations. The original .50 Action Express bore diameter was .510" with conventional rifling, but the switch to polygonal rifling on production Desert Eagles allowed the gauge plug to drop through, rendering the gun a destructive device under Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco, Firearms and Explosives (BATFE) regulations. Nominal bullet diameter was reduced to the current 0.500 inch (12.7 mm) rather than the original .510" – thus the noticeably tapered case.
Loaded .50 AE ammunition is currently available from CCI Ammunition, Speer, Hornady, and IMI with the latter ammunition being imported into the US by Magnum Research under the "Samson Ultra" trademark. Fired from a standard six-inch Desert Eagle barrel, Speer's 300-grain load produces a muzzle velocity of over 1,500 ft/s, giving a muzzle energy of over 1,500 ft x lb (2,000 J). Fired from a 10-inch barrel, the same load produces a muzzle velocity of over 1,600 ft/s, giving a muzzle energy of nearly 1,800 ft x lb (2,400 J).
Recoil of the .50 AE in the Desert Eagle pistol is substantial, although only marginally more severe than the .44 Magnum, as the auto mechanism and weight of the gun smooth the recoil somewhat. Other firearms chambered for the .50 AE include the AMT AutoMag V and the LAR Grizzly Win Mag. 

https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/.50_Action_Express
</EN>
<DE>
Die .50 Action Express ist eine Patrone mit dem Kaliber 12,7 mm (0,5 Zoll). Sie wurde für die Verwendung in Faustfeuerwaffen entwickelt, die bekannteste Waffe in .50 Action Express ist die Selbstladepistole Desert Eagle. 
Der Boden der Patrone ist mit dem der .44 Magnum identisch. Das ermöglicht es, die Patrone nur durch Austausch des Laufes aus einer für .44 Magnum eingerichteten Desert Eagle zu verschießen. Der Durchmesser der Patronenhülse beträgt 13,9 mm (0,547 Zoll). Diese Munition wird vorwiegend in Kurzwaffen, aber auch in einigen Langwaffen verwendet. 

https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/.50_Action_Express
</DE>
<ES>
El .50 Action Express (.50 AE), 12,7 x 33 según el sistema métrico, es un cartucho de gran calibre para pistola desarrollado en 1988 por Evan Whildin de Action Arms. Es uno de los cartuchos más potentes producidos y uno de los más poderosos cartuchos de pistola en producción.
La Magnum Research Desert Eagle fue la primera pistola semiautomática que empleó el .50 AE. El actual cartucho tiene 13,99 mm de diámetro en la base, con culote rebatido. El diámetro del culote del .50 AE es el mismo del cartucho .44 Magnum. Una Desert Eagle Mark XIX que dispara el .50 AE puede ser modificada a .44 Magnum cambiando solamente el cañón y el cargador. Las pistolas Mark VII en .357 y .44 Magnum tienen el armazón más pequeño y no pueden ser convertidas a .50 AE sin el cambio de la corredera y otras piezas en la fábrica. Cualquier Mark XIX puede ser convertida a 50. AE, pero el modelo .357 Magnum requiere un nuevo cerrojo, cañón y cargador.
La introducción del .50 AE en Estados Unidos tuvo un comienzo difícil. Según las leyes estatales de Estados Unidos sobre las armas de fuego no deportivas, no pueden ser de calibre mayor a 12,7 mm (medido entre campos) para cumplir con las regulaciones del Título 1. El calibre original del .50 AE era de 12,7 mm con un estriado convencional, pero el cambio a un estriado poligonal en las pistolas Desert Eagle de serie las convirtió en aparatos destructivos según las regulaciones de la Agencia de Alcohol, 
Tabaco, Armas de Fuego y Explosivos (Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco, Firearms and Explosives, BATFE). El diámetro nominal de la bala fue reducido al actual 12,7 mm (0,5"), en lugar del original de 12,95 mm (0,512). Por esta razón la vaina es cónica. 

https://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/.50_Action_Express
</ES>
<FR>
Le .50 Action Express (.50 AE, 12,7 × 32,6 mm) est une munition de gros calibre pour arme de poing développée en 1988 par Evan Whilden de Action Arms.
Les pistolets semi-automatiques Desert Eagle d'IMI/Magnum Research, le Grizzly de LAR et l'AMT V d'AMT font partie des rares armes chambrées dans cette munition. Le revolver M500 de Smith &amp; Wesson est quant à lui chambré en .500 Smith &amp; Wesson (12,7 × 41 mm).

    Calibre : 12,7 mm
    Masse de la balle : 21 g
    Vitesse à la bouche : 425 m/s (canon de 15,2 cm)
    Énergie : 1 896 J (canon de 15,2 cm)


https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/.50_Action_Express
</FR>
</loc>