<loc>
<IT>
La 12,7 × 99 mm NATO o .50 BMG (Browning Machine Gun) è una cartuccia sviluppata per la mitragliatrice Browning M2 verso la fine del primo decennio del XX secolo.
Entrata in servizio ufficialmente nel 1921, questa munizione è basata sul forte ingrandimento della cartuccia .30-06 ed è stata prodotta in molte varianti e generazioni tra cui: incamiciata in metallo (FMJ), tracciante, perforante, incendiaria, ad abbandono di involucro e decalibrata. Le cartucce da utilizzare con le mitragliatrici sono unite tra loro con una maglia metallica. 
È uno dei tipi di munizione più grandi mai prodotte con efficacia di penetrazione e con un range di fuoco altissimo, caratteristiche che la rendono adatta sia per le armi individuali e di reparto sia per quelle da trasporto individuale o su mezzo. Esistono 6 tipi di queste munizioni: MU3-TJ (Ball-FMJ), MU3-P (FMJ), MU3-PB, MU3-N (Tracer M17,FMJ), MU3-PN (APT-FMJ), MU3-PBN; i primi due rispetto al terzo differiscono per il peso della pallottola e per la velocità di volata oltre che per l'accuratezza nel raggiungimento del bersaglio, 
gli altri differiscono per tipo di "palla" o per essere traccianti o incendiari. Specialmente i proiettili contrassegnati con MU3-P hanno una penetrazione su uno spessore di acciaio dolce di circa 16mm centrato ad una distanza di 150m. Il modello incendiario MU-3PBN ha lo stesso indice di penetrazione con lo stesso bersaglio ma con effetti incendiari sulla superficie a contatto col proiettile. La cartuccia 12,7×99 mm NATO è anche utilizzata nel tiro a grande distanza e nei fucili dei tiratori scelti, principalmente dalla 
Barrett Firearms Company per i suoi fucili di precisione come il Barrett M82, così come in altre mitragliatrici calibro .50 non Browning. L'utilizzo in fucili a colpo singolo o semi-automatici ha portato alla realizzazione di molte versioni specializzate di qualità (match-grade) non utilizzate nelle mitragliatrici. Un fucile di precisione McMillan Tac-50 .50 BMG fu usato dal caporale canadese Rob Furlong per realizzare il più lontano colpo di fucile messo a segno confermato della storia, 
quando colpì un Talebano a 2430 metri nel corso della campagna del 2002 in Afghanistan. Il record di Furlong è stato battuto nel novembre 2009 dal britannico Craig Harrison, che centrò il bersaglio a ben 2475 m (1,53 miglia) di distanza, superando Furlong di 45 m (49 iarde). Il record di Craig Harrison è stato a sua volta battuto nel giugno 2017 da un cecchino canadese di cui non è stato reso noto il nome: uccisione verificata in Iraq da 3540 metri. Secondo il Times, il proiettile ha impiegato meno di 10 secondi per raggiungere l'obiettivo.

https://it.wikipedia.org/wiki/12,7_%C3%97_99_mm_NATO
</IT>
<EN>
The .50 Browning Machine Gun (.50 BMG, 12.7×99mm NATO and designated as the 50 Browning by the C.I.P.) is a cartridge developed for the Browning .50 caliber machine gun in the late 1910s, entering official service in 1921. Under STANAG 4383, it is a standard cartridge for NATO forces as well as many non-NATO countries. The cartridge itself has been made in many variants: multiple generations of regular ball, tracer, armor-piercing (AP), incendiary, and saboted sub-caliber rounds. 
The rounds intended for machine guns are made into a continuous belt using metallic links. The .50 BMG cartridge is also used in long-range target and anti-materiel rifles, as well as other .50-caliber machine guns. A wide variety of ammunition is available, and the availability of match grade ammunition has increased the usefulness of .50 caliber rifles by allowing more accurate fire than lower quality rounds.
Military cartridge types:
Cartridge, caliber .50, tracer, M1
    This tracer is used for observing fire, signaling, target designation, and incendiary purposes. This bullet has a red tip.
Cartridge, caliber .50, incendiary, M1
    This cartridge is used against unarmored, flammable targets. The incendiary bullet has a light blue tip
Cartridge, caliber .50, ball, M2
    This cartridge is used against personnel and unarmored targets. This bullet has an unpainted tip.
Cartridge, caliber .50, armor piercing (AP), M2
    This cartridge is used against lightly armored vehicles, protective shelters, and personnel, and can be identified by its black tip.
Cartridge, caliber .50, armor-piercing incendiary (API), M8
    This cartridge is used, in place of the armor-piercing round, against armored, flammable targets. The bullet has a silver tip.
Cartridge, caliber .50, tracer, M10
    Tracer for observing fire, signaling, target designation, and incendiary purposes. Designed to be less intense than the M1 tracer, the M10 has an orange tip.
Cartridge, caliber .50, tracer, M17
    Tracer for observing fire, signaling, target designation, and incendiary purposes. Can be fired from the M82/M107 series of rifles.
Cartridge, caliber .50, armor-piercing incendiary tracer (API-T), M20
    This cartridge is used in place of the armor-piercing round against armored, flammable targets, with a tracer element for observation purposes. This cartridge is effectively a variant of the M8 armor-piercing incendiary with the added tracer element. Can be fired from the M82/M107 series of rifles. This bullet has a red tip with a ring of aluminum paint.
Cartridge, caliber .50, tracer, headlight, M21
    Tracer for use in observing fire during air-to-air combat. Designed to be more visible, the M21 is three times more brilliant than the M1 tracer.
Cartridge, caliber .50, incendiary, M23
    This cartridge is used against unarmored, flammable targets. The tip of the bullet is painted blue with a light blue ring.
Cartridge, caliber .50, ball, M33
    This cartridge is used against personnel and unarmored targets. Can be fired from the M82/M107 series of rifles.
Cartridge, caliber .50, saboted light armor penetrator (SLAP), M903
    This cartridge has a 355 – 360 gr (23.00 – 23.33 g) heavy metal (tungsten) penetrator that is sabot-launched at a muzzle velocity of 4,000 ft/s (1,219 m/s). The 0.50 in (12.7 mm) diameter sabot is designed to separate after leaving the muzzle, releasing the 0.30 (7.62 mm) penetrator. It is injection molded of special high strength plastic and is reinforced with an aluminum insert in the base section. The cartridge is identified by an amber sabot (Ultem 1000). For use only in the M2 series of machine guns. 
	This round can penetrate 0.75in (19 mm) of steel armor at 1,500 yards (1,400 m).
Cartridge, caliber .50, saboted light armor penetrator tracer (SLAP-T), M962
    Like the M903, this is a SLAP round, with the only difference being that the M962 also has a tracer element for observing fire, target designation, and incendiary purposes. It has a red plastic sabot for identification, and is used only in the M2 series of machine guns.
Cartridge, caliber .50, ball, XM1022
    A long-range match cartridge specifically designed for long-range work using the M107 rifle.
Cartridge, caliber .50, M1022 long-range sniper
    The .50 caliber M1022 has an olive green bullet coating with no tip ID coloration. The projectile is of standard ball design. It is designed for long-range sniper training and tactical use against targets that do not require armor-piercing or incendiary effects. It exhibits superior long range accuracy and is trajectory matched to MK211 grade A. The M1022 is ideal for use in all .50 caliber bolt-action and semi-automatic sniper rifles. The bullet remains supersonic out to from 1,500 m (1,640 yd) to 1,600 m (1,750 yd).
Cartridge, caliber .50, high-explosive incendiary armor-piercing (HEIAP), Mk 211 Mod 0
    A "combined effects" cartridge, the Mk 211 Mod 0 HEIAP cartridge contains a .30 caliber tungsten penetrator, zirconium powder, and Composition A explosive. It can be used in any .50 caliber weapon in the US inventory with the exception of the M85 machine gun. The cartridge is identified by a green tip with a gray ring.
Cartridge, caliber .50, armor-piercing incendiary dim tracer (API-DT), Mk 257
    The .50 caliber Mk 257 API-DT has a purple bullet tip. The bullet has a hardened steel core and incendiary tip. It is used in the M2, M3, and M85. Dim trace reduces the possibility of the weapon being located during night fire and is visible only with night-vision devices.
Cartridge, caliber .50, armor-piercing (AP), Mk 263 Mod 2
    The .50 caliber Mk 263 has a black tip. The bullet has a hardened steel core and features double valleys to reduce bearing surface thereby decreasing friction and increasing stability. It is used in the M2, M3, and M85.
Cartridge, caliber .50, armor-piercing incendiary tracer (API-T), Mk 300 Mod 0
    as with the Mk 211 Mod 0, but with a tracer component. This cartridge likely can be used in any .50 caliber weapon in the US inventory with the exception of the M85 machine gun, as with the Mk 211 Mod 0.
Cartridge, caliber .50, armor piercing explosive incendiary (APEI), Mk 169 Mod 2
    This cartridge is used against hardened targets such as bunkers, for suppressive fire against lightly armored vehicles, and ground and aerial threat suppression. It is generally fired either from pilot-aimed aircraft-mounted guns or anti-aircraft platforms, both produced by FN Herstal. It is identified by a gray over yellow tip. A tracer variant of it also exists.
Cartridge, caliber .50, ball, Mk 323 Mod 0
    Created by the Naval Surface Warfare Center Crane Division, this cartridge uses M33 ball projectiles in polymer cases instead of brass. It has a clear polymer case, with a standard brass head fused at the bottom. The Mk 323 can be fired from M2HB/M2A1 machine guns and GAU-21/A aircraft guns with the same performance. It gives a 25 percent weight savings over brass-cased ammunition and allows 40 percent more ammunition to be carried for the same weight. The Mk 323's polymer casing is applied to tracer, AP, API, and SLAP projectiles.
DARPA (Defense Advanced Research Projects Agency) contracted with Teledyne Scientific Company to develop the EXACTO program, including a .50-caliber guided bullet. Videos published by DARPA show the guided bullet diverting to strike a moving target.

https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/.50_BMG
</EN>
<DE>
Die Patrone 12,7 × 99 mm NATO (auch .50 BMG, für Browning Machine Gun) ist eine Standardpatrone der NATO vor allem für schwere Maschinengewehre. 
Die Patrone wurde ursprünglich in den 1920er-Jahren von John Moses Browning für das M2-MG entwickelt. Vorläufer dieser Patrone war die von den deutschen Polte-Werken gemeinsam mit Mauser für das Tank- und Flieger-MG entwickelte und im Tankgewehr M1918 verwendete 13×92-mm-Mauser-Patrone mit Halbrand. Vorherige Versuche mit französischer 11-mm-Munition brachten nicht die erhofften Resultate. Durch die Analyse erbeuteter deutscher Tankgewehre mit der dazugehörigen Munition konnte dann die .50 BMG entwickelt werden.
Im Jahr 1982 wurde dieser Munitionstyp von der Barrett Firearms Manufacturing, Inc. erstmals in einem Scharfschützengewehr verwendet, dem M82A1. Die .50 BMG gilt im militärischen Scharfschützenbereich als Patrone mit hoher Zerstörungskraft bei extremer Reichweite und wird überwiegend zum gezielten Einzelschuss gegen Materialziele wie Funkanlagen und Radargeräte verwendet.
Eine zusätzliche Munitionsart unabhängig von den standardisierten Typen ist die in den 1980ern entwickelte Saboted Light Armor Penetrator (SLAP) Patrone. Hier wird ein unterkalibriger pfeilförmiger Penetrator aus Wolframcarbid mittels eines Kunststofftreibspiegels verschossen. Diese Munitionsart dient der Kampfwertsteigerung des M2-Maschinengewehrs. Die Durchschlagsleistung beträgt 19 mm Panzerstahl auf eine Entfernung von 1500 Metern.
Munitionsarten (US-Militär):
Cartridge, Caliber .50, Tracer, M1
    Leuchtspurmunition zur Zielmarkierung, Schussverfolgung und zur Branderzeugung. Spitze ist rot.
Cartridge, Caliber .50, Incendiary, M1
    Brandmunition, wird gegen ungepanzerte und brennbare Ziele eingesetzt. Spitze ist hellblau.
Cartridge, Caliber .50, Ball, M2
    Vollmantelmunition gegen Weichziele und ungepanzerte Ziele
Cartridge, Caliber .50, Armor-Piercing, M2
    Panzerbrechende Munition zum Einsatz gegen leicht gepanzerte Fahrzeuge, geschützte Stellungen und gegen Weichziele. Spitze ist schwarz.
Cartridge, Caliber .50, Armor-Piercing-Incendiary, M8
    Panzerbrechende Brandmunition, die gegen gepanzerte brennbare Ziele verschossen wird. Spitze ist silbern.
Cartridge, Caliber .50, Tracer, M10
    Leuchtspurmunition, die nicht so hell leuchtet wie die M1. Spitze ist orange.
Cartridge, Caliber .50, Tracer, M17
    Leuchtspurmunition, die aus Gewehren der M82- und M107-Reihe verschossen werden kann.
Cartridge, Caliber .50, Armor-Piercing-Incendiary-Tracer, M20
    Diese Patrone ist eine Abart der M8 mit zusätzlicher Leuchtspur und der Möglichkeit, sie aus dem M82 oder M107 zu verschießen. Spitze ist rot mit einem silberfarbigen Ring darin.
Cartridge, Caliber .50, Tracer, Headlight, M21
    Leuchtspurmunition für den Luftkampf, leuchtet etwa dreifach heller als die M1-Munition.
Cartridge, Caliber .50, Incendiary, M23
    Brandmunition zum Einsatz gegen ungepanzerte, brennbare Ziele. Spitze ist blau mit einem hellblauen Ring.
Cartridge, Caliber .50, Ball, M33
    Vollmantelmunition gegen Weichziele und ungepanzerte Ziele. Kann aus Scharfschützengewehren wie dem M82 verschossen werden.
Cartridge, Caliber .50, Saboted Light Armor Penetrator, M903
    Panzerbrechendes Unterkalibergeschoss, das sich in einem Treibspiegel befindet. Treibspiegel ist bernsteinfarben.
Cartridge, Caliber .50, Saboted Light Armor Penetrator-Tracer, M962
    Wie die M903-Munition nur zusätzlich mit Leuchtspurelement zur Schussverfolgung. Der Treibspiegel ist rot.
Cartridge, Caliber .50, Ball, XM1022
    Eine Long-Range-Patrone, die speziell für das Barrett M82A1 entwickelt wurde.
Cartridge, Caliber .50, High-Explosive Incendiary Armor-Piercing (HEIAP), Mk 211 Mod 0
    Eine Mehrzweckmunition mit Wolframkern, leicht entzündlichem Zirconiumpulver und einer Composit-A-Sprengladung. Diese Munition kann nicht aus M85-Maschinengewehren verschossen werden. Spitze ist grün mit grauem Ring.
Cartridge, Caliber .50, Armor-Piercing-Incendiary-Tracer, Mk 300 Mod 0
    Mk 211 mit Leuchtspurelement
Eine Übersicht der in der Bundeswehr verwandten Munition befindet sich in der Liste von Bundeswehrmunition. 

https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/12,7_%C3%97_99_mm_NATO
</DE>
<ES>
El .50 BMG (Browning Machine Gun) o 12,7 × 99 mm OTAN es un cartucho desarrollado para la ametralladora Browning Calibre .50 a finales de los años 1910. Entrando oficialmente en servicio en 1921, el cartucho es básicamente un .30-06 Springfield sobredimensionado. Ha sido fabricado en muchas variantes: bala simple, trazadora, antiblindaje, incendiaria y sub-calibre. Los cartuchos para ametralladoras son encintados con ayuda de eslabones metálicos.
El .50 BMG también es empleado en fusiles de largo alcance y fusiles de francotirador, así como en otras ametralladoras calibre 12,7 mm. Su empleo en fusiles monotiro y semiautomáticos ha dado origen a varios cartuchos de alto desempeño especializados, que no se emplean en ametralladoras. Un fusil de francotirador McMillan Tac-50 calibre 12,7 mm fue empleado por el Cabo Rob Furlong del Ejército canadiense para lograr la baja confirmada a mayor distancia de la historia, 
al abatir a un rebelde Talibán a 2430 metros durante la campaña del 2002 en Afganistán. El récord anterior para una baja confirmada a gran distancia fue logrado por el francotirador de los Marines Carlos Hathcock en 1967, a una distancia de 2286 m. Hathcock empleó este cartucho en una ametralladora Browning M2 equipada con una mira telescópica. Esta arma fue empleada por otros francotiradores, lo cual condujo al desarrollo de fusiles de francotirador que empleaban este cartucho. 
El anterior cartucho estándar para los fusiles de francotirador era el .30-06 Springfield, pero el .50 BMG es más preciso a gran distancia. Está disponible una amplia variedad de cartuchos .50 BMG, al mismo tiempo que la disponibilidad de cartuchos de alto desempeño ha aumentado la utilidad de los fusiles calibre 12,7 mm al disparar con mayor precisión que empleando cartuchos de menor calidad. 

https://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/12,7_%C3%97_99_mm_OTAN
</ES>
<FR>
La cartouche de 12,7 × 99 mm OTAN (également appelée .50 BMG pour « Browning Machine Gun ») est une munition de mitrailleuse lourde et de fusil de précision utilisée par les forces de l'OTAN. 
La .50 BMG présente une capacité de pénétration, une portée et une précision supérieures aux munitions des mitrailleuses moyennes et légères. Essentiellement tirée depuis la Browning M2, elle a été conservée comme munition standard pour les armées de l'OTAN. De nombreuses versions ont été développées, balle blindée standard, perforante, traçante, incendiaire et même sous-calibrée avec un sabot détachable.
La Russie et les pays de l'ex-pacte de Varsovie possèdent quant à eux les mitrailleuses DShK et NVS 12.7 Utes en calibre 12,7 mm dont les performances sont comparables à la KPV chambrée en 14,5 mm qui présente une puissance nettement supérieure à la .50 BMG. 
Cette munition a été conçue pendant la Première Guerre mondiale par John Browning pour un projet d'arme anti-aérienne. Il s'agit d'une version agrandie de la .30-06 Springfield ; la mitrailleuse destinée à la tirer est une mise à l'échelle de la M1919/M1917 également conçue par Browning au début du XX siècle et se nomme M2.
Le développement de la .50 BMG est parfois considéré comme dépendant de la 13,2 mm TuF allemande. Cette munition était développée par l'Allemagne pour être chambrée dans des fusils antichars destinés à contrer les tanks britanniques de la Première Guerre mondiale. Le développement de la .50 BMG a pourtant débuté avant que le projet allemand parvienne à son terme et lorsque celui-ci fut découvert, la question se posa de savoir s'il fallait la copier. 
Après analyse, il apparut que ses performances étaient inférieures à celles de la .50 BMG et que son étui à bourrelet convenait mal à un emploi dans une arme automatique. Entrée en service en 1921, la .50 BMG employée dans la mitrailleuse M2 offrit un avantage sensible aux Alliés pendant la Seconde Guerre mondiale : elle était suffisamment puissante pour défaire nombre de blindés légers allemands, équipés pour leur part de mitrailleuses moyennes et de canons automatiques, certes plus puissants mais beaucoup plus rares et beaucoup plus coûteux. 
À l'inverse, en matière de combat aérien, la .50 BMG, presque exclusivement employée dans les avions de combat américains de la Seconde Guerre mondiale manquait de puissance pour le combat aérien de la fin du conflit. Alors que les autres nations mettaient généralement en œuvre un ou plusieurs canons automatiques à bord de leurs chasseurs, les États-Unis déployaient presque exclusivement la .50 BMG, pour des motifs logistiques.
Des versions modernisées de la mitrailleuse M2 sont toujours utilisées aujourd'hui : elles sont notamment encore utilisées à bord de certains hélicoptères et connaissent une diffusion importante au sol comme arme embarquée dans les véhicules ou pour défendre des positions fixes. La M2 est plus rarement mise en œuvre par l'infanterie seule. Les munitions incendiaires sont particulièrement efficaces contre les cibles aériennes et les munitions perforantes contre de l'infanterie à couvert dans des bâtiments ou encore les véhicules légèrement blindés. 
Elle a néanmoins perdu de sa polyvalence depuis le milieu des années 1950, car certains transports de troupe blindés et d'autres blindés légers sont conçus pour lui résister. 
Bien qu'initialement développée pour les mitrailleuses, la .50 BMG est également chambrée dans des fusils de précision de fort calibre et déployés dans les années 1980 pour des missions de destruction d'objectifs non blindés (radars, aéronefs au sol…). La portée et la puissance du .50 BMG ont également permis de contrer les tireurs adverses équipés d'armes moins puissantes ou d'engager des cibles à longue portée. La cartouche standard de .50 BMG est toutefois trop peu précise pour les missions antipersonnel qui nécessitent l'emploi d'une cartouche spécifique de précision. 

https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/12,7_%C3%97_99_mm_OTAN
</FR>
</loc>