<loc>
<IT>Il .55 Boys è una cartuccia .50 BMG con il collo modificato per accettare un proiettile calibro .55 con anima d'acciaio (per aumentarne la penetrazione) 
e con un cinturino aggiunto alla base del bossolo per sopportare la pesante carica del propellente. 
Le sue performance sono scarse se comparato a munizioni anticarro esterne al Regno Unito come la tedesca 7.92x94mm Patronen 
e la sovietica 14.5x114mm risultando come obsoleta molto rapidamente. 

Mark I:
Questa è la prima variante del .55 Boys. Usa una palla da 926 gr (60 g) con anima d'acciaio con copertura in piombo con camiciatura in acciaio. 
Il proiettile e la versione tracciante vennero creati anche utilizzando un anima in alluminio in modo da rendere più facile il training. 
Ha una velocità alla volata di circa 747 m/s (2,450 ft/s).

Mark II:
Questa variante portava una carica migliorata, per aumentarne la velocità e quindi la penetrazione. Genera una velocità alla volata di circa 884 m/s (2,899.5 ft/s).
Con un angolo ideale, il Mark II era capace di forare un'armatura di 23.2 mm (0.91 in) a 91 m (100 yd), 20.9 mm (0.82 in) a 274 m (300 yd) e 18.8 mm (0.74 in) a 
457 m (500 yd). yards.

APCR munizione con tungsteno
Lo sperimentale "composito rigido perforante" (APCR infatti sta per Armour-Piercing Composite Rigid) venne progettato nel 1942. 
Usa un nucleo in tungsteno invece dell'acciaio, il quale ne aumenta considerevolmente l'abilità penetrante e da una spinta alla velocità di volata 
rispetto al Mark II portandolo approssimativamente a 944 m/s (3100 ft/s). Differisce dal Mark I e Mark II per il suo proiettile in due sezioni. 
Questo modello non è mai stato utilizzato in quanto armi e munizioni anticarro migliori, quali il PIAT,, entrarono già in servizio. 
Nonostante le migliorie, il .55 Boys risultò comunque troppo debole per distruggere i carri inviati dall'Asse. 

https://it.wikipedia.org/wiki/.55_Boys
</IT>
<EN>The .55 Boys (13.9×99mmB in metric) is an anti-tank cartridge used by the United Kingdom in World War II. It was designed for use with the Boys Anti-Tank Rifle.
Contents.
The .55 Boys is a .50 BMG cartridge necked up to accept a .55 caliber bullet and with a belt added to its case. 
It performed poorly when compared to contemporary foreign anti-tank rounds, such as the German 7.92×94mm Patronen and the Soviet 14.5×114mm rounds and, 
as a result, it was quickly deemed obsolete. 

Mark I
This is the first variant of the .55 Boys. It uses a 926 gr (60.0 g). hardened steel core bullet with a lead sleeve, which is covered with a steel jacket. 
A ball and tracer version of this round was also created along with a practice round using an aluminum core in order to be more feasible for training. 
It has a muzzle velocity of roughly 747 m/s (2,450 ft/s). 

Mark II
An improved loading named the Mark II was released in order to increase the round's velocity and its penetration. 
It generates a muzzle velocity of approximately 884 m/s (2,899.5 ft/s).
At an ideal angle, the Mark 2 round was able to pierce 0.91 inches (23.2 mm) of armour at 100 yd (91 m), 0.82 inches (20.9 mm) at 300 yards 
and 0.74 inches (18.8 mm) at 500 yards.

APCR tungsten round
An experimental armour-piercing composite rigid (APCR) .55 Boys round was designed in 1942. It used a tungsten core instead of a steel core, 
which greatly increased its penetrating ability and gave a boost to its muzzle velocity from the Mark II's 884 m/s to approximately 944 m/s (3100 ft/s). 
It differs from the Mark I and II rounds because of its two-part bullet. 
This model was never officially adopted because far better anti-tank rounds and weapons, such as the PIAT, were entering service at the time. 
The .55 Boys, even with a greatly improved bullet, was simply too weak to defeat the tanks being fielded by the Axis powers. 

https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/.55_Boys
</EN>
<DE>N/A</DE>
<ES>N/A</ES>
<FR>N/A</FR>
</loc>