<loc>
<IT>
La .700 Nitro Express è una cartuccia per fucili da caccia grossa, prodotta dalla ditta britannica Holland &amp; Holland a partire dal 1988; 
deriva dalla precedente .600 Nitro Express, di cui costituisce fondamentalmente una versione ingrandita, potenziata e dotata di una pallottola di 
maggiori dimensioni. 

https://it.wikipedia.org/wiki/.700_Nitro_Express
</IT>
<EN>
The .700 Nitro Express (17.8×89mmR) is a big game rifle cartridge made by Holland &amp; Holland, London, England.
The .700 Nitro Express develops an approximate average of 8,900 foot-pounds force (12,100 J) of muzzle energy with a 1,000 gr (65 g) 
bullet at 2,000 ft/s (610 m/s). However handloaders can push the cartridge to generate as much as 15,000 foot-pounds (20,000 J) 
of energy in a modern bolt action, by using a 1,000 gr (65 g) bullet fired at 2,600 ft/s (792 m/s). 
However, doing so necessitates a rifle so heavy it is almost inoperable for hunting purposes. 
Lathe turned cases as used in the Accurate Reloading rifle above will suffer blown primers at this level though a good source of drawn brass would allow 
(in theory) velocities up to 2,700 ft/s (820 m/s). The typical average muzzle velocity of a factory-loaded cartridge is 2,000 ft/s (610 m/s). 
In the 18-pound (8.2 kg) rifle used by Accurate Reloading this would result in recoil energy of approximately 160 ft x lbf (220 J). 
This is more than ten times the average recoil from a .308 Winchester 
which is a very common hunting calibre, and more than 4 times the recoil of a strong .45-70 Government round. 

https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/.700_Nitro_Express
</EN>
<DE>
Die .700 Nitro Express ist eine der größten und leistungsstärksten Patronen für nichtmilitärische Langwaffen. 
Sie wird überwiegend im Bereich der Großwildjagd eingesetzt. 
Die zylindrische, leicht konische Hülsenform der Patrone mit Rand ist an historische Schwarzpulverpatronen aus dem 19. Jahrhundert wie die 
.45-70 Government oder die Patrone .50-90 Sharps angelehnt. Im Vergleich dazu haben moderne Gewehrpatronen aus dem 21. 
Jahrhundert wie die .300 Winchester Short Magnum eine andere Form; sie sind durch eine ausgeprägte Schulter der Patrone zwischen 
Ladungsraum und Hülsenmund erkennbar. Die Treibladung der Patrone besteht aus Nitrozellulose-Pulver. Das Projektil ist mit 65 Gramm 
für Jagdmunition vergleichsweise sehr schwer. Die ballistische Leistungsfähigkeit der .700 Nitro Express liegt unterhalb der Patrone 12,7 × 99 mm NATO. 
Deshalb wird sie in der Regel für wesentlich kürzere Distanzen eingesetzt als die .50 BMG. 

https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/.700_Nitro_Express
</DE>
<ES>N/A</ES>
<FR>
Le .700 Nitro Express (ou .700 NE) est une munition de chasse surpuissante destinée au très gros gibier, 
notamment au safari aux Big Five, plus précisément à l'éléphant. 
Calibre - 17,78×89mm (.700 inch) Masse du projectile - 64.8 grammes Fabricants - A-Square и Woodleigh (balles), 
A-Square, Kynamco Ltd et W. Romey (charge propulsive)
Déviation verticale de la balle par rapport à la ligne de visée :
    Distance de 50 m — 3 cm au-dessus ;
    100 m — 2,9 cm au-dessus ;
    150 m — 6,4 cm en dessous ;
    200 m — 25,6 cm en dessous.
	
https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/.700_Nitro_Express
</FR>
</loc>