<loc>
<IT>N/A</IT>
<EN>
The 5.6×57mm (designated as the 5,6 × 57 by the C.I.P.) cartridge was created by Rheinisch-Westfälische Sprengstoffwerke (RWS) in Germany for hunting small deer such as roe deer, and for chamois. The calibre has a significant following among European sportsmen, and most European mass production riflemakers chamber several models of rifle for this cartridge. During the 1970-1990 period this cartridge was widely and successfully used in the Republic of Ireland for deer shooting, since security considerations 
at a period of Provisional Irish Republican Army violence had led to a ban on the civilian ownership of calibres larger than .224in. Some British small deer specialist hunters use the 5.6×57 mm with great success on roe deer, muntjac and Chinese water deer.
With a factory-load velocity of 3,500 ft/s (1,100 m/s) with a 74-grain, cone-pointed bullet, it is approximately 100 ft/s (30 m/s) faster than the .220 Swift cartridge firing a bullet of equivalent weight. The larger case capacity means that handloaders can produce 50-grain loads that, with velocities in excess of 4,100 ft/s (1,200 m/s), will outpace anything that can safely be achieved by the Swift. The .223 Winchester Super Short Magnum is a 21st-century cartridge that is comparable to the 5.6×57 mm.
The 5.6×57mm cartridge case has a distinctively thick case wall, and this causes significant problems when handloading, owing to the force that needs to be used through the press when re-sizing the case neck. It has been suggested that this unusual neck thickness is the result of the use of .22 rimfire chamber adapters in centrefire rifles chambered for this cartridge.

https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/5.6%C3%9757mm
</EN>
<DE>N/A</DE>
<ES>N/A</ES>
<FR>
La munition de 5,6 × 57 mm (désigné comme le 5,6 × 57 par le CIP) a été créée par la Rheinisch Westfälische Sprengstoffwerke (RWS) en Allemagne pour la chasse aux petits cervidés tels que le chevreuil et chamois. Le calibre est relativement répandu parmi les tireurs sportifs européens, et la plupart des grands fabricants de fusils européens proposent plusieurs modèles de fusils pour cette cartouche. Au cours de la période 1970-1990, cette cartouche a été largement (et avec succès) utilisée en République d'Irlande pour le tir au cerf, car des considérations de sécurité à une période de violence pour l'Armée républicaine irlandaise 
provisoire avaient conduit à une interdiction de possession civile de calibres supérieurs à .224 pouces. Certains chasseurs britanniques spécialisés dans les petits cervidés utilisent le 5,6 × 57 mm avec beaucoup de succès sur les chevreuils, les muntjacs et les cerfs d'eau chinois.
Avec une vitesse de initiale de 1 100 m/s (3 500 ft/s) pour une balle de 74 grains à pointe conique, elle est d'environ 30 m/s (100 ft/s) plus rapide que la cartouche .220 Swift tirant une balle de poids équivalent. Le plus grand volume de la douille permet également d'effectuer des rechargements de la munition allant jusqu'à des charges de 50 grains qui, avec des vitesses supérieures à 1 200 m/s (4 100 ft/s), dépasse tout ce qui peut être réalisé en toute sécurité par le Swift. La .223 Winchester Super Short Magnum est une cartouche du 21e siècle comparable au 5,6 × 57 mm.
La douille de la cartouche 5,6 × 57 mm a une paroi plutôt épaisse, ce qui pose des problèmes importants lors du rechargement des munitions, en raison de la force qui doit être délivrée via la presse lors du redimensionnement du col du douille. Il a été suggéré que cette épaisseur de col inhabituelle est le résultat de l'utilisation d'adaptateurs de chambre à percussion annulaire de .22 dans les fusils à percussion centrale chambrés pour cette cartouche. 

https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/5,6_%C3%97_57_mm
</FR>
</loc>