<loc>
<IT>
Il 5.8 × 42 millimetri DBP87 (" D An (弹) B ùqiāng (步枪) P utong (普通), 19 87 "; letteralmente "Fucile cartuccia standard 1987") è una cartuccia militare sviluppata nella Repubblica popolare Cinese.
L'Esercito popolare di liberazione afferma che la sua cartuccia è superiore alle cartucce della NATO da 5,56 × 45 mm e a quelle russe da 5,45 × 39 mm. Un'altra variante chiamata DBP88 è stata progettata specificamente per le armi automatiche pesanti e per i fucili dei tiratori scelti. La cartuccia pesante da 5,8 × 42 mm ha le stesse dimensioni della cartuccia standard da 5,8 × 42 mm, ma utilizza un proiettile aerodinamico più lungo con un'anima pesante in acciaio per aumentare le prestazioni a distanze prolungate. A partire dal 2010 tutte le varianti della cartuccia da 5,8 × 42 mm sono state gradualmente sostituite dalla variante DBP10. 

https://it.wikipedia.org/wiki/5,8_%C3%97_42_mm
</IT>
<EN>
The 5.8×42mm / DBP87 ("Dàn (弹) Bùqiāng (步枪) Pŭtōng (普通), 1987"; literally "Standard Rifle Cartridge, 1987") is a military rimless bottlenecked intermediate cartridge developed in the People's Republic of China. There is limited information on this cartridge, although the People's Liberation Army says that it is superior to the 5.56×45mm NATO and Soviet 5.45×39mm cartridges. Another variant called the DBP88 "heavy round" was designed specifically for squad automatic weapons and designated marksman rifles. The 5.8×42mm "heavy round" cartridge has the same dimensions as the standard 5.8×42mm cartridge, 
but utilizes a longer streamlined bullet with a heavy steel core for increased performance at extended ranges and penetration.
As of 2010 all 5.8×42mm cartridge variants are gradually succeeded by the DBP10 variant. 
The DBP87 cartridge with 4.15 grams (64.0 gr) bullets has a muzzle velocity of 930 metres per second (3,051 ft/s) from a standard barrel (Type 95 / QBZ-95, 463 mm barrel length), and 940 to 960 metres per second (3,084 to 3,150 ft/s) from the Type 95 LSW (557 mm barrel length). The bullet has a ballistic coefficient (G7 BC) of approximately 0.156.[4] The steel core has a diameter of 4.1 millimetres (0.16 in). In order to save cost, several compromises were made. In particular, the cartridge case is made of steel, which is cheaper than brass. To reduce the chance of rust, the case is covered in a thin layer of protective paint in dark brown. 
To ensure high extraction reliability, the case has a thick rim and a large extractor groove.
The DBP88 "heavy round" cartridge has a 5 grams (77 gr) bullet and a muzzle velocity of 870 metres per second (2,854 ft/s) from a standard barrel (Type 95 / QBZ-95, 463 mm barrel length), and 940 to 960 metres per second (3,084 to 3,150 ft/s) from the Type 95 LSW / Type 95 SAW / QBB-95 (557 mm barrel length), and 895 metres per second (2,936 ft/s) from the Type 88 / QBU-88 (620 mm barrel length). The bullet has a ballistic coefficient (G7 BC) of approximately 0.210. It has an effective range of 800 metres (875 yd) and can penetrate 3 mm steel plates at a distance of 1,000 metres (1,094 yd).
The DBP95 cartridge was developed in 1995 for the QBZ-95. The DBP95 is an improved version of the DBP87 that uses a cleaner propellant and non corrosive primer. Its performance remains similar and the production costs are higher, but the negative effects on the weapon are reduced. It is basically the same round as the DBP87 other than these minor differences, and was used until 2010 when it was replaced by the DBP10.
The DBP10 cartridge is the newest 5.8mm variant to date. It was developed in 2010 and has a hardened steel-cored 4.6 grams (71 gr) bullet, a muzzle velocity of 915 metres per second (3,002 ft/s) and is designed to match all currently serving 5.8×42mm chambered weapons. As such, it will consolidate and replace all previous DBP87/95 and DBP88 5.8×42mm rounds. The bullet has a ballistic coefficient (G7 BC) of approximately 0.193. Major improvements include a non-corrosive primer, a copper-coated steel case with a copper alloy bullet jacket with a 3.8 millimetres (0.15 in) diameter hardened steel core for better penetration of (body) armor. 
It also uses a cleaner burning propellant so as not to leave residue inside the weapon after firing. However, although testing of the previous DBP87/95 5.8 mm rounds showed that they were less likely to cause serious wounds, the issue was not addressed with the new DBP10 round. DBP10 has an operating pressure of 255 to 289.4 MPa (36,980 to 41,970 psi). The DBP10 cartridge weighs 12.9 grams (199 gr). 
Accuracy of fire at 300 m (328 yd) (R50) is stated as 75 mm (3.0 in), at 600 m (656 yd) (R50) is stated as 140 mm (5.5 in) and at 800 m (875 yd) (R50) is stated as 230 mm (9.1 in). R50 at a specific range means the closest 50 percent of the shot group will all be within a circle of the mentioned diameter at that range. The circular error probable method employed by the Chinese and other (European) militaries cannot be converted and is not comparable to the common US methods (groupsize of 5 or 10 successive shots fired at 100 yards) for determining accuracy. 

https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/5.8%C3%9742mm
</EN>
<DE>
Die 5,8 × 42 mm ist eine moderne chinesische Mittelpatrone. Sie wurde Ende der 1980er-Jahre – dem Trend zum kleineren Kaliber folgend – entwickelt, um die Standardpatrone 7,62 × 39 mm M 43 abzulösen. Nach der Entwicklung der Patrone entwickelte die chinesische Rüstungsindustrie eine Reihe moderner Sturmgewehre und Maschinengewehre für diese Munition. 
Basierend auf den Erfahrungen, die die US-amerikanischen Streitkräfte im Vietnamkrieg mit der neuen 5,56-mm-Kleinkalibermunition machten, entwickelte die Sowjetunion die AK-74 mit der dazugehörigen 5,45×39-mm-Patrone. Die chinesische Rüstungsindustrie und das chinesische Militär war über diese Entwicklungen – nicht zuletzt aufgrund der Waffenhilfe für Vietnam, 
infolge der mit hoher Wahrscheinlichkeit Beutewaffen und -munition nach China gelangten – informiert. Im März 1971 fand in Peking die sogenannte „Konferenz 713“ statt, auf der die künftigen Entwicklungen im Infanteriewaffenbereich besprochen wurden und Kriterien für Infanteriewaffen und -munition festgelegt wurden.
Die neu zu entwickelnde Munition sollte ein Kaliber von etwa 6 mm sowie eine Mündungsgeschwindigkeit um die 1000 m/s haben. Gegenüber der 7,62×39-mm-Standardpatrone sollten der Rückstoß und das Gewicht verringert sowie gleichzeitig die Präzision und Endballistik verbessert werden.
Bei der nächsten „Konferenz 744“ wurde das Kaliber auf entweder 5,8 oder 6 mm festgelegt. Für die Hülse wurden sieben verschiedene Entwürfe präsentiert, die Patronengesamtlängen zwischen 56 und 59,5 mm bedingten.
Die eigentliche Entwicklung begann 1978. Im Jahr 1979 wurden das Kaliber 5,8 mm und eine Hülsenlänge von 42 mm als endgültige Maße festgelegt.
Für erweiterte Feldtests wurde eine größere Anzahl Sturmgewehre des Typs 87 hergestellt, die technisch dem auf die neue Patrone umgestellten Typ 81 entsprachen.
1987 war die Entwicklung abgeschlossen und die Patrone wurde als DBP87 in die Bewaffnung der Volksbefreiungsarmee aufgenommen.
DBP88
1988 begann die Arbeit an einer Variante mit schwererem Geschoss und besserer Endballistik. Das Geschoss wiegt 5,0 g und erreicht eine Mündungsgeschwindigkeit von 900 m/s.

https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/5,8_%C3%97_42_mm
</DE>
<ES>
El 5,8 × 42 mm (designación china: DBP-87) es un cartucho de fusil de origen chino para fusil y ametralladoras ligeras. 
Se introdujo al servicio en servicio en 1987 con el nuevo fusil de asalto QBZ-95, que no fue incorporado al servicio de manera formal por ciertos problemas con el arma y su diseño. Se creía que gradualmente supliría y reemplazaría al proyectil 7,62 × 39 mm, que desde 1951 y para entonces era la norma y es aún el cartucho en uso y base para el diseño de armas de asalto en China.
El 5,8 × 42 mm es un ejemplo de la tendencia internacional de fabricar calibres pequeños para uso militar, aumentando la cadencia y sostenimiento de la tasa de fuego, manteniendo siempre el mismo peso portado por la infantería. Cartuchos como el 5,45 x 39 mm, 5,56 × 45 mm OTAN, y el 5,7 × 28 mm belga permiten que un soldado lleve más munición por el mismo peso. Además disminuyen el retroceso y el impacto sobre el cerrojo, favoreciendo el diseño de armas más livianas y la puntería en el tiro automático.
China inicia el desarrollo del cartucho 5.8×42mm/DBP87 en 1979, culminando el mismo con la presentación del proyectil en 1987. El cartucho de munición 5.8×42mm/DBP-87 fue diseñado para reemplazar el 7,62 × 39 mm soviético en uso por el Ejército de Liberación de China (PLA). El fusil Tipo 95/QBZ-95 (Pinyin: [轻武器,步枪,自动, 1995]; en Pinyin: Qīng wǔqì, Bùqiāng, Zìdòng, 1995; o literalmente como "Cartucho ligero para armas o rifles automáticos del año 1995") en su calibre 5.8 mm, dispara el cartucho 5.8×42 mm/DBP-87 o su variante mejorada, el DBP-95; siendo ésta versión el nuevo estándar dentro del PLA.
En junio del 2004, una versión más actualizada del cartucho 5.8x42mm entró en desarrollo en sustitución de su modelo precedente y con el objetivo de de pasar a ser la munición para el rifle revisado Tipo 95-1. Ambos diseños finalizaron en el año 2010 y la producción empezará el mismo año. Este nuevo cartucho es conocido por la sigla DBP-10.

https://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/5,8_%C3%97_42_mm
</ES>
<FR>
La cartouche militaire de 5,8 x 42 mm est une cartouche de fusil utilisée en République populaire de Chine. Sa production a été lancée en 1987. 
Variantes
    DBP87 : version normale munie d'une balle légère conçue pour fusil-mitrailleur et fusil d'assaut.
Balistique indicative de la DBP87
    Masse de la balle : 4,15 g
    Vitesse initiale : 970 m/s
    Énergie initiale : 1950 joules
	
	DBP88 : version normale munie d'une balle plus lourde conçue pour fusil de précision et mitrailleuse polyvalente.
Balistique indicative de la DBP88
    Masse de la balle : 4,80 g
    Vitesse initiale : 890 m/s
    Énergie initiale : 1900 joules

https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/5,8_%C3%97_42_mm
</FR>
</loc>