<loc>
<IT>N/A</IT>
<EN>
The 6.5mm Creedmoor, designated 6.5 Creedmoor by SAAMI, 6,5 Creedmoor by the C.I.P. or 6.5 CM or 6.5 CRDMR for short, is a centerfire rifle cartridge introduced by Hornady in 2007 as a modification of the 6.5 Carcano and the .30 TC, and is based on the .308 Winchester. It was developed in partnership by Hornady Senior Ballistics Scientist Dave Emary and Dennis DeMille, VP of product development for Creedmoor Sports, hence the name. 
The cartridge was designed specifically for long-range target shooting, although it has success in game hunting. Bullet-for-bullet, the 6.5mm Creedmoor achieves a slower muzzle velocity than longer cartridges such as the 6.5-284 Norma or magnum cartridges such as the 6.5mm Remington Magnum. However, due to its overall length of 2.825 inches (71.8 mm), it is capable of chambering in short-action rifles. 
In general, 6.5 mm (.264") bullets are known for their relatively-high sectional density and ballistic coefficients, and see success in rifle competition. The 6.5mm Creedmoor was designed for target shooting at longer ranges, and as such, couples a sensible case volume (3.40 ml) to bore area (34.66 mm2/0.3466 cm2) ratio with ample space for loading relatively-long slender projectiles providing good aerodynamic efficiency and external ballistic performance for the projectile diameter.
For some loads, the 6.5mm Creedmoor is capable of duplicating the muzzle velocity or trajectory of the .300 Winchester Magnum while generating significantly-lower recoil, based on lighter projectile weight. This cartridge is designed for a bolt-face diameter of .473 inches (roughly 12 mm), conversion of a short action rifle to another caliber (such as the .22-250 Remington, .243 Winchester or .300 Savage) with similar bolt-face diameter generally requires 
little more than a simple barrel change, or on the Armalite-style AR-10 series, a complete upper-assembly.
The 6.5mm Creedmoor is a medium-power cartridge comparable to the .260 Remington and 6.5×47mm Lapua. Three-hundred yard energy using 129-grain Hornady SST bullets is listed by an independent reviewer as 1,641 foot-pounds force (2,225 J). For the 140 grain bullet at 2,700 feet per second (823 m/s) initial velocity, another reviewer reports an MPBR for a six-inch-high target of 265 yards (242 m), 
and reports a manufacturer-claim of "almost 1,600 ft x lbf (2,169 J)" of retained energy at 300 yards (274 m) using a 24 inches (610 mm) barrel. SAAMI test data confirms 6.5 mm Creedmoor, 15 feet (4.6 m) from muzzle, velocity of 2,940 ft/s (896 m/s) for the 129-grain bullet and 2,690 ft/s (820 m/s) for the 140-grain bullet (which compares to .300 Winchester Magnum data of 2,930 ft/s (893 m/s) for a 200-grain bullet and 2,665 ft/s (812 m/s) for a 210-grain bullet).[2] Long-range shooter Ray "RayDog" Sanchez summarized the bolt-action Tubb 2000 rifle in 6.5mm Creedmoor as "boringly accurate" at 1,000 yards (914 m). He asserted the rifle/ammunition combination he used maintained sub-MOA groups at 1,000 yards (914 m).

https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/6.5mm_Creedmoor
</EN>
<DE>N/A</DE>
<ES>N/A</ES>
<FR>N/A</FR>
</loc>