<loc>
<IT>
La cartuccia calibro 6,5mm Remington Magnum è un derivato diretto della cartuccia calibro .350 Remington Magnum ottenuto per restringimento del colletto fino a consentire l'introduzione di un proiettile del diametro nominale di 6,5mm (.264"). La sua commercializzazione  risale al 1966, quando la Remington la presentò per la prima volta insieme ad una nuova versione della carabina Modello 600. Putroppo l'arma per la quale il 6,5mm Remington Magnum venne inizialmente camerato aveva una canna troppo CORTA (N.B. era di soli 470mm contro i 610mm tipici di un'arma da caccia !!), il che rendeva impossibile sfruttare appieno il potenziale operativo di questa nuova cartuccia. Viceversa, con una canna "canonica" di 610mm di lunghezza (24"), il 6,5mm Remington Magnum è in grado di sviluppare tutto ciò di quanto è capace. Sotto questo aspetto il 6,5mm Remington Magnum è idoneo per la caccia a qualsiasi animale che vive sul continente americano, con la sola eccezione degli animali più grossi e pericolosi. Lo stesso discorso vale per la caccia in Asia o in Africa. Naturalmente il 6.5mm Remington Magnum è idoneo per svolgere qualsiasi tipo di attività venatoria nel continente europeo. 
L'unico difetto di questa interessante cartuccia è rappresentato dal colletto eccessivamente "corto", il richiede che i proiettili siano inseriti in profondità per rispettare la lunghezza complessiva massima prevista (O.A.L.). Questo comporta che lo spazio interno venga ridotto, con la conseguenza che risulterànno a sua volta ridotte il quantitativo di polvere introdotta e la velocità esprimibile (N.B. usando un'arma con una canna corta la perdita di velocità sarà evidente). Per questo motivo, i primi caricamenti commerciali eano basati su una palla da 120grs. (7,7 GRAMMI), allo scopo di trovare il giusto compromesso tra massa e velocità.

(https://www.grurifrasca.net/oldsite/Sito/Ricarica/fucili/6,5RM.html)
</IT>
<EN>
The 6.5mm Remington Magnum is a .264 caliber (6.7 mm) belted bottlenecked cartridge introduced in 1966. The cartridge is based on a necked down .350 Remington Magnum which on turn is based on a shortened, necked down, blown out .375 H&amp;H Magnum case. The cartridge was one of the first short magnum cartridges. 

The 6.5 mm (.264 caliber) has been extremely popular in Europe and especially in the Scandinavian countries and this trend continues today. The 6.5x52mm Carcano, 6.5x53mmR (.256 Mannlicher), 6.5x54mm Mannlicher-Schönauer, 6.5×55mm Swedish Mauser, 6.5×58mmR Krag–Jørgensen and the 6.5×58mm Portuguese are among these cartridges of originally military European origin. What the 6.5 mm (.264 caliber) bullets offered was excellent sectional density and ballistic coefficients. The Scandinavian countries dominated the Olympics in the Nordic events shooting 6.5 mm center fire cartridges like the 6.5×55mm until 1972 when the centerfire shooting events were dropped. However, in North America the .264 caliber did not make much of a head way in terms of popularity. Beginning in the 1950s several ex-service Norwegian Krag–Jørgensen and Swedish Mauser began trickling into the United States. Winchester had designed the .264 Winchester Magnum but it did not gain much of a following and the rifles were plagued by short barrel lives.
In 1966 Remington introduced the 6.5 Remington Magnum, which was based upon the previous years' .350 Remington Magnum, in the 18.5 inch barrel Model 600 carbine. This was poor choice of rifle by Remington as it was unable to exploit the performance potential of the 6.5mm Remington. While Remington did later chamber the cartridge in the 24 inch Model 700 rifle, the damage was already done to the cartridge's reputation. Damage from which it would never fully recover, and eventually it passed into obsolesce. Attempts have been made to revive the cartridge by Ruger and then again by Remington in 2004 in the Model 673 Guide Rifle but these attempts at revival have been unsuccessful.
The 6.5mm Remington Magnum remains an excellent rifle cartridge with a greater performance potential over all the European 6.5mm cartridges save the 6.5x68mm RWS which is similar to the .264 Winchester Magnum. Furthermore, due to its short stature, it can be chambered in lighter, quicker handling short action rifles. On account of the case capacity of the cartridge a barrel with a minimum length of 24 inches is necessary to realize the potential of the cartridge. With shorter barrels performance level drop dramatically especially when slower burning powders are utilized.
Currently Remington no longer produces ammunition for the cartridge.

 (https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/6.5mm_Remington_Magnum)
</EN>
<DE>N/A</DE>
<ES>N/A</ES>
<FR>N/A</FR>
</loc>