<loc>
<IT>N/A</IT>
<EN>
The 6.5×68mm rebated rim bottlenecked centerfire rifle cartridge (also known as the 6.5×68mm RWS, 6.5×68mm Schüler, or the 6.5×68mm Von Hofe Express) and its sister cartridge the 8×68mm S were developed in the 1930s by August Schüler from the August Schüler Waffenfabrik, Suhl, Germany as magnum hunting cartridges that would just fit and function in standard-sized Mauser 98 bolt-action rifles. This is one of the early examples where a completely new rifle cartridge (the 6.5×68mm and 8×68mm S have no other cartridge as parent case) was developed by a gunsmith to fit a specific popular and widespread type of rifle. 
German and Austrian hunters use the powerful, high velocity 6.5×68mm for long-range hunting in mountainous terrain like the Alps mountain range. The 6.5×68mm as a pure civil cartridge can be used in countries which ban civil use of former or current military ammunition.
Since there are not many factory loads available (RWS offers only 2 factory loads) and due to its good field reputation, the 6.5×68mm is often used by reloaders. They have used this cartridge extensively to create powerful loads by handloading.
Factory rifles in 6.5×68mm normally have 250 mm to 280 mm (1 in 9.8 to 11 inch) twist rates, which are too long to adequately stabilize modern long heavy 6.5 mm bullets. This slow twist rate was chosen since the bullet jackets used in the 1930s were not strong enough to cope with the forces generated by the magnum muzzle velocities of the 6.5×68mm. The traditional 6.5×68mm twists nowadays inhibits its potential. To make the 6.5×68mm an awesome long-range cartridge, rifle barrels with a 200 mm to 230 mm (1 in 7.9 to 9 inch) twist rate are a better choice. Due to the large case capacity in relation to the 6.5 mm (.264 inch) caliber bore size the 6.5×68mm is very harsh on barrels. The 6.5×68mm typically wears out a rifle barrel in 500 to 1000 rounds. A lot of thorough barrel cleaning (after every 5 shots) and carefully avoiding long strings of shots help to minimize barrel wear. This makes this cartridge impractical for most competition shooters who tend to fire a lot of rounds in practice to acquire and maintain expert long-range marksmanship.
Reloaders use the 6.5×68mm as a Jack of all trades long-range cartridge on all European game from fox, roe deer and chamois upwards to the big European game like red deer and moose. These people realized that bullets with different characteristics can be utilized to produce varying effects on game. As with all 6.5 mm cartridges, the big game hunting bullets used in the 6.5×68mm have comparatively high sectional densities for good penetration on suitable size game animals. 

https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/6.5%C3%9768mm
</EN>
<DE>N/A</DE>
<ES>N/A</ES>
<FR>N/A</FR>
</loc>