<loc>
<IT>
La cartuccia progettata da Vladimir Fedorov aveva una manica a forma di bottiglia e non aveva un bordo sporgente, la manica stessa era piuttosto lunga (57,1 mm) ed era realizzata in ottone. Nella forma e nel design del bossolo, la cartuccia era simile al calibro di cartuccia tedesco 7,92x57 mm (Mauser). Il vantaggio principale della cartuccia di potenza ridotta e calibro era una riduzione del rinculo durante le riprese, che rendeva le munizioni più comode se usato in armi automatiche, in particolare il fucile automatico, su cui il progettista lavorava (rispetto alle normali cartucce di fucile di quegli anni). 
Infatti, Vladimir Fedorov ha immediatamente creato un sistema - "cartuccia d'arma". Prendendo la custodia a forma di bottiglia senza il labbro sporgente come base, il progettista si è assicurato un lavoro di base per la creazione di un sistema semplificato per la fornitura di cartucce e l'estrazione di cartucce esaurite, nonché di grandi magazzini, che erano già stati portati alle cartucce 1920 negli 25.
Le opere che Fedorov ha iniziato in 1910-ies, hanno anticipato l'emergere nel futuro di una cartuccia intermedia per armi automatiche e sono stati il ​​primo passo in questa direzione. La macchina automatica creata da Fedorov e la cartuccia per esso sono stati testati in 1913 un anno prima dell'inizio della prima guerra mondiale. 
Come osserva lo storico delle armi Andrei Ulanov, in condizioni normali, le cartucce 3200 sono state testate durante i test, per tutto il tempo di test, è stata rilevata la percentuale di ritardi per 1,18, per quel periodo di tempo e la fase di test è stato considerato un buon risultato. Lo stesso designer ha scritto che il lavoro sulla nuova cartuccia è stato riconosciuto come prezioso e importante, e le prove preliminari della mitragliatrice e della cartuccia sono risultate così favorevoli che è stato pianificato di produrre migliaia di cartucce 200 per test completi delle nuove munizioni per ulteriori test sviluppati da Fedorov.
Sfortunatamente, lo sviluppo dell'automa e della cartuccia ad esso è stato impedito dalla prima guerra mondiale, che ha avuto inizio in 1914. Il tempo di guerra non permetteva di sperimentare e portare armi, il lavoro sperimentale negli impianti venne fermato. Allo stesso tempo, l'impero russo si trovò di fronte a una grave carenza di fucili e cartucce convenzionali per loro, che fu la ragione per l'acquisto di prodotti rilevanti all'estero. È per questo motivo che nell'anno 1916, Vladimir Fedorov ha rifatto il suo fucile mitragliatore sotto la cartuccia giapponese 6,5x50 mm Arisaka, 
in quel momento c'erano già abbastanza cartucce di questo tipo in Russia. Più di 100 sono passati anni dagli eventi descritti, ma la cartuccia del calibro 6,5 mm diventa di nuovo rilevante e richiesta. All'inizio di 2019, l'informazione cominciò a comparire su vari media che le piccole braccia dell'esercito americano stavano aspettando una trasformazione radicale. La principale trasformazione sarà la sostituzione delle cartucce calibro 5,56x45 mm NATO con nuove cartucce calibro 6,5 mm. 
I primi campioni di nuove munizioni dovrebbero essere testati prima della fine del 2019 dell'anno, e nuovi fucili automatici e mitragliatrici leggeri dovranno essere inviati per prove militari già negli 2020. 

https://it.topwar.ru/159207-65-mm-patron-fedorova.html
</IT>
<EN>
Vladimir Grigorievich Fedorov graduated from the Mikhailovsky Artillery Academy in 1900, and almost immediately was appointed to serve in the Artillery Committee of the GAU. The young design engineer worked a lot on studying the specifics of using new ammunition from different countries. During the development and adoption of the upgraded 7,62x54 mm cartridge with a light bullet, the young designer presented his own concept for the 6,5 mm caliber rifle ammunition. The new cartridge of reduced power was distinguished by its perspective design and should have been ideally suited for firing from automatic weapons. 
The creation of ammunition of such a caliber Fedorov was largely inspired by the experience of the Russian-Japanese war and the use of the 6,5xNNXX mm cartridge by the Japanese. 
Already in 1911, Vladimir Fedorov presented his 5-charging automatic rifle under the usual cartridge 7,62x54 mm (in modern terminology - a self-loading rifle). In 1912, the new weapon passed the test stage at the test site, and the artillery committee decided to purchase a batch of new rifles. At the same time, the designer worked on the creation of a fully-fledged automaton chambered for the 6,5 mm cartridge of its own design. The cartridge created by Fedorov was supposed to be more powerful than Japanese ammunition - 6,5x57 mm. Especially for him it was planned to produce three types of pointed bullets: two with a lead core (length 31,37 mm and 32,13 mm, respectively) and an armor-piercing bullet with a core of tungsten (length 30,56 mm). The weight of the cartridge was approximately 21 grams.
The cartridge designed by Vladimir Fedorov had a bottle-shaped sleeve and did not have a protruding rim, the sleeve itself was quite long (57,1 mm) and was made of brass. In form and design of the cartridge case, the cartridge was similar to the German cartridge caliber 7,92x57 mm (Mauser). The main advantage of the cartridge of reduced power and caliber was a reduction in recoil when shooting, which made the ammunition more convenient when used in automatic weapons, in particular the automatic rifle, which the designer worked on (compared to ordinary rifle cartridges of those years). In fact, Vladimir Fedorov immediately created a system - “weapon-cartridge”. 
Taking the bottle-shaped sleeve without a protruding lip as a basis, the designer secured a groundwork for creating a simplified system for supplying cartridges and extracting spent cartridges, as well as capacious stores, which had already been brought to 1920 cartridges in the 25s.
The works that Fedorov began in 1910-ies, anticipated the emergence in the future of an intermediate cartridge for automatic weapons and were the first step in this direction. The automat created by Fedorov and the cartridge for it were tested in 1913 a year before the start of the First World War. As the weapon historian Andrei Ulanov notes, under normal conditions, the 3200 cartridges were tested during tests, for all the testing time, the percentage of delays for the 1,18 was noted, for that period of time and the testing phase this was considered a good result. 
The designer himself wrote that the work on the new cartridge was recognized as valuable and important, and the preliminary tests of the machine gun and the cartridge for it turned out to be so favorable that it was planned to make 200 thousands of cartridges for comprehensive testing of the new ammunition for further tests developed by Fedorov.
Unfortunately, the development of the automaton and the cartridge to it was prevented by the First World War, which began in 1914,. The wartime did not allow to experiment and bring weapons, the experimental work at the plants was stopped. At the same time, the Russian Empire was faced with a serious shortage of conventional rifles and cartridges for them, which was the reason for the purchase of relevant products abroad. It is for this reason that in the 1916 year, Vladimir Fedorov remade his submachine gun under the Japanese cartridge 6,5x50 mm Arisaka, there were already enough cartridges of this type in Russia at that time.
More than 100 years have passed since the events described, but the cartridge of the caliber 6,5 mm again becomes relevant and in demand. At the beginning of 2019, information began to appear in various media that the small arms of the American army were waiting for a radical transformation. The main transformation will be the replacement of cartridges caliber 5,56x45 mm NATO with new cartridges caliber 6,5 mm. The first samples of new ammunition are planned to be tested before the end of the 2019 of the year, and new automatic rifles and light machine guns will have to be sent for military trials already in the 2020s.

https://en.topwar.ru/159207-65-mm-patron-fedorova.html
</EN>
<DE>N/A</DE>
<ES>N/A</ES>
<FR>N/A</FR>
</loc>