<loc>
<IT>N/A</IT>
<EN>
The 6mm Lee Navy (6×60mmSR), also known as the 6mm U.S.N. or .236 Navy, is an obsolete American rifle cartridge. It was the service cartridge of the United States Navy and Marine Corps from 1895 (replacing the .45-70 Government round) to 1899, when it was replaced by the .30-40 Krag. It was the first small-bore high-velocity smokeless powder cartridge to be adopted by either service.
A commercial sporting version of the M1895 Lee Straight Pull was sold by Winchester. It did not sell well in U.S. markets due to a heavy preference by American consumers for lever-action rifle designs. The cartridge was chambered for a time in the Remington-Lee and Blake magazine rifles. With a reputation for penetration and explosive effect, the 6mm Lee was reportedly quite popular as a hunting cartridge in Alaska and Northwest Canada. It was discontinued from commercial production in 1935. The 6mm Lee cartridge case later served as the basis for the .220 Swift, which used a necked-down 6mm Lee case with a .22-caliber bullet.

https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/6mm_Lee_Navy
</EN>
<DE>N/A</DE>
<ES>
El 6mm Lee Navy (6 x 60 SR), también conocido como el 6mm U.S.N.​ o .236 Navy, es un cartucho estadounidense de fusil obsoleto.​ Fue el cartucho estándar de la Armada de los Estados Unidos y el Cuerpo de Marines de los Estados Unidos desde 1895, reemplazando oficialmente al cartucho .45-70 Government, y era el primer cartucho con bala de pequeño calibre y alta velocidad cargado con pólvora sin humo en ser adoptado por cualquier rama de las Fuerzas Armadas estadounidenses. El 6mm Lee Navy fue a su vez reemplazado en 1899 por el cartucho .30 Army (.30-40 Krag). 
La Winchester vendió una versión de cacería del Lee M1895 con cerrojo rectilíneo. No se vendió bien en el mercado civil estadounidense, debido a la gran preferencia por los fusiles de palanca entre los consumidores estadounidenses. El 6mm Lee Navy fue empleado por un tiempo en los fusiles Remington-Lee M1885 y Blake. Con una reputación de buena penetración y efecto explosivo, el 6mm Lee Navy fue bastante popular como cartucho de caza en Alaska y el noroeste de Canadá.​ Su producción comercial cesó en 1935. El casquillo del 6mm Lee Navy posteriormente sirvió como base para el .220 Swift, que emplea un casquillo de 6mm Lee Navy con el cuello recortado y monta una bala de calibre 5,5 mm.

https://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/6mm_Lee_Navy
</ES>
<FR>N/A</FR>
</loc>