<loc>
<IT>
Nata poco dopo la .223 militare, su progetto della Remington, la poteva superare in precisione e fu per molto tempo la 6mm. più precisa per il tiro di Bench-Rest con cui furono anche fatti alcuni record. In seguito l'avvento del .308 fece decadere anche questa munizione. Molti AR15 furono ricamerati in 6x45mm.
In realtà le prestazioni di queste munizioni nate dai bossoli .222 e .223 sono identiche, la 6mm-223 Rem. ebbe maggiore successo con l'uso di bosoli militari, più economici e dall'approvigionamento continuo, inoltre l'uso di proiettili più pesanti l'ha resa per breve tempo, più precisa emeno sensibile al vento sulle lunghe distanze. 

(http://www.tiropratico.com/ammunition/pagine/6x45.html)
</IT>
<EN>
The 6×45mm is a rimless, bottlenecked cartridge based on the .223 Remington or 5.56 NATO cartridge necked up to .243 (6mm). The cartridge is also known as the 6mm-223 Remington or 6mm/223. 
Soon after the release of the .223 Remington as a commercial cartridge, shooters began experimenting with the cartridge in an attempt to improve its performance. Several of these experimenters necked up the .223 Remington to 6mm as the .243 inches (6.17 mm) caliber bullets provided better external ballistic performance over .224 inches (5.69 mm) caliber bullets. While several variations existed between early versions of these cartridges, the 6×45mm as we know it today became the standard version of the cartridge which is simply a necked up version of the .223 Remington without any further modifications or improvements made to it. 

The 6×45 mm is a wildcat cartridge and has not been standardized by any agency nor has it been offered a proprietary cartridge by any ammunition manufacturer. Some specialty rifle makers such as those that sell varmint rifles offer rifles chambered in this cartridge. Specifications for the cartridge are derived from the necked up parent cartridge without further improvement. 
The cartridge maximum overall length is nominally given as 2.230-inch (56.6 mm), however, as the cartridge is a wildcat cartridge chamber dimensions may vary from manufacturer to manufacturer. For this reason overall length of the cartridge may vary. 
The AR-15/M16 can easily be converted to the 6×45mm with a simple barrel swap with few or no further modifications to the rifle. This is also true for rifles such as Ruger’s Mini-14 and most bolt-action rifles chambered for the .223 Remington cartridge. The 6×45mm cartridge provides better down range performance than the .223 Remington or the 5.56 NATO cartridges. The cartridge is currently offered by Les Baer in an AR rifle. The cartridge had been offered by Cooper Arms, Kimber and a few other rifle manufacturers in their rifles as a regular factory chambering for a period of time.
However, the cartridge’s breakthrough was in the area of handgun hunting where it became very popular. The bolt-action Remington XP-100 pistol and the break-action Thompson/Center Contender handgun were chambered for the cartridge. It provided a flat-shooting cartridge capable of taking small deer and small game species.
In February 2010, Black Hills Ammunition began selling 6×45mm ammunition. They use standard .243 bullets weighing 85 and 100 gr. Sporting Products LLC also began to distribute AR-15 uppers and complete rifles chambered for the 6×45mm.
Shultz &amp; Larsen of Denmark offer the "Legacy" model. A light weight (2,65 kg / 5lbs 13,5oz), miniature action, barrel swap rifle system. Calibers offered are .222 Rem (1/10" twist), .223 Rem (1/8" and 1/10" twist), 6x45 (1/8" twist) and .300 Whisper (1/7,5" twist). standard barrels are 510 mm / 20" long. 

(https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/6%C3%9745mm)
</EN>
<DE>N/A</DE>
<ES>N/A</ES>
<FR>N/A</FR>
</loc>