<loc>
<IT>
Il 7,62 × 39 mm è uno dei due calibri standard delle munizioni da guerra di produzione sovietica.
È stata utilizzata dalla mitragliatrice leggera RPD nel 1944 e successivamente dal fucile d'assalto AK-47, venendo poi sostituita dagli eserciti del blocco ex-sovietico dal calibro 5,45 × 39 mm. 

Lo sviluppo venne iniziato allo scopo di ideare una munizione intermedia simile al 7,92 × 33 mm utilizzata dall'StG 44; questa tendenza fu seguita dalla NATO che introdusse il calibro 7,62 × 51 mm. La nuova cartuccia venne ideata dall'esigenza di trovare una cartuccia più potente del 7,62 × 25 mm Tokarev ma meno potente della 7,62 × 54 mm R, proporzionalmente uguale alla cartuccia 14.5 × 114 mm anticarro. 
La munizione da guerra Sovietica, denominata M43 ha l'ogiva con anima in acciaio, ricoperto di piombo ed esternamente una camiciatura in rame. La cartuccia è composta di un innesco Berdan e bossolo in acciaio.
Successivamente, nel 1960, la Jugoslavia sperimentò una nuova versione, la M60 con profilo più tozzo; l'anima in acciaio della palla anziché avere tutta la lunghezza dell'ogiva era contenuta solo nella parte anteriore. Questa modifica ha spostato il centro di gravità nella parte posteriore del proiettile, causando così un effetto di ribaltamento e quindi a creare una maggior cavità temporanea in caso di impatto su tessuti. 

https://it.wikipedia.org/wiki/7,62_%C3%97_39_mm
</IT>
<EN>
The 7.62×39mm (aka 7.62 Soviet or formerly .30 Russian Short) round is a rimless bottlenecked intermediate cartridge of Soviet origin that was designed during World War II. Due to the worldwide proliferation of the Soviet SKS and AK-47 pattern rifles, as well as RPD and RPK light machine guns, the cartridge is used by both militaries and civilians alike.
Shortly after World War II, the AK-47 was designed, later becoming the world's most widespread military-pattern rifle. The cartridge remained the Soviet standard until the 1970s. It was largely replaced in Soviet service by the 5.45×39mm cartridge, which was introduced with the new AK-74 rifle, and continues in service with the modernized current-issue Russian Armed Forces AK-74M service rifle, as well as the AK-12 rifle. In the 21st century the 7.62×39mm remains a common service rifle chambering, including for newly developed rifles like the AK-15. 

Variants:
	M43: 
	The original Soviet M43 bullets are 123 grain boat-tail bullets with a copper-plated steel jacket, a large steel core, and some lead between the core and the jacket. The cartridge itself consisted of a Berdan-primed, highly tapered (usually steel) case which seats the bullet and contains the powder charge. The taper makes it very easy to feed and extract the round, since there is little contact with the chamber walls until the round is fully seated. This taper is what causes the AK-47 to have distinctively curved magazines 
	(helping to distinguish AK-47s from AK-74s, which feed from a much straighter magazine). While the bullet design has gone through a few redesigns, the cartridge itself remains largely unchanged. The ballistic coefficient (G7 BC) of the M1943 pattern full metal jacket boat bullet is 0.138. The complete solidity of the M43 projectile causes its only drawback—it is very stable, even while traversing tissue. It begins to yaw only after traversing nearly 26 cm (10 in) of tissue. This greatly reduces the potential wounding effectiveness of the projectile against humans.
	M67:
	In the 1960s Yugoslavia experimented with new bullet designs to produce a round with a superior wounding profile, speed, and accuracy to the M43. The M67 projectile is shorter and flatter-based than the M43. This is mainly due to the deletion of the mild steel insert. This has the side effect of shifting the center of gravity rearward in comparison to the M43. This allows the projectile to destabilize nearly 17 cm (6.7 in) earlier in tissue. This causes a pair of large stretch cavities at a depth likely to cause effective wound trauma. 
	When the temporary stretch cavity intersects with the skin at the exit area, a larger exit wound will result, which takes longer to heal. Additionally, when the stretch cavity intersects a stiff organ like the liver, it will cause damage to that organ. However, the wounding potential of M67 is mostly limited to the small permanent wound channel the bullet itself makes, especially when the bullet yaws (tumbles).
	Commercial ammunition:
	Commercial Russian-made 7.62×39mm ammunition, such as those sold under the Wolf Ammunition brand name, are also available in full metal jacket (FMJ), soft-point (SP) and hollow-point (HP) variety.[3] The SP bullets offer improved expansion.
	Type 56: Chinese Mild Steel Core
	Chinese (Type 56) military ammunition (developed in 1956) is a M43 style cartridge with a mild steel core (MSC) and a thin copper or brass jacket. In 1956, the Chinese developed their own 7.62x39mm assault rifle. It is a variant of the Soviet-designed AK-47(specifically Type 3 and AKM) assault rifles. Production started in 1956 at State Factory 66 but was eventually handed over to Norinco, who continues to manufacture the rifle primarily for export. Norinco developed and produced a 7.62x39mm ammunition for the new Chinese Type 56 7.62x39mm rifle. 
	The Chinese ammunition (as well as all other M43 ammunition) is currently banned from importation in the U.S. because U.S. federal law classifies the round as an armor-piercing handgun round. This classification is based on materials and bullet design rather than on empirical ability to penetrate armor. 

https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/7.62%C3%9739mm
</EN>
<DE>
Die Mittelpatrone 7,62 × 39 mm (häufig auch unter der militärischen Bezeichnung Kurzpatrone M 43 geführt) gehörte als Munition zur Ausrüstung der Roten Armee, der Armeen des Warschauer Pakts und der Volksbefreiungsarmee Chinas. Sie wird noch bei den finnischen Streitkräften und den Streitkräften vieler anderer Staaten verwendet. 
Bereits zu Beginn des 20. Jahrhunderts begann in Russland die Entwicklung von Selbstladegewehren, wie zum Beispiel des Fjodorow-Gewehres. Nach dem Ersten Weltkrieg wurde verfügt, dass alle automatischen Waffen die Armeepatrone 7,62 × 54 mm R zu verwenden hatten, die schon während der Regentschaft des Zaren Nikolaus II eingeführt worden war. Dies brachte zahlreiche konstruktionstechnische Probleme mit sich, denn durch ihren markanten Rand war die Patrone für diesen Zweck ungeeignet. 

Bis zum Beginn und noch während des Zweiten Weltkrieges versuchten sich viele sowjetische Konstrukteure an der Aufgabe, eine zuverlässige selbstladende Waffe auf der Grundlage der vorgegebenen Munition zu entwickeln. Das beste Resultat dieser Bemühungen war wohl das Selbstladegewehr SWT-40, das aber nicht völlig überzeugen konnte, was zu einem großen Teil auf die Eigenart der Munition zurückzuführen war. Während des Krieges wurde der Armeeführung bewusst, dass die Mosin-Patrone für die üblichen Gefechtsentfernungen überdimensioniert war, 
jedoch Maschinenpistolen wie die Schpagin PPSch-41 eine zu geringe Reichweite hatten. Den Weg, wie diese Lücke zu füllen war, zeigte eine deutsche Entwicklung: die Kurzpatrone 7,92 × 33 mm, wie sie im Sturmgewehr 44 verwendet wurde. 
Schon im Jahr 1943 wurde die neue Patrone vorgestellt: sie war randlos (was ihre Verwendung in automatischen Waffen begünstigte) und stark konisch (was das Einführen in die Patronenkammer bzw. das Ausziehen aus der Kammer erleichterte). Die erste Waffe auf Grundlage der neuen M 43 erschien bereits ein Jahr darauf mit dem Selbstladekarabiner SKS-45 des Konstrukteurs Sergej Gawrilowitsch Simonow. Die Patrone wurde daraufhin in Waffenprototypen von Michail Timofejewitsch Kalaschnikow verwendet, aus denen später das Sturmgewehr AK-47 entstand. 

Es gibt eine Vielzahl von stärkeren Gewehrpatronen als die M 43 und zweifellos präzisere und weiter reichende Waffen als die AK 47. Was der Kombination aus beiden eine so große Verbreitung verschaffte, war die Art und Weise, wie hierbei mehreren Anforderungen gleichermaßen Rechnung getragen wurde:
    hohe Zuverlässigkeit der AK 47, auch unter widrigen Gefechtsfeldbedingungen
    hohe Feuerrate
    ausreichende Reichweite und Genauigkeit auf mittlere Entfernungen
    Schützen können durch das geringere Gewicht der Patrone eine größere Menge an Munition mitführen
    im Vergleich zu herkömmlichen Infanteriepatronen geringere Schützenbelastung durch geringeren Mündungsknall und Rückstoß

https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/7,62_%C3%97_39_mm
</DE>
<ES>
El 7,62 x 39​ es un cartucho de fusil de origen soviético, usado en la actualidad y manufacturado por países del antiguo bloque soviético. 
El 7,62 x 39 fue diseñado durante la Segunda Guerra Mundial y utilizado por la carabina SKS. El cartucho fue influido por una variedad de productos extranjeros, especialmente el cartucho experimental alemán de preguerra GeCo 7,75 x 39 mm,​ y posiblemente por el 7,92 x 33 Kurz alemán (kurz significa corto en alemán). Más tarde fue creado para usar este cartucho el fusil de asalto más conocido del mundo: el AK-47. El cartucho mantuvo la carga soviética estándar hasta los años setenta, y es todavía por lejos el cartucho más utilizado en el mundo. 
Su reemplazo, el 5,45 × 39 mm es igual de poderoso debido a su peculiar (y de dudosa legalidad internacional) construcción y es más controlable en fuego automático (debido a su bajo retroceso), pero más caro. Del cambio fue en parte responsable el Ejército de Estados Unidos al cambiar su cartuchería 7,62 × 51 OTAN a 5,56 x 45 OTAN. 

Al contrario del 7,62 x 51 OTAN, el 7,62 x 39 ruso es de menor potencia, lo que significa también menor alcance y letalidad, pero también menos peso, retroceso y tamaño. Esto se nota especialmente en fuego a ráfagas. Además, su capacidad lesiva a distancias habituales de combate es normalmente adecuada. Cuando la OTAN se dio cuenta de estas ventajas, adoptó el calibre 5,56 x 45 OTAN. Más pequeño y ligero que el ruso, pero de velocidad muy alta que lo compensaba (950 m/s del 5,56 mm frente a los 715 del 7,62 mm ruso). 
Las prestaciones de letalidad de los dos cartuchos son pues más o menos similares. Aunque el diseño ruso parece desempeñarse mejor en armas con cañones cortos, pues la pérdida de velocidad que esto supone no le afecta tanto. Sin embargo, es menos preciso que el calibre OTAN.​ Aunque estas diferencias son menores. La munición estándar militar rusa de 7,62 mm dispara una bala de 8 gramos (123 grains) a 715 m/s. 

https://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/7,62_%C3%97_39_mm
</ES>
<FR>
La munition intermédiaire de 7,62 × 39 mm M43 (pour Modèle 1943) connaît depuis les années 1950 une diffusion mondiale car elle est tirée par le célèbre et commun fusil d'assaut AK-47.
Il s'agit d'une munition soviétique composée d'une balle d'un calibre de 7,62 mm, montée sur un étui de 39 mm de longueur d’où la dénomination 7,62 × 39 mm.
Sa principale caractéristique, outre d'équiper beaucoup d'opérateurs sans affiliation nationale (par exemple des groupuscules terroristes), par la facilité d'obtention d'un Avtomat Kalashnikova modèle 47, est sa grande capacité de pénétration. Cela permet ainsi de passer outre les soft covers, abris disséminés qu'offre une zone de combat urbaine, telle une tôle en métal, un mur de briques ou une légère épaisseur de béton, 
chose difficilement faisable avec les autres munitions répandues, comme la 5,56 × 45 mm, munition standard des forces de l'OTAN, ou la 5,45 × 39 mm M74, émulation soviétique de cette munition atlantique. On trouve aujourd'hui plus facilement des munitions provenant des ex-membres du pacte de Varsovie, les arsenaux russes Izhmash et Tula alimentant essentiellement le marché interne. 

Développé et introduit pour un usage militaire par l'Union soviétique en 1943, le 7,62 × 39 mm est la cartouche de fusil d'assaut la plus populaire au monde. Initialement chambrée pour la carabine SKS, elle s'est inspirée des calibres intermédiaires développés par les Allemands comme la munition expérimentale d'avant-guerre 7,75 × 39 mm et probablement aussi la 7,92 mm kurz.
La 7,62 mm M43 possède une balle moins lourde et une charge de poudre moins puissante que les munitions de fusils similaires. Cette puissance intermédiaire lui permet d'avoir une meilleure portée qu'une munition d'arme de poing mise en œuvre dans les pistolets mitrailleurs tout en demeurant moins encombrante et développant moins de recul que les munitions de fusil. Dès lors, elle peut être mise en œuvre par des mécanismes de rechargement semi-automatique ou automatique plus légers tout en demeurant contrôlables par le tireur. 
En contrepartie, la portée est réduite, mais elle permet toutefois de tirer de 200 à 300 mètres, une distance au-delà de laquelle les engagements effectivement constatés sur le terrain sont rares.
Même si l'Union soviétique a suivi l'exemple de l'OTAN en adoptant une cartouche de petit calibre de 5,45 × 39 mm, le 7,62 × 39 mm demeure une munition très répandue. D'abord parce qu'un grand nombre d'armes en circulation fait qu'un laps de temps important va s'écouler avant que l'on ne voie le dernier fusil de guerre de ce calibre, ensuite parce que le faible calibre de la 5,45 × 39 mm en limite le pouvoir vulnérant et fait regretter à certains militaires la traditionnelle cartouche de 7,62 × 39 mm. Le 7,62 × 39 mm est aussi la cartouche parente du .220 Russian, du .22PPC et du 6 mm PPC.
Outre les armes produites par les pays de l'ex-pacte de Varsovie, des armes militaires récentes à destination des troupes d'élite, produites par des pays membres de l'OTAN, chambrent la 7,62 × 39 mm afin de leur permettre de se ravitailler lorsqu'elles opèrent en territoire ennemi. 

https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/7,62_%C3%97_39_mm_M43
</FR>
</loc>