<loc>
<IT>
Giovanissima cartuccia, nata nel 1980 dalla modifica del più famoso bossolo del .308 Win. Nulla di nuovo, già nel '53 e nel '63 furono prodotte munizioni con le stesse caratteristiche, la 7-08 però doveva camerare le azioni corte delle carabine semiauto. Nata quindi esclusivamente per la caccia fu adattata alle armi semiauto e per tiri molto lunghi, oltre i 300 mt. possiede ancora più energia delle consorelle, cosi la 7-08 ha avuto grande successo tra i cacciatori di tutto il mondo. 

http://www.tiropratico.com/ammunition/pagine/7-08rem.html
</IT>
<EN>
The 7mm-08 Remington is a rifle cartridge that is almost a direct copy of a wildcat cartridge developed around 1958 known as the 7mm/308. As these names would suggest, it is the .308 Winchester case necked down to accept 7 mm (.284) bullets with a small increase in case length. Of cartridges based upon the .308, it is the second most popular behind only the .243 Winchester. However, the .308 is more popular than both. 
In 1980, the Remington Arms company popularized the cartridge by applying its own name and offering it as a chambering for their Model 788 and Model 700 rifles, along with a limited-run series within their Model 7600 pump-action rifles during the early 2000s. 
The popularity of the cartridge means there is a fairly wide selection of factory loads, making it a choice even for those who do not handload. Bullets weighing from 100 to 195 grains are available. Bullets in the 130-150gr range will suit most hunting applications while long range shooters will opt for the heavier bullets to take advantage of their higher ballistic coefficients. Depending on construction, bullets of 154 to 195gr can also be used in loads suitable for medium and larger game or target purposes. Medium burning rifle powders usually work best in the 7mm-08. 

https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/7mm-08_Remington
</EN>
<DE>N/A</DE>
<ES>N/A</ES>
<FR>
Le 7mm-08 Remington est une munition de carabine qui est presque une copie directe d'une cartouche développée vers 1958, connu comme le 7mm/308 . Comme l'indique son nom, elle est issue d'une douille de calibre .308 Winchester mais son col a été réduit pour accepter un projectile de 7mm (.284) avec une légère augmentation de la longueur de l'étui. De toutes les cartouches basés sur la .308, c'est le troisième plus populaire, 
derrière le .308 lui-même et la .243 Winchester. En 1980, la "Remington Arms company" a popularisé la cartouche en appliquant son propre nom afin d'offrir ce calibre à ces carabines 788 et 700. 
Balistique indicative:
    Masse de la balle : de 6,5 à 11,6g (100 à 180 grains)
    Vitesse 9g (140 grains)
        initiale : 850m/s
    Énergie
        initiale : 3304J

https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/7_mm-08_Remington
</FR>
</loc>