<loc>
<IT>
Prodotta nel 1984 dalla Winchester su progetto di Ken Waters che mirava a migliorare il munizionamento per le carabine a leva, limitate dai problemi posti dai caricatori tubolari, è sicuramente meglio della consorella .30-30 e ha prestazioni migliori ma solo in canne estremamente lunghe. I cacciatori però rimangono fedeli alle corte canne delle carabine a leva classiche, in questi casi le due munizioni si eguagliano, questo ha limitato la diffusione di questa munizione. 

http://www.tiropratico.com/ammunition/pagine/7-30waters.html
</IT>
<EN>
The 7-30 Waters cartridge was originally a wildcat cartridge developed by author Ken Waters in 1976 to give better performance to lever-action rifle shooters than the parent .30-30 Winchester cartridge, by providing a higher velocity and flatter trajectory with a smaller, lighter bullet. By 1984, Winchester introduced a Model 94 rifle chambered for the 7-30 Waters, establishing it as a commercial cartridge. In 1986, Thompson/Center began chambering 10-inch, 14-inch, and 20-inch Contender barrels for the cartridge.
A review of the 7-08 Rem. (a .308 Win. case necked down to 7mm), explains the design of the cartridge with the following:

    Anything a 7mm can do, a .30 caliber of comparable sectional density and ballistic coefficient can also do. The catch is, in order to send a .30-caliber slug over a trajectory as flat as that 7mm bullet, about 20 percent more recoil is going to be generated. . . . [A bullet in] 7mm produces clearly superior downrange performance in terms of delivered energy and trajectory at any given recoil level [compared to a bullet in .30 caliber].

There are two primary reasons a 7mm recoils less than an comparably effective .30 cal. cartridge: (1) to match the 7mm's ballistic coefficient requires a significantly heavier .30 cal bullet; and (2) to drive that heavier .30 cal bullet at similar velocities (for kinetic energy and wind resistance ("time-to-target")), requires more powder. This combination of heavier bullets with heavier powder charges significantly increases the recoil of the .30 caliber.
The .30-30 Winchester is typically limited to short ranges, primarily because of the relatively small case capacity and the 150-grain and 170-grain bullet weights. To compensate for this, Waters necked the cartridge down to use a 7mm bullet (.284 inches), rather than the original .308 caliber (7.62 mm) bullet. Because it was designed to function in lever-action rifles, the 7-30 maintained the same low working pressure, yet Waters' original design fired a lighter bullet (139 grains) at a higher velocity (2600 ft/s).
A typical .30-30 factory load fires a 150-grain bullet at 2390 ft/s, while the current 7-30 factory load fires a 120-grain bullet at 2700 ft/s. Muzzle energy is just over 1900 ft-lbs for both of these loads, but the lighter weight 7mm bullet has a higher velocity and flatter trajectory. 

https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/7-30_Waters
</EN>
<DE>N/A</DE>
<ES>N/A</ES>
<FR>N/A</FR>
</loc>