<loc>
<IT>
La 7mm. Mauser prodotta dal 1892 per i fucili d'ordinanza Mauser, fu adottata anche da Spagna e Belgio e in seguito anche dal Messico e altri stati sud Americani. Remington e Winchester camerarono alcuni modelli dei loro fucili in questo calibro. Ottima catuccia sia in veste militare sia in veste da caccia continua a mantenere il suo successo tutt'ora se pur meno potente del .270 Win. In America il successo fu consegnato grazie al grande numero di fucili recuperati dal secondo conflitto mondile in Europa. 
La RWS produce ancora questa munizione per la caccia con grande successo. Esiste anche un modello della stessa cartuccia con bossolo flangiato per armi basculanti.

http://www.tiropratico.com/ammunition/pagine/7x57Mauser.html
</IT>
<EN>
The 7×57mm Mauser (designated as the 7mm Mauser or 7×57mm by the SAAMI and 7 × 57 by the C.I.P. is a first-generation smokeless powder rimless bottlenecked rifle cartridge. It is known as .275 Rigby in the United Kingdom. It was developed by Paul Mauser of the Mauser company in 1892 and adopted as a military cartridge by Spain in 1893. It was subsequently adopted by several other countries as the standard military cartridge, and although now obsolete as a military cartridge, it remains in widespread international use as a sporting round. 
Many sporting rifles in this calibre were made by British riflemakers, among whom John Rigby was prominent; and, catering for the British preference for calibres to be designated in inches, Rigby called this chambering the .275 bore after the measurement of a 7 mm rifle's bore across the lands.
Paul Mauser visited the Kingdom of Spain in 1892 after the delivery of trial rifles in 1891 and brought with him a new rifle designed to use a new cartridge of 7 mm caliber. He had developed this cartridge for use with the then-new smokeless propellant, introduced as Poudre B in the 1886 pattern 8mm Lebel, which started a military rifle ammunition revolution. At the time of its development 7×57mm Mauser was a high-performance smokeless-powder cartridge. 
The Mauser Model 1892 rifle turned out to be a transitional design that was manufactured in limited numbers for the Spanish Army. It was quickly improved to the Mauser Model 1893 featuring a new internal box magazine where the cartridges were stored in a staggered column. The Spaniards were so impressed with the Mauser Model 1892 and 1893 rifles and their new 7×57mm Mauser cartridge that they not only ordered rifles and ammunition with Mauser, but also awarded him the Grand Cross of the Spanish Military Order of Merit, the highest decoration Mauser ever received.

https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/7%C3%9757mm_Mauser
</EN>
<DE>
Die 7 × 57 mm ist eine Gewehrpatrone. Dabei steht die 7 für das Kaliber und die 57 für die Länge der Hülse (jeweils in mm).
Die Militärpatrone 7 × 57 mm wurde, aufbauend auf der Hülse M/88, 1892 von Mauser konstruiert. Aufgrund ihrer für damalige Verhältnisse sehr guten Präzision und des geringen Rückstoßes wurde sie schnell von Spanien, sowie mittel- und südamerikanischen Staaten als Militärpatrone in Verbindung mit dem Mauser-Gewehr eingeführt.
Im Jahre 1893 wurde die 7 × 57 mm auch als Jagdpatrone vorgestellt. Wiederum verhalf die Präzision und vor allem der geringe Rückstoß der 7 × 57 zu einer schnellen und weiten Verbreitung. Später lief ihr jedoch die rasantere 7 × 64 mm von Wilhelm Brenneke den Rang ab. Trotzdem findet die 7 × 57 mm heute noch zahlreiche Verwendung als Jagdpatrone. In den USA ist sie unter der Bezeichnung 7 mm Mauser bekannt.
Für die Verwendung in Kipplaufwaffen ist auch eine Randpatrone mit der Bezeichnung 7 × 57 R erhältlich. 

https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/7_%C3%97_57_mm
</DE>
<ES>
El cartucho 7 × 57 mm, también conocido como 7 mm Mauser, 7 × 57 mm Mauser, 7 mm Mauser Español en los Estados Unidos y .275 Rigby en el Reino Unido, fue desarrollado por Paul Mauser, de la compañía Mauser, en 1892 y adoptado por España como cartucho militar en 1893.​ Fue consecuentemente adoptado como cartucho militar estándar por varios países. Se le reconoce como un hito en el diseño de cartuchos modernos y, aunque obsoleto como cartucho militar, tiene un amplio empleo a nivel internacional como cartucho de cacería. 
El 7 x 57 ha sido meritoriamente descrito como "el deleite de un experto en balística". Muchos fusiles de cacería en este calibre fueron fabricados por armeros británicos, siendo John Rigby el más conocido entre estos; debido a la usanza británica de nombrar los calibres en pulgadas, Rigby denominó a este calibre como .275 Rigby tras medir el espacio entre las estrías del ánima del cañón de un fusil calibre 7 mm. El ejército español adoptó un nuevo fusil Mauser en 1893. 
Este empleaba un cartucho de percusión central cargado con pólvora sin humo y que montaba una bala con un diámetro nominal de 7 mm (0.275 pulgadas), con un casquillo de 57 mm de largo - de ahí los nombres de "7x57mm Mauser" y "7x57mm Mauser Español". La bala pesaba 11 gramos (175 granos) y tenía una velocidad en boca de aproximadamente 700 metros/segundo (2300 pies/segundo). Para finales del siglo XIX, estas características eran impresionantes. 
El cambio en el modelo de la bala, de una con punta redonda a una puntiaguda, fue en parte responsable del desempeño del cartucho al reducir la resistencia del aire en las distancias de combate habituales. 

https://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/7_%C3%97_57_mm_Mauser
</ES>
<FR>
La cartouche pour fusil 7 × 57 mm Mauser fut conçue par Mauser pour son Gewehr 93. Cette munition militaire fut réglementaire en Amérique latine (Brésil, Chili, Colombie, Costa Rica, Cuba, Guatemala, Honduras, Mexique, Nicaragua, Salvador, Uruguay et Venezuela) et en Europe (Espagne, France (Grande Guerre) et Serbie). Son appellation métrique est 7 × 57 mm. Elle est chargée avec de la poudre sans fumée. Les balles espagnoles étaient à bout arrondi puis pointu. Elle est encore utilisée à la chasse en Allemagne et en Autriche. 
Dimensions:
    Diamètre réel de la balle : 7,24 mm
    Longueur de l'étui : 57 mm
    Longueur de la cartouche : 78 mm
    Masse
        balle : 11,2 g
        charge : 2,45 g

https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/7_%C3%97_57_mm_Mauser
</FR>
</loc>