<loc>
<IT>N/A</IT>
<EN>
The 8×58mmR Danish Krag also known as the 8×58mmRD is a late 19th-century rimmed centerfire military rifle cartridge similar to other early smokeless powder designs. It was briefly adopted by Norway and Sweden and remained the standard Danish service rifle cartridge from 1889 until 1945.
The cartridge was developed in Denmark in 1888 using round-nosed bullets with 4 grams (62 gr) of gunpowder, and adopted the following year by Denmark in the Krag–Jørgensen M89 rifle. Sweden implemented a major arsenal rebuilding of Remington Rolling Block rifles for the 8×58mmR, and Norway experimentally compared 8×58mmR Remington Rolling Block conversions to the Jarmann M1884. Its service in Sweden was very brief, though, since the 6.5×55mm was developed by Sweden and Norway in 1891, formally approved in 1893, 
and entered service in the Norwegian Krag–Jørgensen rifle in 1894, and in the Swedish Mauser carbine in 1894 and rifle in 1896. Denmark modernized military loading of the 8×58mmR in 1908 using smokeless powder with spitzer bullets; and Danish troops were still armed with the 8×58mmR when Germany invaded in 1940.
Surplus military rifles have been used for hunting; and ammunition was manufactured in Otterup and by Norma Precision after World War II. Documentation is scarce for the design pressure specifications of these surplus firearms. Although modern weapons may have been designed for smokeless powder loadings, their similarity to arms designed for gunpowder loadings causes uncertainty about the safety of firing modern cartridges in weapons lacking proof test documentation.

https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/8%C3%9758mmR_Danish_Krag
</EN>
<DE>
Die Patrone 8 × 58 mm R wurde 1890 als Munition des Infanteriegewehres Krag-Jörgensen 1889 in Dänemark eingeführt. Es wurde ein Kupfermantel-Rundkopfgeschoss mit Bleikern verwendet. 1892 erfolgte die Modifikation der Patronen mit einem Kupfer-Nickel-Mantel. Ab 1909 wurde ein Spitzgeschoss eingeführt. Da die Patrone bereits während des Zweiten Weltkrieges veraltet war, wurde sie nach 1945 in Dänemark eingestellt. 

https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/8_%C3%97_58_mm_R
</DE>
<ES>N/A</ES>
<FR>N/A</FR>
</loc>