<loc>
<IT>N/A</IT>
<EN>
It is based on the Soviet 7.62×39 mm round, but with the neck expanded to fit a 9.3mm bullet. Initial design of the cartridge began in the 1940s by a team of 27 unknown members. Final design was completed by N. Zabelin, L. Dvoryaninova and Y. Frolov of the TsNIITochMash in the 1980s. The intent was to create a subsonic cartridge for suppressed firearms for special forces units that had more power, range and penetration than pistol cartridges usually used in such weapons. 
The commercial wolf ammunition bullet weighs 276 grain, or 18 grams, a little more than double that of the normal 123 gr 7.62×39 mm round, and has only subsonic muzzle velocity. This reduced velocity does not produce a sonic boom, and also limits the muzzle energy and effective range of a weapon when compared to high velocity rounds normally used in (non-suppressed) rifles. The round has an optimistic effective lethal range of 400 to 530 meters and a maximum penetration of up to 10 mm of steel. Like the 5.45×39mm cartridge, 
9×39mm SP-5 features an airpocket in the tip, which increases its tendency to yaw or "keyhole" upon impact, thus increasing soft tissue damage in human targets, and also the armor-piercing SP6 cartridge are more effective against light armored, vehicle, or light barrier targets, although neither of those are imported into the USA. 
Variants:
SP-5 (7N8) - The SP-5 (СП-5) (SP: Spetsialnyj Patron; "special cartridge") was developed by Nikolai Zabelin. It is a conventional lead core FMJ bullet, developed for accuracy.
SP-5UZ - The SP-5UZ (СП5-УЗ) is an SP-5 variant with an increased charge intended for a factory-specific strength testing of the weapons.
SP-6 (7N9) - The SP-6 (СП-6) was developed by Yuri Frolov. It has a hardened metal armor-piercing core. It can penetrate 2 mm (0.079 in) of steel at 500 meters or 6 mm (0.24 in) of steel, 2.8 mm (0.11 in) of titanium or 30 layers of Kevlar at 200 meters. At 100 meters it penetrates 8 mm (0.31 in) of steel, while retaining enough power to inflict damage to a soft target behind it.
SP-6UCh - The SP-6Uch (СП-6Уч) is an SP-6 variant intended for training.
PAB-9 (7N12) - The SP-6's bullet is expensive, so an attempt was made to make a lower-cost version of the cartridge. The PAB-9 (ПАБ-9) used a stamped rather than machined steel core. It sacrificed too much performance to be usable. As of 2011, its usage is prohibited.
SPP - The SPP (СПП) (SPP: Snaiperskie Povishennaya Probivaemost; "sniper - increased penetration") is a sniper round with increased penetration.
BP - The BP (БП) (BP: Broneboin'ie Pulya; "armor-piercing bullet") is an armor-piercing round. 

https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/9%C3%9739mm
</EN>
<DE>
Die 9 × 39 mm ist eine sowjetische Unterschall-Mittelpatrone, die in schallgedämpften Spezialwaffen wie dem Wintores-Scharfschützengewehr, dem Sturmgewehr AS Wal oder der OZ-14 Grosa verwendet wird. Das Geschoss ist im Verhältnis zum Durchmesser sehr lang, weshalb trotz der Geschossgeschwindigkeit unterhalb der Schallmauer eine vergleichsweise hohe Durchschlagsleistung und gestreckte Flugbahn erreicht wird. 
Die Patrone wurde aus der 7,62×39-mm-Patrone M43 entwickelt. Dazu wurde die Hülse der M43 auf 9 mm aufgeweitet, die übrigen Dimensionen blieben unverändert. Die Geschosse sind Neuentwicklungen.  Die Patrone wurde gezielt auf Unterschallgeschwindigkeit des Projektils hin entwickelt, um den Überschallknall zu vermeiden. Der verbleibende Mündungsknall lässt sich mit einem Schalldämpfer stark vermindern. 
Typen:
    SP-5 (GRAU-Index 7N8, russisch СП-5): Spezialnij Patron, „Spezialpatrone“. Präzisionsmunition mit Bleikern-Vollmantelgeschoß.
    SP-5US (russisch СП5-УЗ): Versuchsvariante der SP-5 mit verstärkter Ladung.
    SP-6 (GRAU-Index 7N9, russisch СП-6): Panzerbrechende Patrone mit Stahlkern. Durchschlagsleistung 6 mm Stahl oder 2,8 mm Titan bzw. 30 Lagen Kevlar auf 200 Meter.
    SP-6U (russisch СП-6УЧ): Trainingsvariante mit den ballistischen Eigenschaften der SP-6.
    PAB-9 (GRAU-Index 7N12, russisch ПАБ-9): Vereinfachte kostengünstige Variante der SP-6, die aufgrund der damit verbundenen Nachteile wie verringerte Präzision und erhöhter Rohrverschleiß nicht mehr produziert wird.
    SPP (russisch СПП): Präzisionsmunition mit erhöhter Durchschlagsleistung.
    BP (russisch БП): Panzerbrechende Patrone.

https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/9_%C3%97_39_mm
</DE>
<ES>
El 9 × 39 mm es un cartucho de fusil soviético/ruso. Está basado en el cartucho soviético 7,62 x 39, pero con un cuello ampliado para dar cabida a una bala de 9 mm. 
El cartucho fue diseñado por N. Zabelin, L. Dvoryaninova y Y. Frolov de la TsNIITochMash en la década de 1980. La intención era crear un cartucho subsónico para armas de fuego con supresor de sonido para unidades de fuerzas especiales que tuviera más poder, rango y penetración que otros cartuchos. Al igual que el cartucho de 5,45 x 39, el 9 x 39 SP-5 tiene una bolsa de aire en la punta, que mejora enormemente su capacidad de orientación.
Variantes
    SP-5 (7N8): El SP-5 (СП-5) (SP: Patrón Spetsialnyj, "Cartucho Especial") fue desarrollado por Nikolai Zabelin. Se trata de un cartucho que monta una bala encamisada (FMJ) convencional con núcleo de plomo, pero desarrollado para la precisión.
    SP-5UZ: El SP-5UZ (СП5-УЗ) es una variante del SP-5, con carga propulsora incrementada, destinado a probar la resistencia especifica del cañón y otras piezas de las armas.
    SP-6 (7N9): El SP-6 (СП-6) fue desarrollado por Yuri Frolov. Cuenta con un núcleo antiblindaje de metal templado, que puede penetrar 2 mm de acero a 500 metros, 2,8 mm de titanio o 30 capas de Kevlar a 200 metros. A 100 metros penetra 8 mm de acero, mientras que conserva la energía suficiente para neutralizar un soldado detrás de él.
    SP-6UCh: El SP-6UCh (СП-6УЧ) es una variante del SP-6 usado para entrenamiento.
    PAB-9 (7N12): La bala del SP-6 es cara, por lo que se hizo un intento de hacer una versión de menor costo del cartucho. En la bala de PAB-9 (ПАБ-9) se utilizó un núcleo de acero estampado en lugar de uno de acero mecanizado. Se sacrificó demasiado su rendimiento para ser utilizable. Su uso está prohibido a partir de 2011.
    SPP: El SPP (СПП) (SPP: Snaiperskie Povishennaya Probivaemost, "francotirador-mayor penetración") es una cartucho de francotirador con carga propulsora incrementada y una mayor penetración.
    BP: El BP (БП) (TA: Broneboin'ie Pulya, "Bala antiblindaje") es un cartucho antiblindaje, con bala perforante de punta hueca.

https://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/9_%C3%97_39_mm
</ES>
<FR>
La cartouche russe de 9x39 mm fut créée dans les années 1980 (à l'époque soviétique) afin de fournir aux Spetsnaz une munition pour arme automatique dotée d'un pouvoir plus vulnérant que celle de 7.62x39 mm subsonique (nommée 7.62x39 US, pour Umenshennaya Skorost, « Basse Vitesse ») utilisée dans des variantes d'AK-47/AKM équipées de silencieux détachables, la faible vélocité diminuant fortement la puissance d'arrêt de la balle.
Une nouvelle munition fut extrapolée à partir de la 7.62x39 mm: le projectile fut élargi, passant d'un diamètre de 7.62 à 9 mm, alourdi et profilé. Initialement, deux variantes furent créées :
    La cartouche SP-5, à balle standard à noyau de plomb pour tirs de précision,
    La cartouche SP-6, à noyau d'acier durci, perforante.

Deux armes (très similaires) furent créées spécifiquement pour cette nouvelle munition :
    Le fusil de précision VSS Vintorez
    Le fusil d'assaut AS Val

Ces deux fusils sont basés sur le principe de l'AK-47 et dotés d'un silencieux intégral (tenant lieu de canon), celui-ci permet de rendre imperceptible la détonation à une distance de 50 m. La portée effective de ces armes ne dépasse pas 400 m (à titre de comparaison, le Dragunov SVD permet des tirs deux fois plus longs).
Depuis la chute de l'URSS, d'autres armes chambrant la 9x39 mm ont fait leur apparition en Russie afin de tirer parti du fort pouvoir d'arrêt de la munition ; aucun de ces fusils n'est en effet équipé de silencieux de manière permanente :
    L'OTs-12 "Tiss", à la production confidentielle, s'apparentant à un AKS-74U,
    L'OTs-14-4A "Groza", fusil d'assaut bullpup modulaire basé sur l'AKS-74U,
    Le SR-3, SR-3M "Vihr", qui peut se résumer à un AS Val sans silencieux. Ce fusil d'assaut compact à forte puissance d'arrêt est utilisé par le FSO, le FSB (ex-KGB) et le MVD,
    Le 9A-91 est une version simplifiée (donc moins chère) du SR3 utilisée par le MVD,
    Le VSK-94 est au 9A-91 ce que le Vintorez est au Val ; il est utilisé par différents services de police russe,
    L'AK-9, dernier né de la famille Kalashnikov.

https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/9_%C3%97_39_mm_russe
</FR>
</loc>